<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02030808</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Anesth-Dec13(2)</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02030808</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Remifentanil Without Muscle Relaxant for Thoracotomy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Target-Controlled Infusion of Remifentanil Without Muscle Relaxant Allows Acceptable Surgical Conditions During Thoracotomy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dammam University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dammam University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Although the administration of muscle relaxation is essential standard of care for thoracic
      procedures, it could cause long-reversal times and postoperative residual curarization (PORC)
      increasing length of post-anesthesia care unit (PACU) stay and hospital costs. Sugammadex
      offers new perspectives to reduce the incidence of PORC. Unfortunately it is not available in
      many countries because of its significantly high cost. We hypothesized that the use of
      target-controlled remifentanil infusion (TCI) with the non-muscle relaxant (NMR) would be
      associated with comparable surgical conditions and reduced total costs compared with the use
      of neuromuscular blockers during thoracotomy.

      After ethical approval, 66 patients scheduled for elective thoracotomy under sevoflurane
      anesthesia with TCI remifentanil will be included in this prospective, randomized,
      single-blind, controlled study.

      Patients will be randomly assigned to receive cisatracurium or saline (n = 33 for each group)
      throughout the procedure. Laryngoscopy and intubating conditions, intraoperative modified
      thoracic surgery rating scale (Table below), incidence of light anesthesia, and use of
      vasopressors and anesthetics, clinical recovery, incidence of PORC, PACU and hospital stays,
      and total costs will be recorded.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Administration of muscle relaxation is essential standard of care in thoracic surgery as it
      causes an improvement of surgical conditions. The concept of &quot;Fast-track thoracic anesthesia&quot;
      requires the use of either short or intermediate-acting nondepolarising neuromuscular
      blocking drugs, to provide a sufficient neuromuscular blockade during surgery and to restore
      the normal neuromuscular transmission immediately at the end of surgery.1

      However, long-reversal times and postoperative residual curarization (PORC) are still a
      problem in 30%-60% of the anesthetized patients even with the use of new intermediate-acting
      neuromuscular blockers.2-3 PORC could cause aspiration of the lungs and respiratory failure4
      after thoracic surgery that may prolong the post anesthesia care unit (PACU) and hospital
      stays.

      Although, sugammadex, a modified gamma-cyclodextrin, offers new perspectives to reduce the
      incidence of PORC,4 it is not available in many countries because of its significantly high
      cost.5

      Therefore, in fast-track cardiac surgery, it seems unnecessary to maintain paralysis by
      repetitive bolus injection or continuous infusion of neuromuscular blockers with overall
      surgeons' satisfaction.6

      The use of remifentanil without muscle relaxants provides excellent intubating conditions and
      short recovery duration.7 The effective concentration range of remifentanil for tracheal
      intubation without muscle relaxant is 4.5-5.5 ng/ml.8 The use of non-muscle relaxant (NMR)
      anesthetic techniques using remifentanil with either propofol or sevoflurane allows early
      extubation after trans-sternal or video-assisted thymectomy in myasthenic patients.9-10

      The use of NMR technique on the surgical conditions during thoracotomy in patients without
      neuromuscular diseases has not yet been studied.

      We hypothesizes that the use of NMR technique during thoracotomy will be associated with
      comparable surgical conditions with the standard use of neuromuscular blockers.

      The attending anesthesiologist is not blinded. All patients will be premedicated with 1-2 mg
      oral lorazepam the night before surgery.

      In all patients, standard monitors, and state and response entropy (SE and RE, respectively)
      will be applied. Neuromuscular blockade is measured with a train-of-four (TOF) (Datex-Ohmeda
      Division, Instrumentarium Corporation, Helsinki, Finland). The forearm is immobilized to
      prevent interfering movements. The ulnar nerve will be stimulated supramaximally at the wrist
      with a TOF stimuli (60 mA for 200 μsec) at 15-sec intervals. Baseline twitch amplitude is
      established after induction of anesthesia. TOF ratio is recorded as ratio between the fourth
      and the first twitch (T4/T1).

      The radial artery is catheterized. Normothermia is maintained by using forced-air warming
      blankets. A thoracic epidural or paravertebral catheter is inserted but no local anesthetics
      are infused during the study to avoid their effects on the study outcomes.

      Anesthetic technique is standardized in all studied patients. Anesthesiologists who give the
      anesthetic will not be involved in the collection of outcome data.

      After preoxygenation, anesthesia is induced using propofol 1.5-3 mg/kg and target-controlled
      infusion (TCI) of remifentanil at an effect-site concentration (Ce) of 4 ng/mL using the TCI
      system (Injectomat® TIVA Agilia, Fresenius Kabi, France), to achieve the SE values below 50
      and the difference between RE and SE below 10 and the mean arterial blood pressure (MAP) and
      heart rate are &lt;20% of the baseline values. When the SE is &gt;50 and the RE-SE difference is
      &gt;10, and the MAP and heart rate are &gt;20%, propofol 0.5 mg/kg is administered followed with
      gradual increases in remifentanil Ce by 0.5 ng/mL with a maximum Ce of 6 ng/ml.

      Anesthesia is maintained with 0.7-1.5 minimum alveolar concentration (MAC) of sevoflurane to
      maintain the SE values below 50 and the difference between RE and SE below 10.

      Remifentanil Ce will be increased by 0.5 ng/mL when the SE values are &gt; 50, the difference
      between RE and SE &gt;10, and the MAP and heart rate are &gt;20% of the baseline values despite a
      target sevoflurane MAC ≥ 1.5.

      When the SE is &lt;50 and the RE-SE difference is &lt;10, the sevoflurane MAC will be gradually
      decreased to a minimum of 0.7, followed with gradual decreases in remifentanil Ce by 0.5
      ng/mL with a minimum Ce of 1.5 ng/ml.

      Light anesthesia is defined as an episode with SE values that exceeds 50 and/or MAP and HR
      values that exceeds the baseline by 20% and that lasted for more than 3 consecutive min.

      Patients' two lungs (TLV) are mechanically ventilated with fraction of inspired oxygen (FiO2)
      of 0.4 in air, tidal volume (VT) of 8 mL/kg, inspiratory to expiratory (I: E) ratio of 1:2.5
      and PEEP of 5 cm H2O, fresh gas flow (FGF) of 1.5-1.7 l/min, and respiratory rate adjusted to
      achieve a PaCO2 of 35-45 mm Hg.

      After pleurotomy, the patient's dependent lung is ventilated with a TV of 6 mL/kg and FiO2,
      I: E ratio, PEEP, FGF, and respiratory rate, are maintained as during TLV and the lumen of
      the nondependent lung is left open to air.

      Hemodynamic control is standardized according to the authors' protocol.

      During surgery, the authors will administer Lactated Ringer's solution at a rate of 2
      mL/kg/h. If MAP drops down to 60 mmHg, 250 mL of plasma protein fraction 5% will be
      administered, and, if this is not enough, repeated doses of intravenous of ephedrine 5 mg or
      norepinephrine 5 µg, will be administered to maintain urine output to be equal or greater
      than 0.5 ml/kg/hour. A hemoglobin concentration of 8 g/dL or greater is compensated with red
      blood cell concentrates.

      All surgical procedures will be performed by the same surgeons who are blinded for the study.

      In the case of clinically unacceptable laryngoscopy and intubating conditions, poor or
      extremely poor surgical conditions, or a sudden deterioration of surgical conditions despite
      the SE values below 50, the difference between RE and SE &lt; 10, the MAP and heart rate are
      &lt;20% of the baseline values, cisatracurium is administered in a bolus dose of 0.1 mg/kg.

      At the end of surgery, the nondependent lung is re-expanded, TLV is resumed as before
      surgery. The remifentanil and sevoflurane will be discontinued after chest closure and skin
      closure (T0), respectively. In the Muscle Relaxant group, during skin closure, when the TOF
      ratio ranged between 0.3 and 0.5, the neuromuscular blockade is antagonized with 50 µg/kg
      neostigmine and 10 µg/kg glycopyrrolate.

      Tracheal extubation will be performed immediately when all extubation criteria were achieved
      (TOF ratio ≥ 0.9, spontaneous ventilation, the ability to follow verbal commands, eyes
      opening, head lift ≥ 5 s, and hand grip).

      A pilot study showed that the proportion of the surgeons who rated their satisfaction with
      surgical conditions as an excellent (Score 4) in anesthetized patients with cisatracurium was
      92.5%. A priori power analysis indicated that a sample size of 30 patients was sufficiently
      large to detect a 30% difference in the proportion of the excellent operative conditions,
      during the use of NMRT, a type-I error of 0.05 and a power of 90%. We added more patients
      (10%) for a final sample size of 33 patients to compensate patients dropping out during the
      study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Modified surgical rating scale</measure>
    <time_frame>for 3 hours after start of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>A four-point ordinal scale adopted from the surgical rating scale of Martini et al.,ranging from 1 (extremely poor conditions) to 4 (optimal conditions).
Extremely poor (Score 1) indicates that the surgeon is unable to work because of coughing, bucking, diaphragmatic contractions or movements, or the inability to spread or approximate the ribs during chest opening and closure, respectively, because of inadequate muscle relaxation;
poor (Score 2) indicates that there is a visible field, but the surgeon is severely hampered by continuous muscle contractions, spontaneous movements of the surgical lung, or both that could cause hazard of tissue damage;
good (Score 3) indicates that there is an acceptable field with sporadic muscle contractions causing some interference with the surgeon's work;
excellent (Score 4) indicates a wide working field without any lung movement or muscle contractions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>heart rate</measure>
    <time_frame>5 min after induction of anesthesia, 1 min after chest opening, 30 min after start of surgery, 60 min after start of surgery, 90 min after start of surgery, 120 min after start of surgery, 1 min after start of chest closure, 5 min after extubation</time_frame>
    <description>heart rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>5 min after induction of anesthesia, 1 min after chest opening, 30 min after start of surgery, 60 min after start of surgery, 90 min after start of surgery, 120 min after start of surgery, 1 min after start of chest closure, 5 min after extubation</time_frame>
    <description>Mean blood pressure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Train-of-four ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>5 min after induction of anesthesia, 1 min after chest opening, 30 min after start of surgery, 60 min after start of surgery, 90 min after start of surgery, 120 min after start of surgery, 1 min after start of chest closure, 5 min after extubation</time_frame>
    <description>Train-of-four ratio</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>laryngoscopy conditions</measure>
    <time_frame>1 min after laryngscopy</time_frame>
    <description>laryngoscopy conditions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>intubating conditions</measure>
    <time_frame>1 min after intubation</time_frame>
    <description>intubating conditions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost of medications</measure>
    <time_frame>after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>cost of the used medications</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Need for vasoactive drugs</measure>
    <time_frame>for 3 hour during surgery</time_frame>
    <description>use of ephedrine, and norepinephrine</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recovery Times</measure>
    <time_frame>for 1 hours after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>the times to spontaneous eye opening, obey verbal command, tracheal extubation and post-anesthesia care unit discharge</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">66</enrollment>
  <condition>Elective Open Thoracotomy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Muscle Relaxants (MR) group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cisatracurium will be administered</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non- Muscle Relaxants (NMR) group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>No cisatracurium will be administered</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Muscle Relaxants (MR) group</intervention_name>
    <description>patients received 0.2 mL/kg cisatracurium® (Nimbex) 0.2%, and a left-sided endobronchial double-lumen tube was placed when the TOF revealed one or two twitches</description>
    <arm_group_label>Muscle Relaxants (MR) group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Non- Muscle Relaxants (NMR) group</intervention_name>
    <description>No cisatracurium® (Nimbex) will be administered</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non- Muscle Relaxants (NMR) group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists physical class (II-III)

          -  elective open thoracotomy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  New York Heart Association class&gt; II)

          -  Forced vital capacity &lt; 50% of the predicted values

          -  Forced expiratory volume in 1 second &lt; 50% of the predicted values

          -  Hepatic diseases

          -  Renal diseases.

          -  Reactive airways.

          -  Neuromuscular diseases.

          -  Asthma

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Increased risk of regurgitation

          -  Anticipated difficult intubation

          -  Body mass index &gt;35 kg/m2

          -  Electrolytes abnormalities

          -  Acid base abnormalities

          -  Repeat surgery

          -  history of head and neck surgery

          -  Preoperative circulatory support

          -  Preoperative ventilatory support

          -  Medications affecting the neuromuscular junctions

          -  Family history of malignant hyperthermia

          -  Allergy to any of the study drugs
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mohamed R El Tahan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Associate Professor at Anesthesiology Dept</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mohamed A Regal, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Imam Abdulrahman Bin Faisal University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dammam University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Al Khubar</city>
        <state>Eastern</state>
        <zip>31952</zip>
        <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 7, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 7, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 9, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 8, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 8, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 9, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Thoracic surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>non-muscle relaxant</keyword>
  <keyword>target-controlled infusion</keyword>
  <keyword>remifentanil</keyword>
  <keyword>surgical conditions</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscle Hypotonia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Remifentanil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisatracurium</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

