<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02030158</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ANZIC-RC/MR001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02030158</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Statistical Analysis Plan for an Individual Patient Data Meta-analysis of Three, International Trials Comparing Protocolised With Usual Resuscitation in Patients Presenting to the Emergency Department With Severe Sepsis and Septic Shock</brief_title>
  <official_title>Statistical Analysis Plan for an Individual Patient Data Meta-analysis of Three, International, Multicentre, Randomised, Controlled Trials Comparing Protocolised With Usual Resuscitation in Patients Presenting to the Emergency Department With Severe Sepsis and Septic Shock</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Australian and New Zealand Intensive Care Research Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Intensive Care National Audit &amp; Research Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Australian and New Zealand Intensive Care Research Centre</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is the statistical analysis plan for an individual patient data meta-analysis (IPDMA) of
      three EGDT clinical trials.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In 2001, Rivers and colleagues, published the results of a single-centre, proof-of-concept,
      randomised, controlled trial conducted in the USA comparing protocolised resuscitation,
      termed early goal-directed therapy (EGDT), with usual resuscitation in 263 patients
      presenting to the emergency department (ED) with severe sepsis or septic shock. The Rivers'
      trial demonstrated a significant 16% absolute risk reduction (ARR) in hospital mortality from
      46.5% to 30.5%. With a view to informing the generalisability of these findings in their own
      health care settings, three independent, large, multicentre, randomised controlled trials
      testing EGDT were subsequently funded, one in the USA, one in Australasia and one in the UK:

      USA - Protocolized Care for Early Septic Shock (ProCESS); Australasia - Australasian
      Resuscitation In Sepsis Evaluation (ARISE); and UK - Protocolised Management In Sepsis
      (ProMISe). Though independent trials, but with a view to performing a subsequent individual
      patient data meta-analysis (IPDMA), efforts were made to harmonise the three, contemporaneous
      trials on key areas of their design, for example, trial protocol, entry criteria, data and
      data collection, primary and secondary outcomes, etc.

      As exist, and are published, for each of the individual trials, ProCESS, ARISE and ProMISe ,
      the proposed IPDMA requires a pre-specified statistical analysis plan (SAP). The SAP set out
      below has been agreed between the three trial teams and prior to any knowledge of the results
      of any of the individual three trials.

      It should be noted that, any proposed analyses added to the IPDMA SAP, post-knowledge of the
      results of ProCESS, ARISE and/or ProMISe, will be clearly indicated in any subsequent
      publication of the SAP and the results of this IPDMA.

      Objectives

      In patients presenting to the ED with severe sepsis and septic shock:

      Primary objective

        -  to compare the effect of EGDT with usual resuscitation on 90-day all-cause mortality
           Secondary objectives

        -  to compare the effect of EGDT with usual resuscitation on 90-day all-cause mortality
           after adjustment for important baseline covariates

        -  to compare the effect of EGDT across countries

        -  to compare the effect of EGDT on secondary/intermediate outcomes

        -  to compare the effect of EGDT in pre-determined, clinically important subgroups

      Data management Prior to pooling the data from the three trials, the clinical report forms
      for each trial will be compared and similarities/dissimilarities discussed across the trial
      teams to inform the final structure and specification of the IPDMA dataset. Similar variables
      will be double-checked for consistency across the trials (analysis of distribution, range and
      summary statistics) prior to being finally imported into the IPDMA database.

      [Unlike ARISE and ProMISE - which are two-arm trials comparing EGDT with usual resuscitation,
      ProCESS is a three-arm trial with the additional arm evaluating protocolised usual
      resuscitation (termed protocolised standard care). Data from ProCESS for patients recruited
      and randomised to protocolised standard care (n=450) will be excluded from the analysis of
      the primary objective but retained for possible inclusion in the analyses of relevant
      secondary objectives.]

      Analysis principles Primary analyses will be conducted on an intention-to-treat basis, with
      patients retained in their original, randomly assigned groups, and will be unadjusted for the
      effects of covariates.

      Imputation of missing values will be considered and, if employed, the method fully described.
      For all analyses, the number of complete/missing observations will be reported.

      Pre-determined, clinically important subgroup analyses will be conducted even if strong
      evidence of a treatment effect for the primary outcome is absent. All tests will be two-sided
      and a p-value of 0.05 will be used to indicate statistical significance. No formal adjustment
      will be made for multiple comparisons - however, with a large number of subgroup analyses
      planned, cautious interpretation will be employed.

      Sample size calculation As indicated in the Introduction, the treatment effect in the Rivers'
      trial was a 16% ARR in hospital mortality (a 12.6% ARR in mortality at 60-days).
      Individually, ProCESS, ARISE and ProMISe have 80-90% power to detect a 6.5-8.0% ARR in
      mortality (hospital mortality censored at 60-days for ProCESS, 90-day mortality for ARISE and
      ProMISe), assuming a baseline mortality of 24-40% depending on the trial.

      The combined recruitment into ProCESS, ARISE and ProMISE is 4210 patients with 3760 patients
      randomised either to receive EGDT or usual resuscitation. Based on a control event rate
      ranging from 25%-35%, an 80% power and a two-sided p-value of 0.05, this IPDMA will be able
      to detect an ARR in 90-day mortality ranging from 4-5% (with no allowance for heterogeneity
      of treatment effect or clustering of outcomes across the three trials).

      For subgroups, again based on a control event rate ranging from 25%-35%, an 80% power and a
      two-sided p-value of 0.05, this IPDMA will be able to detect an interaction effect (odds
      ratio) of around 1.5 for a subgroup representing half of the total sample and an interaction
      effect of around 1.6 for a subgroup representing one quarter of the total sample. If a
      treatment-subgroup interaction is not significant, then it will be interpreted that the
      treatment effect for that subgroup is best informed by the overall treatment effect in the
      IPDMA.

      Analysis plan The IPDMA will be performed using one stage, multi-level (patients nested in
      sites nested in trials), mixed modelling. Heterogeneity between trials will be determined by
      fitting a fixed interaction term between treatment and trial, while overall treatment effect
      will be reported with trial treated as a fixed effect and site treated as a random effect. A
      secondary analysis will adjust for important baseline covariates, including: age; sex; APACHE
      II score; SBP&lt;90 mm Hg; and use of invasive mechanical ventilation.

      Primary outcome 90 day all-cause mortality - logistic, mixed modelling, with terms for trial
      and site, reported as odds ratios with 95% confidence intervals (CI) Secondary/intermediate
      outcomes Hospital (censored at 60 days) and 28-day mortality - binomial, mixed modelling
      reported as odds ratios with 95% CI Survival analysis - Appropriate survival analysis
      techniques, e.g. Cox proportional hazards regression reported as Hazards Ratio with 95% CI if
      proportionality assumption holds Duration of stay in ED, ICU and hospital - assessed for
      normality, appropriate transformation reported as ratios of geometric means with 95% CI,
      accounting for impact of survivorship Receipt of and duration of mechanical ventilation,
      vasopressor support and renal replacement therapy - binomial, mixed modelling reported as
      odds ratios with 95% CI Where relevant, any assumptions underlying analyses will be detailed
      and reported. All results will be reported in tabular form and displayed using forest plots
      with 95% CI. All analyses will be performed using SAS version 9.3 (SAS Institute Inc., Cary,
      NC, USA). A two-sided p-value of 0.05 will be considered to be statistically significant.

      Subgroup analyses To determine if the relationship between treatment and the primary outcome
      differs between pre-determined, clinically important subgroups, fixed interaction terms
      between treatment and subgroup will be reported. To further ascertain if the
      treatment-subgroup interaction varied between trials, a three-way fixed interaction between
      trial, treatment and subgroup will also be reported. Furthermore, where subgroups are to be
      defined by a continuous variable, they will be analysed both as categorical and continuous
      data with the linearity of the continuous relationship explored. Additional sensitivity
      analyses will be conducted adjusting for important baseline covariates.

      Pre-determined, clinically important, pre-randomisation subgroups of interest will relate to
      site, patient and care delivery factors.

      Site factors:

        -  Country

        -  Type of hospital

        -  Annual admissions

        -  Annual ED presentations

        -  Number ICU beds

        -  Ratio of ICU to hospital beds

        -  Annual ICU admissions

        -  Specialist staffing in ICU

        -  EGDT delivery model

      Patient factors:

        -  Age

        -  Sex

        -  Race/ethnicity

        -  Obesity

        -  APACHE II score

        -  MEDS score

        -  SOFA score

        -  Source of infection

        -  Infectious aetiology

        -  Presentation - refractory hypotension

        -  Presentation - hypoperfusion

        -  Receipt of vasopressors

        -  Receipt of invasive ventilation

      Care delivery factors:

        -  Interval between ED presentation and first administration of antimicrobials

        -  Interval between ED presentation and starting intervention

        -  Time of admission (day/night and weekend/weekday)

        -  Volume of fluid

      Causal mediation analysis Exploratory analyses on post-randomisation variables, to further
      understand the delivery and therapeutic effect of EGDT, will be conducted. Potential
      mediators of the causal effect of EGDT on outcome will be considered and the associations
      between intervention and mediator and between intervention and outcome, adjusted for
      mediator, will be estimated.

      Prior to commencing these IPDMA analyses, a detailed, final SAP will be published.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>All-cause mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days post-randomisation</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>At hospital discharge (censored at 60 days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>28-day mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>At 28 days from randomisation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of survival</measure>
    <time_frame>from randomisation (censored at 90 days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of stay in the Intensive Care Unit (ICU)</measure>
    <time_frame>from ICU admission to ICU discharge (censored at 90 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of duration will be standardised and analyses of these secondary/intermediate outcomes will use agreed, standard approaches that account for impact of survivorship</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of stay in the Emergency Department (ED)</measure>
    <time_frame>From ED admission to ED discharge (censored at 72 hours)</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of duration will be standardised and analyses of these secondary/intermediate outcomes will use agreed, standard approaches that account for impact of survivorship</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of stay in the hospital</measure>
    <time_frame>From hospital admission to hospital discharge (censored at 90 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of duration will be standardised and analyses of these secondary/intermediate outcomes will use agreed, standard approaches that account for impact of survivorship</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Receipt of and duration of mechanical ventilation post-randomisation</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomisation to end of mechanical ventilation (censored at 90 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of duration will be standardised and analyses of these secondary/intermediate outcomes will use agreed, standard approaches that account for impact of survivorship</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Receipt of and duration of vasopressor support post-randomisation</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomisation to end of vasopressor support (censored at 90 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of duration will be standardised and analyses of these secondary/intermediate outcomes will use agreed, standard approaches that account for impact of survivorship</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Receipt of and duration of renal replacement therapy post-randomisation</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomisation to end of renal replacement therapy (censored at 90 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of duration will be standardised and analyses of these secondary/intermediate outcomes will use agreed, standard approaches that account for impact of survivorship</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">4210</enrollment>
  <condition>Severe Sepsis and Septic Shock</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Early Goal-Directed Therapy (EGDT)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Protocolised resuscitation (termed Early Goal-Directed Therapy - EGDT)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual resuscitation</arm_group_label>
    <description>Usual resuscitation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Severe sepsis and septic shock
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        * Enrolled into one of the three studies (ARISE, ProMISe or ProCESS) to either Early Goal
        Directed Therapy or usual resuscitation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kathy Rowan</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Director, Intensive Care National Audit and Research Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Derek Angus</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Director, Clinical Research, Investigation, and Systems Modeling of Acute Illnesses, University of Pistburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rinaldo Bellomo</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>ANZIC-RC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Belinda Howe</last_name>
    <phone>+61 3 9903 0340</phone>
    <email>belinda.howe@monash.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rivers E, Nguyen B, Havstad S, Ressler J, Muzzin A, Knoblich B, Peterson E, Tomlanovich M; Early Goal-Directed Therapy Collaborative Group. Early goal-directed therapy in the treatment of severe sepsis and septic shock. N Engl J Med. 2001 Nov 8;345(19):1368-77.</citation>
    <PMID>11794169</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Delaney A, Peake SL, Bellomo R, Cameron P, Holdgate A, Howe B, Higgins A, Presneill J, Webb S; ARISE Investigators. Australasian Resuscitation In Sepsis Evaluation trial statistical analysis plan. Emerg Med Australas. 2013 Oct;25(5):406-15. doi: 10.1111/1742-6723.12116. Epub 2013 Sep 9.</citation>
    <PMID>24099368</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Power GS, Harrison DA, Mouncey PR, Osborn TM, Harvey SE, Rowan KM. The Protocolised Management in Sepsis (ProMISe) trial statistical analysis plan. Crit Care Resusc. 2013 Dec;15(4):311-7.</citation>
    <PMID>24289513</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pike F, Yealy DM, Kellum JA, Huang DT, Barnato AE, Eaton TL, Angus DC, Weissfeld LA; ProCESS Investigators. Protocolized Care for Early Septic Shock (ProCESS) statistical analysis plan. Crit Care Resusc. 2013 Dec;15(4):301-10.</citation>
    <PMID>24289512</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>ProCESS/ARISE/ProMISe Methodology Writing Committee, Huang DT, Angus DC, Barnato A, Gunn SR, Kellum JA, Stapleton DK, Weissfeld LA, Yealy DM, Peake SL, Delaney A, Bellomo R, Cameron P, Higgins A, Holdgate A, Howe B, Webb SA, Williams P, Osborn TM, Mouncey PR, Harrison DA, Harvey SE, Rowan KM. Harmonizing international trials of early goal-directed resuscitation for severe sepsis and septic shock: methodology of ProCESS, ARISE, and ProMISe. Intensive Care Med. 2013 Oct;39(10):1760-75. Epub 2013 Aug 30.</citation>
    <PMID>23958738</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 20, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 7, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 8, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 7, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 7, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 8, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Severe sepsis</keyword>
  <keyword>Septic shock</keyword>
  <keyword>Early goal directed therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Individual patient data meta-analysis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Emergencies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sepsis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Toxemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shock</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shock, Septic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

