<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02034773</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CC-220-CP-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02034773</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>3-part Study to Evaluate Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics &amp; Pharmacodynamics of Multiple Doses of CC-220 and Relative Bioavailability of a Formulated CC-220 Capsule</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Three-part Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, and Pharmacodynamics of Multiple Doses of CC-220 and to Evaluate the Relative Bioavailability of a Formulated CC-220 Capsule in Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Celgene Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Celgene</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of multiple doses
      of CC-220 in healthy subjects and to evaluate the relative bioavailability of a formulated
      CC-220 capsule
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a 3-part study to be conducted at a single study center. Part 1 is a randomized,
      double-blind, placebo-controlled, ascending-dose study. During the course of Part 1, each
      subject will participate in a screening phase, a baseline phase, a treatment phase and a
      follow up visit. There will be a total of 4 cohorts, each of which consists of a different
      dose level and/or dosing duration, with 8 or 9 subjects per cohort. In each cohort, 6
      subjects will receive a dose of CC-220 and the remaining subjects will receive placebo
      depending on the randomization schedule. In 2 of the cohorts, study drug will be administered
      once daily for a total of 14 days. In the other 2 cohorts, study drug will be administered
      once daily for 28 days. In one of the 28-day dosing cohorts, 2 vaccinations (tetanus toxoid
      adsorbed and pneumococcal vaccinations) will also be administered on Day 14 of the 28-day
      dosing period to help characterize the effect of CC-220 on antibody responses. Part 2 is a
      randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel-group study to explore the effects of
      an alternative dosing schedule on the pharmacodynamics of CC-220. During the course of Part
      2, each subject will participate in a screening phase, a baseline phase, a treatment phase
      and a follow up visit. There will be a total of 2 cohorts, each of which consists of a
      different dose level, with 9 subjects per cohort. In each cohort, 6 subjects will receive a
      dose of CC-220 and 3 subjects will receive placebo depending on the randomization schedule.
      The dosing frequency will be either once every 3 days for 14 days or once every 7 days for 28
      days. Part 3 is a randomized, open-label, two-period, two-way crossover study to evaluate the
      relative bioavailability of one CC-220 formulated capsule, relative to two reference
      capsules, following a single oral dose of CC-220. During the course of Part 3, each subject
      will participate in a screening phase, a baseline phase, a treatment phase consisting of 2
      periods, and a follow up visit. There will be one cohort consisting of a total of 12
      subjects. In each study period, approximately 6 subjects will receive a single dose of CC-220
      as one formulated capsule (test product) and approximately 6 subjects will receive a single
      dose of CC-220 as two reference capsules (reference product).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 months overall</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with adverse events</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentrations of CC-220 and its R-enantiomer in plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days per cohort</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected at pre-specified times to determine levels of CC-220 and its R-enantiomer in plasma</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic Assessmens</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 42 days per cohort</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected at pre-specified times for pharmacodynamic assessments</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum observed plasma concentration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Time to Cmax</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - AUCinf</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero extrapolated to infinity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - AUCt</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to the last quantifiable concentration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - AUCtau</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to tau, where tau is the dosing interval</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - t1/2,z</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Terminal-phase elimination half-life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - CL/F</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Apparent total plasma clearance when dosed orally</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - Vz/F</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Apparent total volume of distribution when dosed orally, based on the terminal phase</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Accumulation Ratio (RA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Accumulation Ratio for Cmax and AUCtau</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>8</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CC-220 0.3mg x 14 days</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CC-220 1mg x 28 days</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CC-220 0.3mg x 28 days</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CC-220 1mg x a total of 14 days</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CC-220 0.3mg (once every 3 days for 14 days)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CC-220 1mg (once every 7 days for 28 days)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CC-220 1mg (formulated and reference capsules)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CC-220</intervention_name>
    <description>CC-220 0.3mg will be administered once daily for 14 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>CC-220 0.3mg x 14 days</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CC-220</intervention_name>
    <description>CC-220 1mg will be administered once daily for 28 days + 1 dose of tetanus toxoid vaccination and 1 dose of pneumococcal vaccination</description>
    <arm_group_label>CC-220 1mg x 28 days</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CC-220</intervention_name>
    <description>CC-220 0.3mg will be administered once daily for 28 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>CC-220 0.3mg x 28 days</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CC-220</intervention_name>
    <description>CC-220 1mg will be administered once daily for 7 days on 2 separate occasions, with a 7-day washout in between, for a total of 14 days of dosing</description>
    <arm_group_label>CC-220 1mg x a total of 14 days</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo will be administered once daily for up to 28 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CC-220</intervention_name>
    <description>CC-220 0.3mg will be administered every 3 days for 14 days (5 total doses)</description>
    <arm_group_label>CC-220 0.3mg (once every 3 days for 14 days)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CC-220</intervention_name>
    <description>CC-220 1mg (once every 7 days for 28 days)</description>
    <arm_group_label>CC-220 1mg (once every 7 days for 28 days)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CC-220</intervention_name>
    <description>CC-220 1mg will be administered as a single dose in each of 2 study periods; once as a formulated capsule and once as two reference capsules</description>
    <arm_group_label>CC-220 1mg (formulated and reference capsules)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Must understand and voluntarily sign a written informed consent document prior to
             any study-related procedures being performed.

             2. Must be able to communicate with the investigator, understand and comply with the
             requirements of the study, and agree to adhere to restrictions and examination
             schedules.

             3. Healthy male or female of any race between 18 to 55 years of age (inclusive) at the
             time of signing the informed consent document, and in good health as determined by a
             physical examination.

             4. For males: Agree to use barrier contraception not made of natural (animal) membrane
             [e.g., latex or polyurethane condoms are acceptable]) when engaging in sexual activity
             with a female of childbearing potential while on study medication, and for at least 28
             days after the last dose of study medication.

        For females: Female subjects must have been surgically sterilized (hysterectomy or
        bilateral oophorectomy; proper documentation required) at least 6 months before screening,
        or be postmenopausal (defined as 24 months without menses before screening, with an
        estradiol level of &lt; 30 pg/mL and follicle-stimulating hormone level of &gt; 40 IU/L at
        screening).

        5. Must have a body mass index between 18 and 33 kg/m2 (inclusive). 6. Clinical laboratory
        tests must be within normal limits or acceptable to the investigator. Platelet count,
        absolute neutrophil count and absolute lymphocyte count must be above the lower limit of
        normal at the screening visit.

        7. Subject must be afebrile, with supine systolic blood pressure: 90 to 140 mmHg, supine
        diastolic blood pressure: 50 to 90 mmHg, and pulse rate: 40 to 110 bpm.

        8. Must have a normal or clinically-acceptable 12-lead electrocardiogram at screening. Male
        subjects must have a QTcF value ≤ 430 msec. Female subjects must have a QTcF value ≤ 450
        msec.

        9. Antitetanus immunoglobulin G titer ≥ 0.1 IU/mL to ensure prior exposure of tetanus
        toxoid. Note: This criterion only applies to those subjects who will be dosed once daily
        for 28 days.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1. History of any clinically significant and relevant neurological, gastrointestinal,
             renal, hepatic, cardiovascular, psychological, pulmonary, metabolic, endocrine,
             hematological, allergic disease, drug allergies, or other major disorders.

             2. Any condition which places the subject at unacceptable risk if he or she were to
             participate in the study, or confounds the ability to interpret data from the study.

             3. Used any prescribed systemic or topical medication (including but not limited to
             analgesics, anesthetics, etc) within 30 days of the first dose administration, unless
             sponsor agreement is obtained.

             4. Used any non-prescribed systemic or topical medication (including vitamin/mineral
             supplements, and herbal medicines) within 14 days of the first dose administration,
             unless sponsor agreement is obtained.

             5. Used CYP3A inducers and inhibitors (including St. John's Wort) within 30 days of
             the first dose administration.

             6. Has any surgical or medical conditions possibly affecting drug absorption,
             distribution, metabolism and excretion, e.g., bariatric procedure. Appendectomy and
             cholecystectomy are acceptable.

             7. Donated blood or plasma within 8 weeks before the first dose administration to a
             blood bank or blood donation center.

             8. History of drug abuse (as defined by the current version of the Diagnostic and
             Statistical Manual) within 2 years before dosing, or positive drug screening test
             reflecting consumption of illicit drugs.

             9. History of alcohol abuse (as defined by the current version of the Diagnostic and
             Statistical Manual) within 2 years before dosing, or positive alcohol screen.

             10. Known to have serum hepatitis or known to be a carrier of hepatitis B surface
             antigen or hepatitis c antibody, or have a positive result to the test for human
             immunodeficiency virus antibodies at screening.

             11. Exposed to an investigational drug (new chemical entity) within 30 days preceding
             the first dose administration, or 5 half-lives of that investigational drug, if known
             (whichever is longer).

             12. Smoke more than 10 cigarettes per day, or the equivalent in other tobacco products
             (self reported).

             13. Vaccination within 30 days of dosing or plans to receive vaccination within 30
             days after dosing. Systemic infection within 30 days of dosing.

             14. Tetanus vaccination within 5 years prior to the first dose administration. Note:
             This criterion only applies to those subjects who will be dosed once daily for 28
             days.

             15. Pneumococcal vaccination within 3 years prior to the first dose administration.
             Note: This criterion only applies to those subjects who will be dosed once daily for
             28 days.

             16. Any self-reported history of hypersensitivity to vaccinations to be administered
             in this study or hypersensitivity to latex. Note: This criterion only applies to those
             subjects who will be dosed once daily for 28 days.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel Weiss, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Celgene</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Debra Mandarino, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Covance</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Covance Clinical Research Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53704</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 10, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 10, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 13, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 10, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 10, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 13, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Safety, Pharmacokinetics, Pharmacodynamics, Healthy Subjects</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

