<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02039856</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CRE 12-026</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02039856</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Implementation of Women's Health Patient Aligned Care Teams</brief_title>
  <acronym>WH PACT</acronym>
  <official_title>Implementation of VA Womens Health Patient Aligned Care Teams WH-PACTs</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>RAND</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      VA has undertaken a major initiative to transform care through implementation of Patient
      Aligned Care Teams (PACTs). Based on the patient-centered medical home (PCMH) concept, PACT
      aims to improve access, continuity, coordination and comprehensiveness using team-based care
      that is patient-driven and patient-centered. However, how VA should adapt PACT to meet the
      needs of special populations, such as women Veterans, is yet to be worked out. The main goal
      of this study is to develop and test an evidence-based quality improvement (EBQI) approach to
      adapting and implementing PACT for women Veterans, incorporating comprehensive women's health
      care in gender-sensitive care environments, thereby accelerating achievement of PACT tenets
      for women Veterans and reducing persistent gender disparities in VA quality of care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Women Veterans' numerical minority in VA healthcare settings has created logistical
      challenges to delivering gender-sensitive comprehensive services. These challenges have only
      grown as more women Veterans have enrolled in VA care. Access and quality have lagged behind
      that of male Veterans, while gender sensitivity, including adequate attention to
      privacy/safety and awareness of women's military roles and experiences, is often lacking.
      On-site availability of gender-specific services has also not kept pace, with women Veterans
      more likely to be outsourced for gender-specific care now than they were ten years ago.
      Further, while the proportion of VA facilities having women's health (WH) clinics has
      increased, prior research has demonstrated that as many as 40% of them were not delivering
      comprehensive primary care services, instead focusing only on gender-specific exams. Lack of
      gender-sensitive, comprehensive care for women has also been associated with measurable
      decrements in women's ratings of VA access, continuity and coordination, as well as measures
      of technical quality.

      The investigators aim to assess the effectiveness of evidence-based quality improvement
      (EBQI) methods for developing a WH PACT model using a cluster randomized trial design (Aim
      #1); examine impacts of receipt of WH-PACT concordant care on women Veterans' outcomes (Aim
      #2); evaluate processes of EBQI-supported WH-PACT implementation (Aim #3); and develop
      implementation and evaluation tools for use in EBQI-supported WH-PACT model adaptation,
      implementation, sustainability and spread to additional VA facilities (Aim #4).

      EBQI is a systematic approach to developing a multi-level research-clinical partnership
      approach to engaging local organizational senior leaders and quality improvement teams in
      adapting and implementing new care models in the context of prior evidence, local practice
      context, and provider behavior change methods, with researchers providing technical support
      and practice facilitation. In a cluster randomized trials, the investigators will evaluate
      WH-PACT model achievement using patient, provider and practice surveys. The investigators
      will examine intermediate changes in provider, staff and team knowledge and attitudes. Using
      analyses of secondary administrative and performance data, the investigators will also
      explore impacts of receipt of WH-PACT care on quality of chronic disease care and prevention,
      health status, utilization and costs. Using mixed methods, the investigators will assess
      pre-post EBQI practice context; document WH-PACT implementation; and examine
      barriers/facilitators to EBQI-supported WH-PACT implementation through a combination of
      semi-structured interviews and monthly formative progress narratives and administrative data
      review.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 9, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 30, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>WH PACT model achievement: This measure assesses changes in level of achievement of WH-PACT features: access, continuity, care coordination, patient-centeredness, comprehensiveness and gender sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>Components of this measure will be measured at three time points in time (baseline, 12- and 24-months follow-up) between October 2013 and March 2016</time_frame>
    <description>This measure is intended to assess the effectiveness of EBQI methods for accelerating the implementation of WH-PACT in experimental practices (8 VAMCs) compared to naturalistic routine PACT implementation controls (4 VAMCs), randomly assigned within four VISNs (2 E-to-1 C within each VISN).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">420</enrollment>
  <condition>Patient-centered Medical Home Implementation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Evidence Based Quality Improvement</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention at eight of 12 study sites consisting of VISN/facility-level stakeholder panel meetings designed to set evidence-based priorities for quality improvement (QI) in the context of local data and needs; local practice quality improvement team design meetings; QI training and education; iterative formative data feedback; across intervention-practice QI collaboration calls; and practice facilitation. Local leadership, QI champions and frontline staff will develop and implement innovation projects aimed at improving aspects of WH PACT implementation based on site-level and VISN priorities in the context of national PACT and WH guidelines.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Routine PACT Implementation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>PACT implementation is a nationally mandated initiative in VA primary care and women's health clinic settings, with audit-and-feedback of PACT-related performance measures, incentives for achievement of PACT attributes and continual guidance on PACT and WH policy and procedures from VA primary care and women's health leaders.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Evidence Based Quality Improvement (EBQI) Intervention Practices</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention at eight of 12 study sites consisting of VISN/facility-level stakeholder panel meetings designed to set evidence-based priorities for quality improvement (QI) in the context of local data and needs; local practice quality improvement team design meetings; QI training and education; iterative formative data feedback; across intervention-practice QI collaboration calls; and practice facilitation. Local leadership, QI champions and frontline staff will develop and implement innovation projects aimed at improving aspects of WH PACT implementation based on site-level and VISN priorities in the context of national PACT and WH guidelines.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Evidence Based Quality Improvement</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>WH PACT EBQI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Routine PACT Implementation (Naturalistic Control Practices)</intervention_name>
    <description>PACT implementation is a nationally mandated initiative in VA primary care and women's health clinic settings, with audit-and-feedback of PACT-related performance measures, incentives for achievement of PACT attributes and continual guidance on PACT and WH policy and procedures from VA primary care and women's health leaders.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Routine PACT Implementation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Control Practices</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Facility inclusion criteria:

          -  VA medical center (VAMC)

          -  Located in a VISN that has 3 or more VAMCs

          -  Membership in the Women's Health Practice Based Research Network (PBRN)

        Key Stakeholder (interviews) inclusion criteria:

          -  VISN and VAMC leaders (SES), VAMC primary care/PACT directors, VAMC women's health
             medical directors, Women Veteran Program Managers (VISN and VAMC), VISN
             representatives in mental health, health information technology/informatics, quality
             improvement/system redesign, at least one Nurse Executive (VISN or VAMC)

          -  Intervention and control VAMCs

        Provider (surveys and interviews) inclusion criteria:

          -  Primary care providers (MD, DO, NP, PA) who have seen 1+ women Veterans in the past
             year

          -  Teamlet primary care provider interviews (MD, DO, NP, PA) at intervention VAMCs

          -  Surveys of primary care providers (MD, DO, NP, PA) at intervention and control VAMCs

          -  Surveys of larger primary care/PACT team members (e.g., clinical pharmacists, health
             coaches)

        Staff (surveys and interviews) inclusion criteria:

          -  Primary care/PACT clinical staff (non-providers) in primary care/PACT teams/teamlets
             that have seen 1+ women Veterans in the past year

          -  Teamlet member interviews at Intervention VAMCs

        Patient inclusion criteria:

        - Women Veterans seen in participating VAMCs with 3+ primary care visits in general primary
        care and/or women's health clinics in the past year

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Facility exclusion criteria:

          -  VA facilities that are not VAMCs (e.g., community-based outpatient clinics or CBOCs)

          -  VAMCs in VISNs with fewer than 3 VAMCs

          -  VAMCs that are not members of the WH PBRN

        Key Stakeholder (interviews) exclusion criteria:

        - Stakeholders outside of the participating VISNs (1, 4, 12, 23) and VAMCs (see study
        sites)

        Provider (surveys and interviews) exclusion criteria:

          -  VA providers who do not deliver primary care in participating VAMCs

          -  VA primary care providers who have not seen or do not see women Veteran patients for
             primary care delivery at a participating VAMC

          -  Teamlet providers at control VAMCs will not be interviewed

        Staff (surveys and interviews) exclusion criteria:

          -  Primary care clinical staff not participating in PACT (e.g., assigned to primary care
             rolls but not actually associated with primary care/PACT direct patient care delivery)

          -  Primary care/PACT clinical staff at control VAMCs will not be interviewed

        Patient exclusion criteria:

          -  Women Veterans who do not use the VA for their health care or for their primary care
             needs

          -  Women Veterans with fewer than 3 VA primary care visits in the prior year and
             therefore not exposed to PACT or WH PACT

          -  Women Veterans with terminal illness and/or poor prognosis or other health concerns
             for whom enrollment and survey participation would prove an inappropriate burden
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Only the patient survey component is gender-based (includes women Veterans only). Eligibility for provider/staff surveys or key stakeholder interviews is not gender-based.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elizabeth M. Yano, PhD MSPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Greater Los Angeles Healthcare System, Sepulveda, CA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Greater Los Angeles Healthcare System, Sepulveda, CA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sepulveda</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91343</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Connecticut Healthcare System West Haven Campus, West Haven, CT</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06516</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jesse Brown VA Medical Center, Chicago, IL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Edward Hines Jr. VA Hospital, Hines, IL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hines</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60141-5000</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Iowa City VA Health Care System, Iowa City, IA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Iowa City</city>
        <state>Iowa</state>
        <zip>52246-2208</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Boston Healthcare System Jamaica Plain Campus, Jamaica Plain, MA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02130</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Central Western Massachusetts Healthcare System, Leeds, MA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leeds</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01053-9764</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Minneapolis VA Health Care System, Minneapolis, MN</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55417</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fargo VA Healthcare System, Fargo, ND</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fargo</city>
        <state>North Dakota</state>
        <zip>58102</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Philadelphia VA Medical Center, Philadelphia, PA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Pittsburgh Healthcare System University Drive Division, Pittsburgh, PA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15240</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clarksburg Louis A. Johnson VA Medical Center, Clarksburg, WV</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clarksburg</city>
        <state>West Virginia</state>
        <zip>26301</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>William S. Middleton Memorial Veterans Hospital, Madison, WI</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yano EM, Bair MJ, Carrasquillo O, Krein SL, Rubenstein LV. Patient Aligned Care Teams (PACT): VA's journey to implement patient-centered medical homes. J Gen Intern Med. 2014 Jul;29 Suppl 2:S547-9. doi: 10.1007/s11606-014-2835-8.</citation>
    <PMID>24715407</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yano EM, Haskell S, Hayes P. Delivery of gender-sensitive comprehensive primary care to women veterans: implications for VA Patient Aligned Care Teams. J Gen Intern Med. 2014 Jul;29 Suppl 2:S703-7. doi: 10.1007/s11606-013-2699-3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24715395</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chuang E, Brunner J, Mak S, Hamilton AB, Canelo I, Darling J, Rubenstein LV, Yano EM. Challenges with Implementing a Patient-Centered Medical Home Model for Women Veterans. Womens Health Issues. 2017 Mar - Apr;27(2):214-220. doi: 10.1016/j.whi.2016.11.005. Epub 2017 Jan 4.</citation>
    <PMID>28063848</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hamilton AB, Brunner J, Cain C, Chuang E, Luger TM, Canelo I, Rubenstein L, Yano EM. Engaging multilevel stakeholders in an implementation trial of evidence-based quality improvement in VA women's health primary care. Transl Behav Med. 2017 Sep;7(3):478-485. doi: 10.1007/s13142-017-0501-5.</citation>
    <PMID>28585163</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Goldstein KM, Vogt D, Hamilton A, Frayne SM, Gierisch J, Blakeney J, Sadler A, Bean-Mayberry BM, Carney D, DiLeone B, Fox AB, Klap R, Yee E, Romodan Y, Strehlow H, Yosef J, Yano EM. Practice-based research networks add value to evidence-based quality improvement. Healthc (Amst). 2017 Jul 12. pii: S2213-0764(16)30101-4. doi: 10.1016/j.hjdsi.2017.06.008. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>28711505</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Meredith LS, Azhar G, Okunogbe A, Canelo IA, Darling JE, Street AE, Yano EM. Primary Care Providers with More Experience and Stronger Self-Efficacy Beliefs Regarding Women Veterans Screen More Frequently for Interpersonal Violence. Womens Health Issues. 2017 Sep - Oct;27(5):586-591. doi: 10.1016/j.whi.2017.06.003. Epub 2017 Jul 25.</citation>
    <PMID>28754476</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Meredith LS, Wang Y, Okunogbe A, Bergman AA, Canelo IA, Darling JE, Yano EM. Attitudes, Practices, and Experiences with Implementing a Patient-Centered Medical Home for Women Veterans. Womens Health Issues. 2017 Mar - Apr;27(2):221-227. doi: 10.1016/j.whi.2016.11.008. Epub 2017 Jan 10.</citation>
    <PMID>28087130</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yano EM, Hamilton AB. Accelerating delivery of trauma-sensitive care: Using multilevel stakeholder engagement to improve care for women veterans. Fam Syst Health. 2017 Sep;35(3):373-375. doi: 10.1037/fsh0000288.</citation>
    <PMID>28945449</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hamilton AB, Yano EM. The importance of symbolic and engaged participation in evidence-based quality improvement in a complex integrated healthcare system: response to &quot;The science of stakeholder engagement in research&quot;. Transl Behav Med. 2017 Sep;7(3):492-494. doi: 10.1007/s13142-017-0528-7.</citation>
    <PMID>28929322</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Brunner J, Chuang E, Washington DL, Rose DE, Chanfreau-Coffinier C, Darling JE, Canelo IA, Yano EM. Patient-Rated Access to Needed Care: Patient-Centered Medical Home Principles Intertwined. Womens Health Issues. 2018 Mar - Apr;28(2):165-171. doi: 10.1016/j.whi.2017.12.001. Epub 2018 Jan 12.</citation>
    <PMID>29339012</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Narain K, Bean-Mayberry B, Washington DL, Canelo IA, Darling JE, Yano EM. Access to Care and Health Outcomes Among Women Veterans Using Veterans Administration Health Care: Association With Food Insufficiency. Womens Health Issues. 2018 May - Jun;28(3):267-272. doi: 10.1016/j.whi.2018.01.002. Epub 2018 Feb 21.</citation>
    <PMID>29475630</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hoggatt KJ, Simpson T, Schweizer CA, Drexler K, Yano EM. Identifying women veterans with unhealthy alcohol use using gender-tailored screening. Am J Addict. 2018 Mar;27(2):97-100. doi: 10.1111/ajad.12689.</citation>
    <PMID>29489045</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yano EM, Darling JE, Hamilton AB, Canelo I, Chuang E, Meredith LS, Rubenstein LV. Cluster randomized trial of a multilevel evidence-based quality improvement approach to tailoring VA Patient Aligned Care Teams to the needs of women Veterans. Implement Sci. 2016 Jul 19;11(1):101. doi: 10.1186/s13012-016-0461-z.</citation>
    <PMID>27435723</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 14, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 16, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 20, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 13, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 13, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 15, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Patient-centered medical homes</keyword>
  <keyword>Primary care</keyword>
  <keyword>Women's health</keyword>
  <keyword>Veterans</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

