<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00237341</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR002446</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00237341</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Duragesic速 (Fentanyl Transdermal System) Functionality Trial in Chronic Low Back Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessing Functionality Changes Associated With Patients Who Were Taking Short Acting Opioids Chronically and Who Initiated Treatment With Duragesic速 (Fentanyl Transdermal System) for the Management of Chronic Low Back Pain.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PriCara, Unit of Ortho-McNeil, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PriCara, Unit of Ortho-McNeil, Inc.</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess physical functionality changes over a minimum of 9
      weeks in patients with non-malignant chronic low back pain who are taking short-acting
      opioids (narcotic pain medications) for 4 or more weeks, and who start taking the long-acting
      opioid fentanyl in the form of a transdermal (skin) patch.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic pain (pain that lasts for more than 3 months) can limit physical functioning and
      negatively affect a person socially and emotionally. Chronic low back pain (that is not
      caused by cancer) is a very common condition that affects up to a third of people in the US
      at any time. The primary objective of the trial is to assess functionality changes over a
      minimum period of 9 weeks using the Oswestry Disability Index (ODI) - a questionnaire to
      measure disability - in patients with non-malignant chronic low back pain who are taking
      short-acting opioids chronically, and who initiate treatment with Duragesic速 (transdermal
      fentanyl). The patch delivers fentanyl in doses of 25, 50, 75, or 100 micrograms per hour.
      The ODI is comprised of 10 sections; each section consists of 6 response alternatives. The 10
      scales assessed by the ODI are Pain Intensity, Personal Care (washing, dressing, etc.),
      Lifting, Walking, Sitting, Standing, Sleeping, Sex Life, Social Life, and Traveling. The
      secondary objective is to assess changes in health-related quality of life (HRQoL) over the
      treatment period using the Total Pain Experience (TPE) subscale of the Treatment Outcomes in
      Pain Survey (TOPS), a questionnaire designed to measure HRQoL changes in patients with
      chronic pain. The TOPS contains 112 items that are scored into 16 scales. These scales
      include: Pain Symptoms, Lower Body Functional Limitations, Upper Body Functional Limitations,
      Perceived Family/Social Disability, Objective Family/Social Disability, Objective Work
      Disability, TPE (a combination of 5 other scales), Life Control, Passive Coping, Solicitous
      Responses, Work Limitations, Fear Avoidance, Patient Satisfaction with Outcomes, Health Care
      Satisfaction, Vitality, and Mental Health (the last two from a questionnaire known as the
      Short Form-36, or SF-36. Fentanyl transdermal system (skin patch) in a dosage prescribed by
      the clinical investigator according to the usual standard of care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2004</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment type="Actual">358</enrollment>
  <condition>Low Back Pain</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fentanyl</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronic low back pain (not related to cancer) for at least 3 months

          -  current use of short-acting opioid (narcotic pain medication) for at least 4 weeks

          -  initiating fentanyl transdermal patch.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Confusion or reduced level of consciousness

          -  skin disease

          -  malignancies (cancer)

          -  currently hospitalized

          -  treated with a long-acting opioid within the last 2 months

          -  pregnant or breast-feeding

          -  abusing drugs or alcohol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>PriCara, Unit of Ortho-McNeil, Inc. Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>PriCara, Unit of Ortho-McNeil, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>http://filehosting.pharmacm.com/DownloadService.ashx?client=CTR_JNJ_6051&amp;studyid=1130&amp;filename=CR002446_CSR.pdf</url>
    <description>Assessing functionality changes associated with patients who were taking short acting opioids chronically and who initiated treatment with Duragesic速 for the management of chronic low back pain.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 7, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 7, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 12, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 19, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 19, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 20, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>chronic low back pain</keyword>
  <keyword>opioid</keyword>
  <keyword>fentanyl</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fentanyl</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

