<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00237952</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NMRPG340711</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NSC94-2314-B-182A-125</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00237952</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Environmental Exposure to Lead and Progressive Renal Insufficiency in Type II Diabetic Nephropathy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Environmental Lead Exposure and Progressive Renal Insufficiency in Patients With Type II Diabetes and Diabetic Nephropathy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background The relationship between long-term heavy lead exposure and chronic interstitial
      nephropathy is well recognized in the previous literatures. Several epidemiological studies
      have demonstrated a positive association between blood lead levels and the age related
      decreases of renal function in the general population and suggested that environmental
      low-level lead exposure may accelerate the progression of renal function in the healthy
      persons. In addition, previous our works suggest environmental lead exposure may correlate to
      progressive renal insufficiency and lead chelation therapy or repeated lead chelation may
      improve and slow the progressive renal insufficiency in non-diabetic patients with chronic
      renal diseases. However, Diabetes mellitus is increasing in prevalence worldwide and is
      currently estimated to affect more than 6.5 percent of the population of the United States.
      In addition, diabetes is the most common cause of end-stage renal disease in many countries,
      accounting for about 40 percent of cases. It is still unknown that the relationship between
      long-term environmental lead exposure and the progressive renal insufficiency in patients
      with type II diabetes and diabetic nephropathy.

      Methods Ninety patints with type II diabetes and diabetic nephropathy (serum creatinine
      levels between 1.5 mg per deciliter and 3.9 mg per deciliter) who have a normal body lead
      burden and no history of exposure to lead or other metals will be observed for 24 months.
      Then, about 50 subjects with high normal body lead burdens (at least 80 μg but less than 600
      μg) will be randomly assigned to the study and control groups. For three months, the 25
      patients in the study group will receive lead-chelation therapy with calcium disodium EDTA
      weekly until the body lead burden fallsl below 50 μg, and the 25 control group receive weekly
      placebo. During the ensuing 12 months, the renal function will be regularly followed up every
      3 months and EDTA mobilization tests will be assessed every 6 months. If body lead burden of
      the study group patients increase more than 60μg, the chelation therapy will be performed
      again until their body burden are less than 60 μg. The primary end point is an increase in
      the serum creatinine level to 2 times the base-line value during the observation period. A
      secondary end point is the change in renal function during the follow up period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2005</start_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary end point is an increase in serum creatinine to 1.5 times the base-line value, measured on two occasions one month apart, or the need for hemodialysis during the longitudinal observation period.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A secondary end point is a temporal change in the creatinine clearance or glomerular filtration rate during the follow-up period.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <condition>Diabetic Nephropathies</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type II</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EDTA chelating agents</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients from 20 through 80 years of age who have type II diabetes mellitus with
             diabetic nephropathy and followed up at our hospital for more than one year were
             eligible if they have a serum creatinine concentration between 1.5 mg per deciliter
             (132.6 μmol per liter) and 3.9 mg per deciliter (344.8 μmol per liter), with a daily
             proteinuria more than 0.5g/day and no micro-hematuria in urinalysis tests, normal size
             of both kidneys, retinopathy with laser therapy by ophthalmologists, a history of
             diabetes more than 5 years and no known history of exposure to lead or other heavy
             metals (body lead burden, less than 600 μg [2.90 μmol], as measured by EDTA
             mobilization testing and 72-hour urine collection). Diabetic nephropathy diagnoses are
             based on the patients' history and the results of laboratory evaluations, renal
             imaging, and renal histological examination.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  type I diabetes; renal insufficiency with a potentially reversible cause, such as
             malignant hypertension, urinary tract infection, hypercalcemia, or drug-induced
             nephrotoxic effects; other systemic diseases, such as connective-tissue diseases; use
             of drugs that may alter the course of renal disease, such as non-steroidal
             anti-inflammatory agents, steroids, immunosuppressive drugs or Chinese herb drugs.;
             previous marked exposure to lead (lead poisoning or occupational exposure); drug
             allergies; and absence of informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ja-Liang Lin, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Lin-Kou Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Lin-Kou Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <state>Taiwan</state>
        <zip>105</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <state>Taiwan</state>
        <zip>105</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 11, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 11, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 13, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 21, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 21, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 23, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Nephropathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chelating Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

