<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00236457</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR002026</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00236457</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study Comparing the Efficacy of Long-acting Injectable Risperidone and Olanzapine Tablets in the Treatment of Patients With Schizophrenia or Schizoaffective Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized, Multi-center, Open Label Trial Comparing Risperidone Depot (Microspheres) and Olanzapine Tablets in Patients With Schizophrenia or Schizoaffective Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to document both short-term, as well as long-term efficacy and
      safety of a long-acting injectable formulation of risperidone, in comparison with olanzapine
      for the treatment of patients with schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Many schizophrenia patients currently take oral antipsychotic medications daily, but
      long-acting injectable formulations may eliminate this need for the daily medication. This is
      an open-label study of a flexible does of a long-acting formulation of risperidone injected
      into the muscle at 2 week intervals over 12 months in patients with schizophrenia or
      schizoaffective disorder. A comparator group will receive daily tablets of olanzapine, a
      psychotropic agent available for the treatment of schizophrenia and schizoaffective
      disorders. This is a two-part trial. Patients will be titrated to the most effective dose of
      trial medication during the first 13 weeks and analyzed for short-term efficacy and safety of
      treatment at Week 13. Patients will be then assessed for maintenance of efficacy, safety, and
      resource use at Week 52 (second part of study). Efficacy assessments include the Structured
      Clinical Interview - Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (SCI-PANSS), overall severity of
      illness measured by the Clinical Global Impression (CGI) scale, and quality of life assessed
      by Wisconsin Quality of Life Index (W-QOLI). Safety evaluations include incidence of adverse
      events, Simpson and Angus Rating Scale for extrapyramidal symptoms, physical examinations,
      clinical laboratory tests (biochemistry, haematology, and urinalysis), and electrocardiograms
      (ECGs). The primary study hypothesis is that treatment with long-acting risperidone injected
      intramuscularly every 2 weeks is not inferior to treatment with daily olanzapine in terms of
      short-term efficacy and is well tolerated by patients with schizophrenia or schizoaffective
      disorder. Risperidone injections (25mg or 50mg) every 2 weeks for 12 months. Investigator may
      decrease or increase dosages (max 50mg) or supplement risperidone injections with risperidone
      tablets (4mg/day max.). Control group receives olanzapine tablets (5mg) daily, adjusted as
      necessary (max 20mg).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2002</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline to Week 13 for total score using the Structured Clinical Interview- Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (SCI-PANSS)</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline through each visit and at study end (Week 53) for SCI-PANSS total score, SCI-PANSS subscales, Clinical Global Impression (CGI) and Wisconsin Quality of Life Index (W-QOLI). Safety evaluations throughout the study.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">629</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <condition>Psychotic Disorders</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>risperidone</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder according to criteria of
             Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 4th edition (DMS IV)

          -  Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) total score =&gt;50, indicating at least a
             minimum level of mental and behavioral disorders

          -  Recent hospitalization or an episode of psychosis requiring medical intervention

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) &lt;=40 (BMI &gt;=30 indicates obesity)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of DMS IV Axis I condition other than schizophrenia or schizoaffective
             disorder

          -  History of neuroleptic malignant syndrome, a rare psychotropic-drug reaction, which
             may be characterized by confusion, reduced consciousness, high fever or pronounced
             muscle stiffness

          -  Past treatment with clozapine

          -  Pregnant or nursing females, or those lacking adequate contraception

          -  Known sensitivity or unresponsiveness to risperidone or olanzapine

          -  Treatment with a long-acting injectable antipsychotic drug near the time of the trial
             start
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L. C. Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>http://filehosting.pharmacm.com/DownloadService.ashx?client=CTR_JNJ_6051&amp;studyid=450&amp;filename=CR002026_CSR.pdf</url>
    <description>A study comparing the efficacy of long-acting injectable risperidone and olanzapine tablets in the treatment of patients with schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 7, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 7, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 12, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 6, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 6, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 8, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Schizophrenia</keyword>
  <keyword>Intramuscular injection</keyword>
  <keyword>Antipsychotic agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Long-acting risperidone</keyword>
  <keyword>Olanzapine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Risperidone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Olanzapine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

