<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02415816</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DWSARC</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2015-00290</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02415816</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diffusion Weighted Magnetic Resonance in Imaging Younger Patients With Newly Diagnosed Bone or Soft Tissue Sarcomas</brief_title>
  <official_title>Diffusion Weighted Magnetic Resonance Imaging in Pediatric Sarcomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Children with sarcomas are routinely assessed with a variety of imaging techniques that
      involve the use of ionizing radiation. These include computed tomography (CT), nuclear bone
      scan, and positron emission tomography-CT (PET-CT). Pediatric sarcoma patients undergo many
      imaging studies at the time of diagnosis, during therapy and for years following completion
      of therapy. Because children are in a stage of rapid growth, their tissues and organs are
      more susceptible to the harmful effects of ionizing radiation than are adults. Furthermore,
      compared to adults, children have a longer life expectancy and, therefore, a longer period of
      time in which to develop the adverse sequelae of radiation exposure, such as the development
      of second malignancies.

      Alternative experimental methods of measuring tumor response will be compared to current
      standard of care measures to determine if the experimental method is equivalent to methods
      currently being used. Investigators wish to determine if they can reduce patient's exposure
      to the harmful effects of ionizing radiation by replacing imaging studies that use radiation
      with whole body diffusion weighted magnetic resonance imaging (DW-MRI) which does not use any
      radiation. They also want to know if DW-MRI measurements of the tumor can tell how well the
      tumor is responding to therapy. There have been studies in adults with cancer that have shown
      that DW-MRI provides useful information about how tumors are responding to therapy. There
      have only been very small studies of DW-MRI in children with tumors in the body. Therefore,
      the role of DW-MRI in pediatric sarcoma patients is not yet known and it is still
      experimental. This study might give us important information that could help us treat other
      children with bone or soft tissue sarcomas in the future.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Whole body (WB) and primary tumor diffusion weighted imaging (DWI) will be performed at
      baseline in all subjects. Additional DW-MRIs will be done up to 3 times during treatment at
      the same time as routine MRI examinations are scheduled. Follow-up primary tumor DWI MRI
      examinations will be performed at time points determined by the participant's therapeutic
      treatment protocol. Follow-up primary tumor DWI examinations will be performed until
      completion of local control (surgical resection or completion of radiation therapy). All
      examinations will be performed on 1.5T Siemens magnetic resonance (MR) scanners unless there
      is a clinical indication for 3T imaging.

      Because investigators will correlate imaging parameters with patient outcome, participants
      will be followed until they are discharged to the After Completion of Therapy Clinic or until
      they have tumor progression or recurrence or develop a second malignancy or death, whichever
      comes first.

      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

        -  To estimate the proportion of pediatric sarcoma patients whose bone/bone marrow and
           soft-tissue metastasis status are correctly staged by whole body diffusion weighted MRI
           (WB DWI) at the time of diagnosis by comparing it to clinical stage.

        -  To determine the correlation between changes in primary pediatric sarcoma
           18F-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography (FDG PET) maximum standardized
           uptake values (SUVmax) and average DWI apparent diffusion coefficient (ADC) values from
           baseline (pre-treatment) to just prior to local control.

      OTHER PRESPECIFIED OBJECTIVES:

        -  To estimate the sensitivity, specificity, accuracy, and negative and positive predictive
           values of WB DWI, PET-CT and PET-CT + bone scan for detecting sites of metastatic tumor
           in pediatric sarcomas using biopsy or clinical follow-up (including imaging studies and
           clinical information) as the reference standards.

        -  To compare the ability of WB MRI, PET-CT and PET-CT + bone scan to detect all sites of
           metastases in pediatric sarcoma patients using biopsy and clinical judgment as the
           reference standards.

        -  To examine the associations of DWI ADC values of primary tumors at diagnosis and
           treatment protocol driven time points during therapy with tumor histology, tumor grade,
           RECIST response, % tumor necrosis, FDG SUVmax and patient outcome.

        -  To compare whole body DWI to conventional T1W and STIR whole body MRI for the detection
           of nodal, bone/bone marrow, soft-tissue or lung metastases among pediatric bone and
           soft-tissue sarcoma patients using biopsy and clinical judgment as the reference
           standards.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 5, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2027</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants with pediatric sarcomas whose bone/bone marrow and soft-tissue metastasis status is correctly staged with whole body DWI MRI</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at time of diagnosis (day 0 within about 5 days)</time_frame>
    <description>To allow for blinding, reading of scan images will be delayed at least 2 months and up to 6 months following scan.
Proportion of participants whose bone/bone marrow and soft-tissue metastases were detected with whole body DWI MRI</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary tumor DWI ADC and FDG PET SUVmax values at baseline and protocol driven time points up until local control</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at time of diagnosis (day 0 within about 5 days) to local control (up to 18 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>The primary tumor DWI ADC (in mm^2/sec) and FDG PET SUVmax (unitless) values at baseline and protocol driven time points up until local control.
Local control is defined as surgical resection or initiation of radiation therapy.
To allow for blinding, reading of scan images will be delayed at least 2 months and up to 6 months following scan.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The number of metastatic lesions detected and not detected with whole body DWI MRI, PET-CT alone and PET-CT + bone scan at the time of diagnosis of a pediatric sarcoma</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at time of diagnosis (day 0 within about 5 days)</time_frame>
    <description>The number of metastatic lesions detected and not detected with whole body DWI MRI, PET-CT alone and PET-CT + bone scan by using biopsy or clinical follow-up as the reference standards. Metastatic sites will be reported in groups by region (bone/bone marrow, lymph nodes, lung and soft-tissue) and all groups together.
To allow for blinding, reading of scan images will be delayed at least 2 months and up to 6 months following scan.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of WB DWI MRIs, PET-CTs and PET-CT + bone scans that correctly identify sites of metastatic disease in patients with newly diagnosed sarcoma.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at diagnosis (day 0 within about 5 days)</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of DWI MRI scans , PET-CTs and PET-CT + bone scan that correctly identify bone/bone marrow, nodal, lung and soft-tissue metastases in pediatric sarcoma patients at the time of diagnosis.
To allow for blinding, reading of scan images will be delayed at least 2 months and up to 6 months following scan.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Primary tumor ADC values for each tumor histology group (osteosarcoma, Ewing sarcoma, non-rhabdomyosarcoma soft-tissue sarcoma and rhabdomyosarcoma (RMS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at diagnosis (day 0 within about 5 days) and at protocol driven time points up to 18 weeks (time of local control).</time_frame>
    <description>To allow for blinding, reading of scan images will be delayed at least 2 months and up to 6 months following scan.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Primary tumor ADC values for low vs intermediate vs high grade tumors</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at diagnosis (day 0 within about 5 days) and at protocol driven time points up to 18 weeks (time of local control).</time_frame>
    <description>To allow for blinding, reading of scan images will be delayed at least 2 months and up to 6 months following scan.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Primary tumor ADC values for tumors grouped by % necrosis in increments of 10% or 20% (i.e. 10%, 20% etc or 20%, 40% etc, whichever is most relevant)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at diagnosis (day 0 within about 5 days) and at protocol driven time points up to 18 weeks (time of local control).</time_frame>
    <description>To allow for blinding, reading of scan images will be delayed at least 2 months and up to 6 months following scan.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Primary tumor ADC values for RECIST response groups (complete remission, partial remission, stable disease, progressive disease)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at diagnosis (day 0 within about 5 days) and at protocol driven time points up to 18 weeks (time of local control).</time_frame>
    <description>To allow for blinding, reading of scan images will be delayed at least 2 months and up to 6 months following scan.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Primary tumor ADC values for FDG SUVmax values</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at diagnosis (day 0 within about 5 days) and at protocol driven time points up to 18 weeks (time of local control).</time_frame>
    <description>To allow for blinding, reading of scan images will be delayed at least 2 months and up to 6 months following scan.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Event free survival)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at diagnosis (day 0 within about 5 days) and at protocol driven time points up to 5 years after the end of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Event free survival is defined as the time between end of therapy and tumor progression/recurrence, development of a second malignancy or death, whichever comes first.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at diagnosis (day 0 within about 5 days) up to 6 years after starting cancer therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival is defined as the percentage of participants still alive at the end of follow-up after starting cancer therapy.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of WB DWI, T1W and STIR MRIs that correctly identify all sites of metastatic disease in patients with newly diagnosed pediatric sarcoma.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at diagnosis (day 0 within 7±2 days)</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of WB DWI, T1W and STIR MRIs that correctly identify metastatic disease grouped by site (bone/bone marrow, lymph node, lung and soft-tissue) as well as all sites together.
To allow for blinding, reading of scan images will be delayed at least 2 months and up to 6 months following scan.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Sarcoma, Bone</condition>
  <condition>Sarcoma, Soft Tissue</condition>
  <condition>Osteosarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Sarcoma, Ewing</condition>
  <condition>Rhabdomyosarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Non-rhabdomyosarcoma Soft-tissue Sarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients who consent to participate in this protocol. They will have diffusion weighted magnetic resonance imaging performed at several time points.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diffusion Weighted Magnetic Resonance Imaging</intervention_name>
    <description>Diffusion weighted magnetic resonance imaging (DWI MRI) is a method that does not involve radiation and can be used to assess the primary tumor as well as to image the entire patient, from head to toe. Diffusion weighted MRI uses a strong motion probing gradient to detect the movement of water in tissue. Tissues that are composed of tightly packed cells, such as tumors, allow less water movement than tissues with loosely packed cells. As tumors respond to therapy they become necrotic and cells are less tightly packed. This change in water diffusivity can be quantitated using DWI. Therefore, DWI provides a non-invasive, non-ionizing, and quantitative method of assessing tumor response at a cellular level and does not depend on a change in tumor size</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participants</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DWI-MRI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All St Jude patients with a known or suspected, newly diagnosed bone or soft-tissue
             sarcoma who will be treated on or as per disease specific protocols.

          -  Study subjects will have undergone or are scheduled for PET-CT and/or bone scan within
             about 2 weeks of the WB and primary tumor DWI MRI.

          -  No limit on age or gender

          -  Informed consent or assent signed by study subject or parent/guardian according to
             institutional guidelines.

          -  Patients should not have begun therapy, or, needed research imaging can be performed
             within 2-5 days of starting therapy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has a tumor that will undergo upfront resection

          -  Subject is unable or unwilling to follow study requirements, including signed consent
             or assent

          -  Subject is hospitalized in the intensive care unit.

          -  Subject does not meet institutional MRI safety screening requirements.

          -  Subject has undergone primary tumor resection prior to arrival at St. Jude.

          -  Subjects who require sedation for WB MRI will be excluded if they have:

               -  An acute cardiopulmonary process including, but not limited to, croup, reactive
                  airways disease, pneumonia, clinical or radiological evidence of pericardial
                  effusion or other cardiopulmonary disease.

               -  Vomiting within 24 hours of the MRI or substantial nausea that may preclude
                  sedation as determined by the anesthesiologist or certified registered nurse
                  anesthetist.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mary E. McCarville, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mary E. McCarville, MD</last_name>
    <phone>866-278-5833</phone>
    <email>referralinfo@stjude.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mary E. McCarville, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>866-278-5833</phone>
      <email>referralinfo@stjude.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mary E. McCarville, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.stjude.org</url>
    <description>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.stjude.org/protocols</url>
    <description>Clinical Trials Open at St. Jude</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 9, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 13, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 14, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pediatric</keyword>
  <keyword>Whole body DWI MRI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteosarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rhabdomyosarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma, Ewing</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

