<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02411227</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>150103</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>15-CC-0103</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02411227</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neurocognitive Driving Rehabilitation in Virtual Environments (NeuroDRIVE) as an Adjunctive Intervention for Traumatic Brain Injury</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Neurocognitive Driving Rehabilitation in Virtual Environments (NeuroDRIVE) as an Adjunctive Intervention for Traumatic Brain Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Center for Neuroscience and Regenerative Medicine (CNRM)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - People with traumatic brain injury (TBI) can have problems with thinking and everyday
      activities. They may have a higher risk for car accidents. NeuroDRIVE uses a virtual reality
      driving simulator. Researchers think it can help test and improve how people think and drive
      after TBI.

      Objective:

      - To test how NeuroDRIVE affects brain performance and driving safety.

      Eligibility:

      - People at least 18 years old with a history of TBI and who had a driver s license at some
      point. They must speak, read, and write English and be physically able to drive.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be asked to release their driving records, but they do not have to do
           this to be in the study.

        -  Visit 1: Screening physical exam.

        -  Visit 2: Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan. Participants will lie on a table that
           slides into a cylinder with a strong magnetic field. A device will be placed over the
           head. Participants may do computer tasks during the scan.

        -  Participants will have tests of memory, attention, and thinking. They may be asked
           questions, take tests, and do simple actions.

        -  Visit 3: Tests of memory, attention, and thinking, plus a virtual reality driving
           assessment.

        -  Participants will be assigned to Group 1 to start NeuroDRIVE training immediately or
           Group 2 to start 10 weeks later.

        -  Visits 4 9, over 4 weeks:

        -  Participants will practice driving skills and mental exercises in the simulator.

        -  They will complete a driving questionnaire online each week.

        -  Visit 10: Repeat of Visit 3, with some small changes.

        -  Visits 11-12: Very similar to Visits 1-2. Includes MRI scan; physical exam;
           questionnaires; and tests of thinking, memory, and attention..

        -  After Visit 12: Participants will fill out a weekly driving survey online for 4 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVE:

      The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the NeuroDRIVE behavioral intervention for
      enhancement of driving abilities, cognitive abilities, and neurobehavioral symptoms after
      traumatic brain injury (TBI). For the purposes of this protocol, NeuroDRIVE refers to the
      novel combined approach of driving training and cognitive rehabilitation in a virtual reality
      environment. While NeuroDRIVE utilizes the VR system as the method through which the
      intervention is administered, NeuroDRIVE is not the VR system itself.

      STUDY POPULATION:

      30 adult patients with a history of mild TBI and 30 adult patients with a history of
      moderate-to-severe TBI. Participants will be recruited from the National Institutes of Health
      (NIH), WRNMMC, and the broader community.

      DESIGN:

      The current study is a Clinical Trial Phase II interventional research study. The primary
      purpose of the study is for treatment, and it will employ a parallel intervention model.
      There will be no masking (i.e., open label). Participants will be classified into two groups
      by TBI severity: those with history of mild TBI and those with history of moderate-tosevere
      TBI. These different severities are known to have distinct cognitive sequelae. Within each
      severity group, participants will be in a 2 (pre-post) x 2 (treatment vs. wait list)
      experimental design.

      OUTCOME MEASURES:

      Primary outcome measures will include:

        -  Results from the Virtual Reality Driving Assessment (baseline and postintervention
           Tactical scenario composite scores)

        -  Total scores on the Neurobehavioral Symptom Inventory

        -  Standard and scaled scores from the following cognitive assessments (from the TBI Common
           Data Elements identified by NINDS):

      WAIS-IV or WMS-IV Digit Span subtest

      WAIS-IV Digit-Symbol Coding subtest

      Secondary outcome measures will include:

      -Neuroimaging results:

      Regions of Interest for FMRI: Bilateral dorsolateral prefrontal cortex

      Regions of Interest for DTI: Corpus callosum, bilateral frontal white matter horns, and
      bilateral longitudinal fasciculi

      -Total scores on the following symptom questionnaires:

      Glasgow Outcome Scale-Extended (GOS-E)

      Ohio State University TBI Identification Method

      Brief Symptom Inventory- 18

      Satisfaction with Life Scale (SWLS)

      PTSD Checklist- Civilian (PCL-C)

      SF-36v2 Health Survey (SF-36v2)

      Fatigue Severity Scale (FSS)

      Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS)

      Beck Depression Inventory-II (BDI-II)

      Combat Exposure Scale (CES)

      Dual Dangerous Driving Index (DDDI)

      -Standard and scaled scores from the following cognitive phenotyping assessments (from the
      TBI Common Data Elements identified by NINDS):

      California Verbal Learning Test- Second Edition (CVLT-II)

      WAIS-IV Symbol Search subtest

      Medical Symptom Validity Test (MSVT)

      -Standard and scaled scores from the following additional cognitive phenotyping assessments:

      Trail Making Test (TMT)

      Test of Premorbid Functioning (ToPF)

      Grooved Pegboard

      Controlled Oral Word Association Test (COWAT)

      Bethesda Eye and Attention Measure (BEAM)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 7, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 20, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 20, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>VR Driving, Cognitive test, and Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MRI, Phenotyping, &amp;amp; Driving evals</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">37</enrollment>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Immediate Intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Wait list</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VR Driving</intervention_name>
    <description>Baseline: Tactical scenario, composite score Post-Assessment: Tactical scenario composite score</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Subjects eligible for participation must meet the following criteria:

          1. Currently has a valid driver s license, or had a valid driver s license prior to
             injury

          2. 18 years of age or older

          3. Able to effectively manipulate the steering wheel and the gas/brake pedals without
             adaptive equipment

          4. Able to read, write, and speak in English

          5. History of traumatic brain injury greater than 12 weeks prior to initiation into the
             current study

          6. Able to provide informed consent

          7. NBSI score greater than or equal to 16 (Mild TBI sub-group only)

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Subjects are not eligible for participation if any of the following conditions exist:

          1. Risk for injury from the MRI magnet, including:

               -  Pacemakers or other implanted electrical devices.

               -  Brain stimulators.

               -  Some types of dental implants.

               -  Aneurysm clips (metal clips on the wall of a large artery).

               -  Metallic prostheses (including metal pins and rods, heart valves, and cochlear
                  implants).

               -  Permanent eyeliner (other non-metallic tattoos are permissible).

               -  Implanted delivery pump.

               -  Shrapnel fragments.

               -  Welders and metal workers are also at risk for injury because of possible small
                  metal fragments in the eye of which they may be unaware.

               -  Fear of confined spaces.

               -  Back problems that may result in back pain or discomfort from lying in the
                  scanner.

               -  Weight of over 350 pounds, due to the weight limit of the MRI table.

               -  It is not known if MRI is completely safe for a developing fetus. Therefore, all
                  women of childbearing potential will have a pregnancy test performed no more than
                  24 hours before each MRI scan. The scan will not be done if the pregnancy test is
                  positive. Because neuroimaging is a key component of the current study, inability
                  to participate in MRI scanning is a necessary exclusion criterion.

          2. History of penetrating brain injury

          3. History of serious medical condition other than TBI that could affect cognitive or
             motor abilities (e.g., multiple sclerosis, encephalitis, cerebrovascular disease)

          4. History of severe motion sickness and/or vertigo.

          5. Other medical or psychological instability that could create difficulty fulfilling the
             study requirements (e.g., untreated mental illness, auditory/visual hallucinations,
             narcolepsy)

        To verify this information, study coordinators will request medical records (i.e., recent
        medical history, medication list, any neuroimaging, and records pertinent to the
        participant s recent injury) to further evaluate potential participants inclusion into the
        study. Medical records can be obtained in three ways:

          1. Participants can bring the records when they come to NIH for testing; it will be made
             clear if they do not bring this information with them and we cannot verify that they
             meet inclusion criteria, potential participants will not be enrolled into the study
             that day.

          2. Alternatively, the participants can also fax their medical records to a secured fax
             machine at the Recreational Therapy office at the NIH where access is only permitted
             to study staff (i.e., scheduler, physician, and nurse psychologist).

          3. Participants may also fill out a medical release document and submit it to the study
             coordinator.

        Medical history data will be reviewed, and if it is clear that the patient does not meet
        the inclusion criteria, we will contact them and cancel their appointment. Data obtained in
        this manner may be used to evaluate participant eligibility; however, it will not be used
        for any research purposes. Additionally, for any patients who are deemed not eligible to
        participate, their medical history data will be destroyed in accordance with NIH
        regulations.

        As a condition of receiving funding from CNRM, de-identified imaging and phenotyping data
        (i.e., neurocognitive test results and behavioral questionnaires) from funded studies must
        be made available within a centralized repository (the CNRM Informatics Core) one year
        after the completion of the study. This is intended to facilitate use and analysis of this
        data for future research questions or projects. As such, potential subjects will be
        informed that they should not participate in this study if they do not want their data used
        for other projects.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leighton Chan, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_2015-CC-0103.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ortoleva C, Brugger C, Van der Linden M, Walder B. Prediction of driving capacity after traumatic brain injury: a systematic review. J Head Trauma Rehabil. 2012 Jul-Aug;27(4):302-13. doi: 10.1097/HTR.0b013e3182236299. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21897289</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cox DJ, Davis M, Singh H, Barbour B, Nidiffer FD, Trudel T, Mourant R, Moncrief R. Driving rehabilitation for military personnel recovering from traumatic brain injury using virtual reality driving simulation: a feasibility study. Mil Med. 2010 Jun;175(6):411-6.</citation>
    <PMID>20572473</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 16, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 7, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 7, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 8, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neuropsychologic Testing</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurocognitive</keyword>
  <keyword>Virtual Reality</keyword>
  <keyword>Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Driving</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

