<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02415855</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CSC2012-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02415855</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Canadian Pradaxa Acute Stroke Safety Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>CPASS</acronym>
  <official_title>Canadian Pradaxa Acute Stroke Safety Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alberta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Boehringer Ingelheim</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alberta</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Study Design:

      This is a multicentre, prospective, open-label, single arm, phase IV registry study. No
      additional procedures are included in the study. Standard clinical data will be collected.
      This will include a physical examination and NIHSS score assessment at baseline. In addition,
      all neuro-imaging will be collected. Standard imaging includes a non-contrast CT brain at
      baseline and 7±2 days post-treatment. Repeat NIHSS score assessment at the time of the 7 day
      CT scan. Repeat clinical and NIHSS score assessment 30 days post-enrolment will also be
      collected when performed as part of standard care.

      Study Objectives:

        1. Demonstrate the safety of early dabigatran initiation after minor stroke/TIA in patients
           with atrial fibrillation.

        2. Determine the frequency of asymptomatic hemorrhagic transformation after 7 days of
           dabigatran treatment following stroke/TIA

        3. Determine the effect of asymptomatic hemorrhagic transformation on functional and
           neurological outcome at 30 days.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Aim and Design:

      The primary aim of the CPASS registry is to demonstrate the safety of early anticoagulation
      with dabigatran following cardioembolic stroke. CPASS is a prospective open label single arm
      observational study. Safety will be established by demonstrating low rates of hemorrhage in
      this setting.

      Administrative Structure:

      CPASS is a Canadian Stroke Consortium led study. The study coordinating centre is at the
      University of Alberta. Case report forms and data monitoring will be completed
      electronically, using an online EDC system. All imaging data will be read centrally at the
      Stroke Imaging Laboratory at the University of Alberta.

      Study Design Considerations:

      A randomized controlled design was considered (dabigatran versus warfarin). This is
      considered impractical for a number of reasons. Novel oral anticoagulants are recommended as
      first line agents for stroke prevention in AF patients by the Canadian Cardiovascular
      Society.19 These agents are associated with improved safety with respect to bleeding
      complications. This makes randomization of a patient to warfarin who would otherwise be
      prescribed dabigatran somewhat ethically dubious. In addition, a randomized design would
      necessitate a very large study, which would not be completed in a reasonable period of time.
      A registry design allows us to address the question of safety in a systematic fashion. A
      safety threshold has been defined for any anticoagulant use early after stroke, based on the
      rates of warfarin-associated intracranial hemorrhage, which have been reported to be 0.5 to
      2.5 per 100 patient years.20-24 The registry design therefore permits determination of
      whether or not dabigatran is within this threshold. Finally, the systematic collection of
      clinical and imaging data will allow us to determine any risk factors for hemorrhagic
      transformation associated with early anticoagulation.

      Prescribed Study Treatments:

      Patients in whom dabigatran is initiated within 14 days of TIA/stroke symptom onset will be
      included in the registry. Patients will be treated either at a dose of 110 mg BID or 150 mg
      BID. The dose and timing of initiation of therapy within that 14 day window will be
      determined by the treating physician. The factors related to physician choice of initiation
      time (relative to symptom onset) will be recorded.

      Visit Schedule / Clinical Data Collection:

      Standard clinical assessments and data will be collected. This will include baseline National
      Institutes of Health Stroke Scale NIHSS, Glasgow Coma Scale (GCS) and vital signs, which will
      be recorded in a case report form. Stroke risk factors, past medical history and medications,
      baseline complete blood count, coagulation profile and renal function tests will also be
      recorded. CHADS2 and CHADSVaSC scores will also be recorded. Clinical endpoints will be
      ischemic stroke or intracranial hemorrhage within 30 days of anticoagulant initiation. All
      cerebral ischemic and intracranial hemorrhagic endpoints will be centrally adjudicated from
      anonymized clinical records, with the intracranial hemorrhages classified as described above.
      A data collection form will be filled out for each subject at 30 days post-enrolment
      indicating clinical status and occurrence of outcome events.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 18, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>30 Days</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptomatic Hemorrhagic Transformation Rate (PH2)</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Symptomatic Hemorrhagic Transformation Rate (PH2) associated with clinical deterioration, defined as worsening of NIHSS score of 4 or more points within 30 days of initiating dabigatran therapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Any parenchymal haemorrhage (PH1 or PH2)</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days post-enrollemnt</time_frame>
    <description>Any parenchymal haemorrhage (PH1 or PH2) on follow-up CT scan at 7±2 days post-enrolment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptomatic hemorrhagic transformation rate</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days post enrolment</time_frame>
    <description>Symptomatic hemorrhagic transformation rate (defined as above) in patients treated with warfarin prior to the index stroke/TIA.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurrent TIA/Ischemic Stroke</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days post enrolment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Systemic hemorrhagic complication rate</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days post enrolment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Ischemic Attack, Transient</condition>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dabigatran</intervention_name>
    <other_name>Pradaxa</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Minor Stroke (NIHSS Score ≤ 3) and Transient Ischemic Attack Patients ≥ 18 years of age,
        with a known history of or demonstrated atrial fibrillation (paroxysmal or persistent), who
        can be treated with dabigatran following stroke.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. All patients will be ≥ 18 years of age.

          2. Minor ischemic stroke, defined as NIHSS score ≤ 3. Transient Ischemic Attack (TIA),
             defined as acute focal neurological deficits, with complete resolution of symptoms
             within 24 h of onset. In cases where onset time cannot be established, it will be
             considered to be the time when the patient was last known to be well.

          3. Atrial Fibrillation (AF, paroxysmal or persistent). AF must be confirmed with
             ECG/Holter monitor, or by history All patients prescribed dabigatran according to the
             Canadian product label by the treating physician following their stroke/TIA. The
             decision to treat with dabigatran and the timing of the first dose will be determined
             by the attending physician, independent of the registry. All patients will have a CT
             scan or MRI, with findings consistent with an ischemic etiology of symptoms.

          4. Ability to obtain informed consent obtained from patient or legally authorized
             representative.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Acute or chronic renal failure, defined as eGFR &lt;30 ml/min (Cockcroft Gault formula).

          2. Known hypersensitivity to dabigatran or any other contraindication to dabigatran
             therapy, as per Canadian label information.

          3. Prior treatment with dabigatran or any other novel oral anticoagulant (including all
             Factor Xa antagonists). Treatment with warfarin prior to the stroke/TIA is acceptable,
             but enrolment cannot begin until the INR is ≤1.5.

          4. Prior symptomatic ischemic stroke (TIA is not an exclusion criterion)

          5. Any significant ongoing systemic bleeding risk, i.e. active GI/GU bleeding or recent
             major surgery.

          6. Clinically significant recent past history or clinical presentation of ICH,
             subarachnoid haemorrhage (SAH), arterio-venous (AV) malformation, aneurysm, or
             cerebral neoplasm. At the discretion of each Investigator.

          7. Hereditary or acquired hemorrhagic diathesis.

          8. Anticipated inability to comply with follow up.

          9. Any condition that, in the judgment of the investigator could impose hazards to the
             patient if study therapy is initiated or affect the participation of the patient in
             the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alberta</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 2B7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1Y 4E9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 9, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 9, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 14, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 25, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alberta</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ken Butcher</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemic Attack, Transient</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dabigatran</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

