<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02412293</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AKU-AKHSP</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02412293</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Community-based Perinatal and Newborn Care in Gilgit District, Northern Areas, Pakistan: an AKU-AKHSP Collaboration</brief_title>
  <official_title>Community-based Perinatal and Newborn Care in Gilgit District, Northern Areas, Pakistan: an AKU-AKHSP Collaboration</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Aga Khan University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aga Khan Health Services</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Aga Khan University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There is limited evidence from community-based interventions to guide the development of
      effective maternal, perinatal and newborn care practices and services in developing
      countries. Investigators planned to evaluate the impact of a low-cost package of
      community-based interventions implemented through government sector lady health workers
      (LHWs) and community health workers (CHWs) of a NGO namely Aga Khan Health Services on
      perinatal and neonatal outcomes in a sub-population of the remote mountainous district of
      Gilgit, Northern Pakistan.

      A community-based package for use by LHWs and CHWs geared towards prevention and promotion of
      maternal and newborn health practices and services will be developed based on formative
      research in the study district. The package will include promotion of antenatal care,
      adequate nutrition, skilled delivery and healthy newborn care practices at household level.
      The health workers will be trained in recognition of danger sign that warrant referral to
      health care service. LHWs and CHWs will delivered the package via community awareness
      sessions and two one-to-one counselling sessions to pregnant women during third trimester and
      five newborn assessment visits in the neonatal period. In addition to this, community
      mobilization activities included formation of CHCs and creation of support for the uptake of
      the interventions. Control areas will continue to receive the routine standard health
      services of governmental and non-governmental organizations in the area. The intervention
      areas will receive the intervention package in addition to the routine standard health
      services. Outcome measures will include changes in maternal and newborn-care practices and
      perinatal and neonatal mortality rates between the intervention and control areas.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The World Health Organization estimates that globally over 9 million infants die annually
      before birth or in the first few weeks of life, and that the majority of these deaths occur
      in the neonatal period. The bulk of these deaths result from pregnancy or delivery associated
      complications, premature births, intrauterine growth retardation and infectious diseases.

      There are over seven million perinatal deaths annually globally mostly in developing
      countries. Almost 4 million newborns suffer moderate to severe birth asphyxia, with at least
      800,000 dying and probably a higher number developing sequel such as epilepsy, mental
      retardation, cerebral palsy and learning disabilities. A recent community based study in
      Zimbabwe, which audited perinatal mortality showed the commonest single cause was perinatal
      asphyxia and an avoidable factor was detected in 76% of cases. In another population based
      study in Bangladesh, which showed a perinatal mortality rate of 75 per 1000 births (37
      stillbirths, 38 first week deaths), the major causes of early neonatal death were attributed
      to a small size at birth (54%), birth asphyxia (26%), and tetanus (8%). In Bangalore, South
      India a prospective hospital based study of 4572 births showed a perinatal mortality of
      43/1000. Using the Wiggles worth's classification , 24% were considered due to birth
      asphyxia, even after exclusion of the premature group. Similarly a recent evaluation of a
      large hospital-based birth cohort for perinatal deaths in Karachi according to the Wiggles
      worth's criteria, indicated that almost 30% of all deaths were related to acute asphyxia.

      Hypotheses

        1. A concerted and coordinated community-based program of training first level primary care
           workers i.e. TBAs, LHWs, lady health visitors and rural health center physicians in the
           prevention, early recognition and management of common perinatal / neonatal problems
           will result in a significant reduction in perinatal and neonatal mortality in the
           Northern areas of Pakistan.

        2. A coordinated program of community education and awareness in the importance of
           perinatal care, prevention and recognition of neonatal problems will lead to improved
           neonatal health, better recognition of neonatal problems and care-seeking behavior.

        3. The strengthening of secondary care perinatal and newborn care and reproductive health
           services will lead to improved referral patterns for perinatal / neonatal problems with
           better outcome.

        4. Increasing the community awareness of neonatal problems and training of first level
           primary care workers will result in better domiciliary management of neonatal problems.

      Phase 1: Formative Research The objectives of this first phase of the study are as follows

        1. Determination of preconditions for studying care seeking practices (referral system,
           availability of BHU staff, doctors, LHVs)

        2. Focusing questions for formative research on care-seeking and causes of perinatal /
           neonatal morbidity / mortality by a modified perinatal / neonatal verbal autopsy)

        3. Rapid anthropological assessment of care-seeking behavior

        4. Illness Episode and Channel Survey

        5. Analysis of results of formative research

        6. Identification of desired behaviors and changes

        7. Selection of behaviors for intervention and their potential acceptability

        8. Acceptability of planned intervention(s) for families, communities and care providers
           and possible additional structural changes

      This initial phase of formative research, will be conducted in the
      Hunza-Karimabad/Nagar/Gojal tehsils of the Gilgit District of the Northern areas. A combined
      methodology of KAP survey and verbal/social autopsy will be employed. These will include an
      in-depth evaluation of knowledge, attitude and practices of families and primary care givers
      (TBAs, LHWs, LHVs and BHU/RHC staff) with regards to

        -  Common causes of maternal morbidity in pregnancy

        -  Maternal nutrition and dietary patterns in pregnancy

        -  Determinants of care seeking behavior during pregnancy and labor

             -  Domiciliary versus hospital births

             -  Selection of care givers by families

             -  Reasons for referral by primary care givers

        -  Perception and recognition of danger signs during child birth by families and care
           givers

        -  Immediate and early newborn care practices (colostrum and prelacteal feeding,
           breastfeeding, cord care, temperature regulation, swaddling, skin care etc).

        -  Concepts of early neonatal morbidity and health seeking behavior;

             -  Risk factors for birth asphyxia and meconium aspiration

             -  Low birth weight and temperature regulation

             -  Neonatal infection (local and generalized)

             -  Seizures or spasms

             -  Respiratory problems

             -  Jaundice

             -  Feeding difficulty

      Phase 2: Implementation phase

      The overall objectives of this phase of the intervention are introduction and implementation
      of simple education and training materials for families and caregivers for community-based
      perinatal and newborn care by means of a phased introduction of the program in the area. In
      addition primary care givers in the target villages of the study area would receive training
      in stabilization and early referral of sick newborns for secondary care.

      The intervention package, consisting of awareness creation about positive maternal and
      newborn health care practices at household level such as importance of; seeking antenatal
      care, adequate nutrition during pregnancy and lactation, skilled birth attendance, early
      initiation of breastfeeding, delayed bathing recognition of danger signs that warrant for
      early referrals, will be developed in collaboration with the Aga Khan Health Services,
      Pakistan. The practices will promote though community mobilization and education strategy
      that included formation of Community Health Committee (CHC) and group education sessions
      using flip charts and videos.

      The LHWs and CHWs in the intervention areas will provide with enhanced trainings on causes of
      perinatal and newborn mortality and risky maternal and newborn care practices and expecting
      to transmit the knowledge to the families to avoid such practices. They will receive training
      in delivering the intervention package through standardized workshops including hands on
      practice on use of specific Information Education and Communication (IEC) materials developed
      for this purpose. The recently modified and simplified integrated management of neonatal and
      childhood illnesses (IMNCI) based system formed the basis of screening, recognition of danger
      signs and referral. The CHWs will deliver interventions in LHW uncovered areas within the
      intervention areas.

      Control areas will continue to receive the routine services of governmental and
      non-governmental organizations in the area. But the public health care facilities of both
      intervention and control areas will receive similar competency based trainings in
      stabilization and early referral of sick newborns for secondary care.

      The intervention Package The LHWs and CHWs will receive trainings on IMNCI-based training
      package. They will also receive orientation about the purpose of the project and how can they
      facilitate group education session by using flip charts and videos. The community-based
      health education sessions will be introduced targeting local communities to sensitize them
      regarding maternal, perinatal and newborn health issues.

      In addition to this, Two days training workshops will be organized to train TBAs in
      intervention areas on &quot;Clean Delivery Practices&quot; at nearest health facilities. The UNICEF
      manual of (DAI) training will be adopted for this training.

      The intervention package will be delivered through monthly household visits, one-to-one
      counseling sessions with pregnant women and video sessions in communities. Additionally, LHWs
      and CHWs in the intervention areas will record information about home visits, newborn
      illnesses, referrals, live births and deaths on special format designed for this project.

      For community mobilization and education, two types of tools will be used one group session
      by use of flip charts and group session by use of video. Participants will be invited from
      all Muhallas (Sub-geographical distribution of the village population) to attend the session,
      facilitated by LHW/CHW to organize the session. Separate sessions will be organized for males
      and females. One session per area will be organized on quarterly basis in local school or LHW
      health house or CHW household within intervention areas. Target groups will be women of
      reproductive age, adolescent girls, fathers, mothers and fathers in law and mothers in law.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in perinatal and neonatal mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Baseline &amp; Endline Surveys</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvements in antenatal care practices</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Years</time_frame>
    <description>Baseline &amp; Endline Surveys</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvements in cord application practices</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Years</time_frame>
    <description>Baseline &amp; Endline Surveys</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvements in delaying first bath after birth</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Years</time_frame>
    <description>Baseline &amp; Endline Surveys</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvements in colostrum administration</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Years</time_frame>
    <description>Baseline &amp; Endline Surveys</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvements in initiation of breastfeeding practices within 1 hour after birth</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Years</time_frame>
    <description>Baseline &amp; Endline Surveys</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">3200</enrollment>
  <condition>Perinatal Problems</condition>
  <condition>Still Births</condition>
  <condition>Neonatal Deaths</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Health Education &amp; Promotion: LHWs and CHWs will delivered the package via community awareness sessions and two one-to-one counselling sessions to pregnant women during third trimester and five newborn assessment visits in the neonatal period in intervention areas.
Training of Health Workers: The LHWs and CHWs will receive trainings on IMNCI-based training package.
Community Mobilization: For community mobilization and education, two types of tools will be used one group session by use of flip charts and group session by use of video.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control areas will continue to receive the routine standard health services of governmental and non-governmental organizations in the area.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health Education &amp; Promotion</intervention_name>
    <description>Promotion of antenatal care, adequate nutrition, skilled delivery and healthy newborn care practices at household level.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Training of Health Workers</intervention_name>
    <description>Training of health workers on recognition of danger sign that warrant referral to health care service.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Community Mobilization</intervention_name>
    <description>Community mobilization activities included formation of community health committees and creation of support for the uptake of the interventions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant women &amp; participants who agree to participate in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant women &amp; participants who disagree to participate in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zulfiqar A Bhutta, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Aga Khan University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aga Khan University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Karachi</city>
        <state>Sindh</state>
        <zip>74800</zip>
        <country>Pakistan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Pakistan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Reducing Perinatal and Neonatal Mortality. Child Health Research Project Special Report. 1999;3:1-48.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Costello AM. Perinatal health in developing countries. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg. 1993 Jan-Feb;87(1):1-2.</citation>
    <PMID>8465375</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. Child health and development: health of the newborn. Geneva: World health Organization 1991.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>De Muylder X. Perinatal mortality audit in a Zimbabwean district. Paediatr Perinat Epidemiol. 1989 Jul;3(3):284-93.</citation>
    <PMID>2788880</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fauveau V, Wojtyniak B, Mostafa G, Sarder AM, Chakraborty J. Perinatal mortality in Matlab, Bangladesh: a community-based study. Int J Epidemiol. 1990 Sep;19(3):606-12.</citation>
    <PMID>2262255</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wigglesworth JS. Monitoring perinatal mortality. A pathophysiological approach. Lancet. 1980 Sep 27;2(8196):684-6.</citation>
    <PMID>6106794</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Raghuveer G. Perinatal deaths: relevance of Wigglesworth's classification. Paediatr Perinat Epidemiol. 1992 Jan;6(1):45-50.</citation>
    <PMID>1553317</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bhutta ZA. Perinatal care in Pakistan. Proceedings of the Symposium on Priorities in Perinatal Care in South Asia. September 1998, Karachi, Pakistan.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 31, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 5, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 9, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 5, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 5, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 9, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Aga Khan University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr Zulfiqar Ahmed Bhutta</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Perinatal</keyword>
  <keyword>neonatal</keyword>
  <keyword>newborn</keyword>
  <keyword>mortality</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Perinatal Death</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stillbirth</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

