<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02412345</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>41528915.5.0000.0068</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>964.653</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02412345</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Extracorporeal Shockwave Therapy in the Treatment for Erectile Dysfunction in Male Renal Transplant Recipients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Extracorporeal Shockwave Therapy in the Treatment for Erectile Dysfunction in Male Renal Transplant Recipients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Sao Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Sao Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to determine the impact of the shock wave application
      in renal transplant patients with diagnosis of erectile dysfunction. Secondary objectives are
      to assess the effects of therapy on quality of life and depression.

      It is expected that with the study is defined the usefulness of the therapy and the
      dissemination of knowledge generated for change in clinical management in renal transplant
      patients with erectile dysfunction.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Renal Transplant Unit, performs about 230 kidney transplants per year and has a screening
      service for registration of candidates for renal transplantation, interviewing about 70
      patients a month. Since the potential and likely benefits of extracorporeal shock wave
      therapy in these patients as well as the anticipation of mild side effects, there is no
      reason for refusal to participate in the study.

      Patients who meet the inclusion criteria will be divided into 2 groups using a randomization
      table created by computer. Patients will be followed for 2 years.

      The study procedure and monitoring will be performed on an outpatient basis.

      Patients are divided into a group of extracorporeal shockwave (ESWT) treatment and placebo in
      a ratio of 1: 1 using a table of random numbers generated by computer.

      The ESWT protocol is protocol-based suggested by Vardi et al. 6. Patients will undergo a 2
      treatment sessions per week for 3 weeks.

      The penis is pulled manually, and shock waves are applied throughout the penile shaft (except
      the glans) and the crura bilaterally. The duration of each ESWT session will be approximately
      10 minutes and 2000 shocks will be applied per session with an intensity of energy of 1 mJ /
      mm 2. The volume of penile tissue exposed to shock waves at each site will be cilyndric
      (diameter: 18 mm, height 100 mm). No local or systemic analgesia is required during the
      procedure.

      To placebo therapy will be used the same device. The effective probe will be replaced by a
      similar one that emits zero energy during each treatment. Local application generates noise
      and a feeling of popping at the application site which will also be experienced by patients
      in the placebo group being impossible for the patient to discern which treatment group
      belongs.

      Penile ultrasound Doppler and drug erection will be performed before therapy and after
      treatment to evaluate the results.

      The diameter of the cavernous arteries is measured before and after intracavernosal injection
      application 20 mcg alprostadil (Caverject ®). In addition, vascular disorders, or stenotic
      atheromatous lesions will be investigated. The systolic and diastolic velocities of the
      cavernous arteries are evaluated 5,10 and 15 minutes after drug injection.

      After obtaining the patient signed informed consent , will be included in the study.
      Laboratory tests will be held at the Hospital Laboratory.

      Studied variables

      The following parameters will be studied during the initial evaluation and follow-up:

        1. Clinical

           Quality of life questionnaire -WHO QOL (World Health Organization - Quality of Life)
           Sexual questionnaire IIEF (International Index of Erectile Function) Comorbidities such
           as hypertension, diabetes and cardiovascular disease Smoking

        2. Laboratory

           Total testosterone, free testosterone, progesterone, albumin, SHBG, FSH, LH, prolactin,
           complete blood count, urea, creatinine, total cholesterol and fractions, triglycerides,
           T3, T4F and TSH.

        3. Imaging tests

      Ultrasound Doppler penile before and 3 months after treatment.

      - Calculation sample

      To define the sample size, the investigators must take into account: data variability (within
      each group) and the difference the investigators want to observe the parameters to be studied
      before and after treatment, beyond the level of significance and power of the test.

      The investigators will assume that the data follow a normal distribution and will use the
      paired t-test methodology, considering that the same patients will be evaluated in both
      conditions.

      The level of significance that work is 5%. Suitable power will be considered to be greater
      than 80%.

      The investigators observe a difference to 5 points required amount of samples is very small,
      whereas only 3 patients t-test. for the non-parametric test we consider a sample of 4
      patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changing in International Index of Erectile Function (IIEF-5) from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 1 year, 2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changing in Erection Hardness score from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 1 year, 2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changing in The World Health Organization Quality of Life (WHOQOL) from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 1 year, 2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changing in Peak systolic velocity by Penile doppler ultrasonography</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline ( previous to treatment) and 3 months after treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Erectile Dysfunction</condition>
  <condition>Renal Transplant</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Extracorporeal Shockwave therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Extracorporeal shockwave therapy at the penis. 6 sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Extracorporal shockwave therapy with a placebo probe. 6 sessions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Extracorporeal shockwave therapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Extracorporeal Shockwave therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Extracorporeal shockwave therapy - sham treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>A probe similar to the treatment group will be used. The noise and appearance is similar. The probe emits zero energy during each treatment. Local application generates noise and a feeling of popping at the application site which will also be experienced by patients in the placebo group being impossible for the patient to discern which treatment group belongs.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Penile ultrasound Doppler with intracavernosal injection application 20 mcg alprostadil</intervention_name>
    <description>Diagnostic test will be performed before treatment and after 3 to 4 months after therapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Extracorporeal Shockwave therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sham treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male patients between 40 and 70 years

          -  Kidney transplant for at least 6 months

          -  Erectile dysfunction (ED) for at least 6 months.

          -  Patients with IIEF score &lt;21

          -  Functioning kidney graft.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  ED because of known endocrine disease (e.g., hypogonadism, hypothyroidism)

          -  ED due to drug treatment (androgen deprivation therapy, for example)

          -  ED due to neurological disease (spinal cord injury, for example)

          -  ED due to structural abnormality of the penis

          -  History of radical prostatectomy or other pelvic surgery

          -  History of pelvic irradiation

          -  penile implant

          -  coagulopathies or on anticoagulants
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kleiton Gabriel Ribeiro Yamaçake</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sao Paulo</city>
        <zip>05403000</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vardi Y, Appel B, Jacob G, Massarwi O, Gruenwald I. Can low-intensity extracorporeal shockwave therapy improve erectile function? A 6-month follow-up pilot study in patients with organic erectile dysfunction. Eur Urol. 2010 Aug;58(2):243-8. doi: 10.1016/j.eururo.2010.04.004. Epub 2010 May 6.</citation>
    <PMID>20451317</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yee CH, Chan ES, Hou SS, Ng CF. Extracorporeal shockwave therapy in the treatment of erectile dysfunction: a prospective, randomized, double-blinded, placebo controlled study. Int J Urol. 2014 Oct;21(10):1041-5. doi: 10.1111/iju.12506. Epub 2014 Jun 17.</citation>
    <PMID>24942563</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liu J, Zhou F, Li GY, Wang L, Li HX, Bai GY, Guan RL, Xu YD, Gao ZZ, Tian WJ, Xin ZC. Evaluation of the effect of different doses of low energy shock wave therapy on the erectile function of streptozotocin (STZ)-induced diabetic rats. Int J Mol Sci. 2013 May 21;14(5):10661-73. doi: 10.3390/ijms140510661.</citation>
    <PMID>23698784</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 15, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 5, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 9, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Sao Paulo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kleiton Gabriel Ribeiro Yamaçake</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Erectile Dysfunction</keyword>
  <keyword>Shockwave therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Renal Transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>Male</keyword>
  <keyword>Renal Transplant Recipients</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Erectile Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alprostadil</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

