<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02416661</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LP 03-2015</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02416661</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>LYSO-PROVE - Determine the Prognostic Value of Lyso-Gb1 for Monitoring the Progress of Gaucher Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>LYSO-PROVE</acronym>
  <official_title>Lyso-Gb1 as Long-term Prognostic Biomarker in Gaucher Disease - an International Multicenter Epidemiological Study (LYSO-PROVE) to Determine the Prognostic Value of Lyso-Gb1 for Monitoring the Progress of Gaucher Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Rostock</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centogene AG Rostock</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Rostock</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study should demonstrate the correlation and predictive value of lyso-Gb1 concentration
      with the clinical severity of naïve, initially non-ERT/SRT Gaucher disease type 1 and during
      the study ERT/SRT-newly started Gaucher type 1 patients
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Gaucher disease is an autosomal recessive inherited lysosomal storage disorder. The disease
      is caused by the hereditary deficiency of the glucocerebrosidase, a lysosomal enzyme that
      breaks down glucocerebroside into glucose and ceramide. Gaucher disease is the most common
      sphingolipidosis and it is among the most frequent inherited diseases among the ethnic group
      of Ashkenazi Jews. The gene that encodes for glucocerebrosidase is located on the long arm of
      the chromosome 1 and contains 11 exons. So far, more than 400 different mutations have been
      described in Gaucher patients, the most frequent of which is the missense mutation but also
      the frame-shift and splice-site mutation and insertions and deletions are known. The more
      frequent mutations are N370S, L444P, IVS2+1G&gt;A, c.84insG, R463C, and R496H. Clinical symptoms
      are numerous. The classical symptoms affect visceral organs (hepatosplenomegaly) and the
      skeletal system (bone marrow infiltrations up to bone infarcts and pathological fractures)
      with consecutive changes in the blood panel (anemia, thrombocytopenia) (Sidransky, 2004).A
      major distinguishing factor is the occurrence of neurological manifestations (myoclonus
      epilepsy, hydrocephalus, eye motion disorders). Today, it is discussed whether the division
      into the classical three types of disease (type 1: non-neuronopathic form; type 2: the acute
      neuronopathic form; type 3: the chronic neuronopathic form) are still applicable because in
      clinical practice the presenting symptoms are only insufficiently reflected with this
      classification.

      There is no clear genotype-phenotype relationship. The same DNA mutation is seen in patients
      with a completely different characterization of the disease. An exception is the mutation
      N370S, which so far has been found only in the visceral form (type1), but still may have a
      high phenotypic heterogeneity in GD Type 1 (Fairley et al., 2008).

      The outcome of the non-neuronopathic diseases could be improved greatly with the introduction
      and widely available enzyme replacement therapy. Among these are the reductions of the size
      of the liver and spleen as well as normalization in the blood count (Elstein and Zimran,
      2009). The glucocerebrosides that are not metabolized are stored in the entire
      reticuloendothelial system. The macrophages enriched with glycolipids form the pathoanatomic
      basis of the so-called &quot;Gaucher cells&quot; which can be verified with the light microscope. The
      accumulation of Gaucher cells in liver, spleen, and bone marrow is thought to underlie the
      characteristic hepatosplenomegaly, pancytopenia and bone complications of GD patients
      (Beutler 2001). There are no causative cures for lysosomal storage diseases and treatment is
      mostly symptomatic, although mostly enzyme replacement therapy (ERT) has been demonstrated
      especially for the treatment of non-neuronopathic GD with good success (Elstein and Zimran,
      2009). In addition, substrate reduction therapy (SRT), a method used to decrease the
      accumulation of storage material, is currently being evaluated for some of these diseases. In
      SRT, oral administration of the iminosugar N-butyldeoxynojirimycin aims to reduce
      Glucosylceramide (GlcCer) synthesis and thus limit its accumulation. However, SRT is only
      approved for mildly tomoderately affected patients in whom ERT is not a therapeutic option
      (Ficicioglu, 2008). Additionally, Eliglustat is currently under investigation for the primary
      oral treatment of GD type 1 patient (Lukina et al., 2014).

      To date a definitive diagnosis of Gaucher's disease can only be made applying biochemical
      testing measuring the reduced enzymatic activity of the beta-glucosidase together with
      genetic confirmation. Since numerous different mutations may be the cause of a particular
      lysosomal storage disease the sequencing of the entire beta-glucosidase gene is applied in
      Gaucher's disease in order to confirm the genetic diagnosis (Zimran, 2011). Although there
      are attempts to apply easy diagnostic methods based on associated biochemical abnormalities
      such as high alkaline phosphatase, angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) and immunoglobulin
      levels, or, in case of Gaucher's disease, by cell analysis showing &quot;crinkled paper&quot; cytoplasm
      and glycolipid-laden macrophages, there is an unmet need for a simple biochemical test
      exhibiting highly specific and highly sensitive detection at an early stage, monitoring
      progression of the disease and early monitoring the efficacy of applied therapies.

      A biomarker should be technically feasible in many hands, easy to measure; useful, with a
      consistent, relative magnitude between patients and controls, or treated and untreated
      patients; reliable, precise, and accurate clinically, and classifiable as strongly predictive
      or prognostic. In GD some lysosomal enzymes, used as indirect biomarkers, were found to be
      elevated, including tartrate-resistant acid phosphatase, hexosaminidase, and a human
      chitinase, chitotriosidase. Thus, there are attempts to monitor the reduction of storage
      cells in tissues by measurement of such surrogate markers of Gaucher cells like
      chitotriosidase and CCL18 (Hollak et al., 1994; Boot et al., 2004). However, the use of
      plasma chitotriosidase as a Gaucher cell marker is hampered by the fact that patients,
      including those with Gaucher's disease, may be deficient in chitotriosidase activity due to a
      24-base pair (bp) duplication in the chitotriosidase gene. Obviously these individuals cannot
      be monitored by the measurement of plasma chitotriosidase activity. The frequency of the
      homozygous 24-bp duplication in the chitotriosidase gene depends on the ethnicity and can
      vary between 6% and nearly 35% in the Latino population (unpublished data). In these cases
      the marker CCL18 is used. Furthermore, elevated levels of CCL18 were also found to be
      associated with a variety of diseases, such as different types of cancer and inflammation of
      joints, lungs and skin. For example, the ascitic fluid of patients suffering from ovarian
      cancer contains a significantly elevated level of CCL18 compared to patients without this
      carcinoma (Budd-Chiari syndrome). Since it attracts and activates specific immune cells CCL18
      plays a role in tumor suppression. Furthermore, children having acute lymphocytic leukemia
      are found to exhibit elevated levels of CCL18. Plasma CCL18 levels do not reflect one
      particular clinical symptom, but rather are a reflection of the total body burden of Gaucher
      cells. The use of primary storage molecules as biomarker was assessed for glucosylceramide
      (Gb1) in plasma of Gaucher's disease patients and compared to the level of Gb1 in healthy
      individuals (Groener et al. 2008). Already in 1989 Rosengren et al. (1989) showed that in
      lipidoses not only the catabolism of the major sphingolipid but also its deacylated compound
      is affected. It is important to note that until today no use of a highly specific and highly
      sensitive biomarker is routinely used beside the methods described above, that exhibits an
      unsatisfactory limit of detection, sensitivity and/or specificity and thus proved to be
      unsuitable for clinical application
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To demonstrate the correlation and predictive value of lyso-Gb1 concentration with the clinical severity of naïve, initially non-ERT/SRT Gaucher disease type 1 and during the study ERT/SRT-newly started Gaucher type 1 patients</measure>
    <time_frame>48 month</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To correlate lyso-Gb1 concentration with the clinical improvement of ERT or SRT treated Gaucher type 1 and the clinical course of non-treated patients based on GD-DS3,Quality of life measured with the SF-36</measure>
    <time_frame>48 month</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">250</enrollment>
  <condition>Lysosomal Storage Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Gaucher Disease</condition>
  <condition>Sphingolipidoses</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Observation</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with genetically confirmed diagnosis of Gaucher disease type 1 without treatment prior to enrollment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      lyso-Gb1 as biomarker for Gaucher Disease For the purpose of measuring lyso-Gb1 one filter
      card is sent to the following laboratory, Centogene AG, Schillingallee 68, 18057 Rostock,
      Germany
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        male or female patients aged 6 months or older with genetically confirmed diagnosis of
        Gaucher disease type 1 without treatment prior to enrollment or no treatment for more than
        24 months ago
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female patients aged 6 months or older

          -  Patients with genetically confirmed diagnosis of Gaucher disease type 1

          -  No prior treatment with enzyme replacement therapy or substrate reduction therapy ro
             no traetment for more than 24 months

          -  Signed informed consent by parents/legal guardian and patient

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female patients being younger than 6 months

          -  Patients without genetically confirmed diagnosis of Gaucher disease type 1

          -  Gaucher disease 2 or 3

          -  Patient is currently undergoing enzyme replacement therapy or substrate reduction
             therapy

          -  Missing signed informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Arndt Rolfs, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Rostock, Albrecht-Kossel-Institute for Neuroregeneration</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Arndt Rolfs, MD</last_name>
    <phone>49-381-494</phone>
    <phone_ext>9540</phone_ext>
    <email>arndt.rolfs@med.uni-rostock.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sabine Rösner</last_name>
    <phone>49-381-494</phone>
    <phone_ext>4797</phone_ext>
    <email>sabine.roesner@med.uni-rostock.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pediatric department Debaghine's Hospital Universitary Hospital Center of Bab-El-Oued</name>
      <address>
        <city>Algiers</city>
        <zip>16030</zip>
        <country>Algeria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Souhila Melzi, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital de Ben Aknoun BOUKHROUFA Abdelkader Service Rhumatologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Algiers</city>
        <zip>16306</zip>
        <country>Algeria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Fadia Rahal, MD</last_name>
      <email>ffadia_2007@yahoo.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>internal Medecine, Dr Mohammad-Lamine&quot;sDebaghine, Universitary Hosspital Center,Bab-El-Oued</name>
      <address>
        <city>Algiers</city>
        <country>Algeria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Djennette Hakem, Prof.</last_name>
      <email>hakem_dj@yahoo.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Abdelkrim Berrah, Prof.</last_name>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pediatric practice</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oran</city>
        <zip>31000</zip>
        <country>Algeria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Houaria Cheriet, MD</last_name>
      <email>houaria26dz@yahoo.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Houaria Cheriet, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service medicine interne EPH Bouguera Boulares Bekkaria</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tébessa</city>
        <zip>12130</zip>
        <country>Algeria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Souhlia Moundher, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gene Lab</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ekram Fateen, Prof.</last_name>
      <email>efateen@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Albrecht-Kossel-Institute for Neuroregeneration (AKos) Centre for Mental Health Disease University of Rostock</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rostock</city>
        <zip>18147</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Arndt Rolfs, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 381 494</phone>
      <phone_ext>9540</phone_ext>
      <email>arndt.rolfs@med.uni-rostock.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sabine Rösner</last_name>
      <phone>+49 381 494</phone>
      <phone_ext>4797</phone_ext>
      <email>sabine.roesner@med.uni-rostock.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aristotle University of Thessaloniki-Department of Pediatrics</name>
      <address>
        <city>Thessaloniki</city>
        <zip>54622</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dimitrios Zafeiriou, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+30 2310 241</phone>
      <phone_ext>845</phone_ext>
      <email>jeff@med.auth.gr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dimitrios Zafeiriou, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Senior Consultant Pediatrician Rainbow Children Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hyderabad</city>
        <zip>500034</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Radha Rama Devi, MD</last_name>
      <email>radharamadevi@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kasturba Medical College, University of Manipal, 575001 Ambedkar (Jyothi) Circle</name>
      <address>
        <city>Munipal</city>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Girisha Katta, MD</last_name>
      <email>girish.katta@manipal.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Girisha Katta, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Division of Genetics, Department of Pediatrics, AIIMS,New Delhi,India</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Delhi</city>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Madhulika Kabra, MD</last_name>
      <email>madhulikakabra@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Neerja Gupta, MD</last_name>
      <email>neerja17@gmail.com, neerja17aiims@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Madhulika Kabra, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sarem Women Hospital - Metabolic and Genetics Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tehran</city>
        <country>Iran, Islamic Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Zahra Hadipour, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+98 (21) 446 70 888</phone>
      <phone_ext>1515</phone_ext>
      <email>f.ashuo@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Fatemeh Hadipou, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+98 (21) 446 70 888</phone>
      <phone_ext>1515</phone_ext>
      <email>f.ashuo@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shaare Zedek Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerusalem</city>
        <zip>93722</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ari Zimran, MD</last_name>
      <email>azimran@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Tama Dinur, MD</last_name>
      <email>dinurtama@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ari Zimran, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>División de Genética</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guadalajara</city>
        <zip>44340</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>José Elias García-Ortiz, MD</last_name>
      <email>jose.elias.garcia@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Averroès Casablanca</name>
      <address>
        <city>Casablanca</city>
        <country>Morocco</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mina Moudatir, MD</last_name>
      <email>minamoudatir@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children hospital's Rabat</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rabat</city>
        <zip>10100</zip>
        <country>Morocco</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nezha Mouane, Prof.</last_name>
      <email>nezhamouane@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Yamna Kriouile, Prof.</last_name>
      <email>dr.kriouile@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Research Center for Hematology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>125167</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elena Lukina, Prof.</last_name>
      <email>elenalukina02@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kira Lukina, MD</last_name>
      <email>kira1404@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Karolinska University, Hospital Huddinge, Hematology Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <zip>141 86</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maciej Machaczka, Prof.</last_name>
      <email>maciej.machaczka@ki.se</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Hedi Chaker</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sfax</city>
        <zip>1008</zip>
        <country>Tunisia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hadji Mseddi Sondes</last_name>
      <email>mseddi_sondes@medecinesfax.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Av. Pateón, Centro Clínico Profesional Caracas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Caracas</city>
        <country>Venezuela</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Liliana Vera, Prof.</last_name>
      <email>lilive29@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Algeria</country>
    <country>Egypt</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Greece</country>
    <country>India</country>
    <country>Iran, Islamic Republic of</country>
    <country>Israel</country>
    <country>Mexico</country>
    <country>Morocco</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>Sweden</country>
    <country>Tunisia</country>
    <country>Venezuela</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.centogene.com</url>
    <description>Centogene is one of the leading laboratories focusing on genetic testing for rare hereditary disorders.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 13, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 9, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 15, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Rostock</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prof. Dr. Arndt Rolfs</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr. med.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gaucher Disease type 1</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphatic Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Lipid Metabolism, Inborn Errors</keyword>
  <keyword>Lipid Metabolism Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Lipidoses</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gaucher Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lysosomal Storage Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sphingolipidoses</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

