<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01028352</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UMCC 2008.062</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HUM00022455</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01028352</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Assess Effect of 8 Wks of Duloxetine Therapy on Breast Cancer Patients With Aromatase-Inhibitor Associated Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>UMCC 2008.62: Prospective Pilot Study Evaluating the Use of Duloxetine for Treatment of Aromatase Inhibitor-associated Musculoskeletal Symptoms in Breast Cancer Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eli Lilly and Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Many women with breast cancer who are treated with aromatase inhibitor medications develop
      aches and pains during treatment, and some develop numbness and tingling in their hands and
      feet. Some examples of aromatase inhibitor medications include anastrozole (Arimidex),
      exemestane (Aromasin), and letrozole (Femara). Frequently, pain medications do not work very
      well to relieve the pain. Duloxetine (Cymbalta) is a medication that was originally developed
      to treat depression. It has also been found to relieve pain that occurs in people with
      diabetes, fibromyalgia, arthritis, and other painful conditions. In this study we are testing
      to see if duloxetine will help treat the pain that can occur in women treated with aromatase
      inhibitors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aromatase inhibitor (AI) therapy is commonly used for treatment of postmenopausal women with
      hormone receptor-positive breast cancer. The most common toxicities are arthralgias and
      myalgias, which can be difficult to manage and necessitate discontinuation of therapy in up
      to 10% of patients. One potential interventional approach is with a pharmaceutical agent such
      as duloxetine, which has been shown to be effective for treatment of other types of chronic
      pain, including fibromyalgia and diabetic neuropathic pain.

      The primary objective of this pilot study is to determine the proportion of breast cancer
      patients with AI-associated musculoskeletal symptoms who experience a 30% reduction in
      average pain score from baseline to 8 weeks due to duloxetine treatment. Participants will be
      treated with duloxetine for 8 weeks. Questionnaires to evaluate pain, functional status,
      depression, menopausal symptoms, and sleep difficulties will be administered at baseline and
      after 2, 4, 6, and 8 weeks of therapy. In addition, 10 milliliters blood of will be drawn
      from the subjects at baseline for future pharmacogenetic evaluation. If the results of this
      pilot study suggest that the efficacy of duloxetine therapy is greater than that expected
      from placebo based on historical controls, then these data will be used to design future
      prospective, placebo-controlled, randomized trials of treatment with duloxetine in this
      patient population.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Patients Who Experience 30% Reduction in Average Pain Score From Baseline to 8 Weeks Due to Duloxetine Therapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects were considered evaluable if they met all eligibility criteria and took at least one dose of duloxetine. Average pain was measured using Wisconsin Brief Pain Inventory Questionnaire.(BPI) The BPI is a 17-item patient self-rating scale that assessed sensory &amp; reactive components of pain. The BPI uses 0 to 10 numeric rating scales for item rating.Since pain can be variable,the BPI asks patients to rate pain at completing questionnaire, and also at its worst, least, and average over the previous 24 hours. The primary endpoint is based on the 24-hour avg pain as reported on BPI.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in Average Pain With 8 Weeks of Duloxetine Therapy. (Sustained)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2, 4 , 6 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>A secondary measure is the percentage of patients treated with duloxetine who experience a sustained 30% reduction in average pain score from baseline to 8 weeks. Sustained 30% reduction is defined as at least 30% reduction in 24-hour average pain severity at the 8 week endpoint, with a 30% reduction from baseline at a visit at least 2 weeks prior to the last visit, and at least 20% reduction from baseline at every visit in between.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Duloxetine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Duloxetine</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be treated with open-label duloxetine:
30 mg daily x 7 days, then
60 mg daily x 3 weeks, then
If a patient believes she has experienced a sufficient reduction in pain after 4 weeks of therapy, she will continue taking 60 mg daily for weeks 5-8
If a patient does not believe she has experienced a sufficient reduction in pain after 4 weeks of therapy, she will have the option of increasing the dose to 60 mg twice daily for weeks 5-8.
After completion of 8 weeks of therapy, patients who wish to discontinue therapy will taper off the drug over 1 week (50% decrease for 4 days, then additional 50% decrease for 3 days). Patients may continue therapy off-study at the discretion of their treating physician.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Duloxetine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cymbalta</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female;

          -  Histologically proven stage 0-III invasive carcinoma of the breast that is ER and/or
             PR positive by immunohistochemical staining, who are receiving a standard dose of
             aromatase inhibitor (AI) therapy (letrozole 2.5mg once daily or exemestane 25mg once
             daily or anastrozole 1mg once daily). Women with oligometastatic disease may be
             included at the discretion of the principal investigator. Surgical resection,
             chemotherapy, and radiation therapy must have been completed at the time of study
             enrollment, with the exception of trastuzumab;

          -  AI therapy has been ongoing for ≥ 2 weeks and treatment is expected to continue;

          -  AI-associated musculoskeletal symptoms, defined as:

               -  Grade 1 or higher musculoskeletal pain that developed or worsened (6 or 7 on
                  CGICS) during AI therapy or

               -  Grade 1 or higher sensory neuropathy that developed or worsened (6 or 7 on CGICS)
                  during AI therapy;

          -  Average pain of ≥4 on the 11-point Likert scale of question #5 of the Brief Pain
             Inventory;

          -  ECOG performance status 0-2;

          -  Willing and able to sign an informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known hypersensitivity to duloxetine or any of the inactive ingredients;

          -  New musculoskeletal pain that is due specifically to fracture or traumatic injury;

          -  Treatment with monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAO-I) within 14 days of enrollment;

          -  Concurrent treatment with phenothiazines (including thioridazine), propafenone,
             flecainide, triptans, MAO-Is, SSRIs, SNRIs, or tricyclic antidepressants;

          -  Currently primary psychiatric diagnosis (schizophrenia, psychosis) or suicidal
             ideation, history of bipolar disorder, or seizure disorder;

          -  Chronic liver disease, end stage renal disease, or creatinine clearance &lt; 30 mL/min as
             defined by the Cockroft-Gault equation;

          -  Uncontrolled narrow-angle glaucoma or clinically significant coagulation disorder;

          -  Pregnant or breast feeding;

          -  History of alcohol or other substance abuse or dependence within the year prior to
             enrollment;

          -  Serious or unstable medical condition that could likely lead to hospitalization during
             the course of the study or compromise study participation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Norah L Henry, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109-0944</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Henry NL, Banerjee M, Wicha M, Van Poznak C, Smerage JB, Schott AF, Griggs JJ, Hayes DF. Pilot study of duloxetine for treatment of aromatase inhibitor-associated musculoskeletal symptoms. Cancer. 2011 Dec 15;117(24):5469-75. doi: 10.1002/cncr.26230. Epub 2011 Jun 20.</citation>
    <PMID>21692065</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 8, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 8, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 9, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>January 30, 2012</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>July 9, 2012</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">August 17, 2012</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 26, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 26, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 8, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan Cancer Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lynn Henry</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Duloxetine Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aromatase Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Between December 2008 and May 2010 35 subjects enrolled and completed baseline questionnaires in the University of Michigan comprehensive cancer center's outpatient hematolgy / oncology clinic</recruitment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Duloxetine</title>
          <description>Participants took 30 mg oral capsules once a day for 7 days, then 60 mg per mouth once per day for 21 days. After 4 weeks if pain had decreased, subjects continued 60 mg. per mouth once per day for 4 weeks. If pain had not decreased, subjects took 60 mg twice per day per mouth for 4 weeks. 5 Questionnaires were administered at baseline and every 2 weeks for 8 weeks; medication was tapered at the end of study.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="35"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="29"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="6"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Ineligible due to baseline average pain</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="5"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Withdrawal by Subject</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Duloxetine</title>
          <description>Participants took 30 mg oral capsules once a day for 7 days, then 60 mg per mouth once per day for 21 days. After 4 weeks if pain had decreased, subjects continued 60 mg. per mouth once per day for 4 weeks. If pain had not decreased, subjects took 60 mg twice per day per mouth for 4 weeks. 5 Questionnaires were administered at baseline and every 2 weeks for 8 weeks; medication was tapered at the end of study.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="35"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="33"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="56" spread=".9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="35"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="35"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Percentage of Patients Who Experience 30% Reduction in Average Pain Score From Baseline to 8 Weeks Due to Duloxetine Therapy.</title>
        <description>Subjects were considered evaluable if they met all eligibility criteria and took at least one dose of duloxetine. Average pain was measured using Wisconsin Brief Pain Inventory Questionnaire.(BPI) The BPI is a 17-item patient self-rating scale that assessed sensory &amp; reactive components of pain. The BPI uses 0 to 10 numeric rating scales for item rating.Since pain can be variable,the BPI asks patients to rate pain at completing questionnaire, and also at its worst, least, and average over the previous 24 hours. The primary endpoint is based on the 24-hour avg pain as reported on BPI.</description>
        <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>Subjects were considered evaluable for the primary endpoint if they met all eligibility criteria and took at least one dose of duloxetine</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Duloxetine</title>
            <description>Participants took 30 mg oral capsules once a day for 7 days, then 60 mg per mouth once per day for 21 days. After 4 weeks if pain had decreased, subjects continued 60 mg. per mouth once per day for 4 weeks. If pain had not decreased, subjects took 60 mg twice per day per mouth for 4 weeks. 5 Questionnaires were administered at baseline and every 2 weeks for 8 weeks; medication was tapered at the end of study.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Percentage of Patients Who Experience 30% Reduction in Average Pain Score From Baseline to 8 Weeks Due to Duloxetine Therapy.</title>
          <description>Subjects were considered evaluable if they met all eligibility criteria and took at least one dose of duloxetine. Average pain was measured using Wisconsin Brief Pain Inventory Questionnaire.(BPI) The BPI is a 17-item patient self-rating scale that assessed sensory &amp; reactive components of pain. The BPI uses 0 to 10 numeric rating scales for item rating.Since pain can be variable,the BPI asks patients to rate pain at completing questionnaire, and also at its worst, least, and average over the previous 24 hours. The primary endpoint is based on the 24-hour avg pain as reported on BPI.</description>
          <population>Subjects were considered evaluable for the primary endpoint if they met all eligibility criteria and took at least one dose of duloxetine</population>
          <units>percentage of participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="29"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="72.4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Decrease in Average Pain With 8 Weeks of Duloxetine Therapy. (Sustained)</title>
        <description>A secondary measure is the percentage of patients treated with duloxetine who experience a sustained 30% reduction in average pain score from baseline to 8 weeks. Sustained 30% reduction is defined as at least 30% reduction in 24-hour average pain severity at the 8 week endpoint, with a 30% reduction from baseline at a visit at least 2 weeks prior to the last visit, and at least 20% reduction from baseline at every visit in between.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline, 2, 4 , 6 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Duloxetine</title>
            <description>Participants took 30 mg oral capsules once a day for 7 days, then 60 mg per mouth once per day for 21 days. After 4 weeks if pain had decreased, subjects continued 60 mg. per mouth once per day for 4 weeks. If pain had not decreased, subjects took 60 mg twice per day per mouth for 4 weeks. 5 Questionnaires were administered at baseline and every 2 weeks for 8 weeks; medication was tapered at the end of study.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Decrease in Average Pain With 8 Weeks of Duloxetine Therapy. (Sustained)</title>
          <description>A secondary measure is the percentage of patients treated with duloxetine who experience a sustained 30% reduction in average pain score from baseline to 8 weeks. Sustained 30% reduction is defined as at least 30% reduction in 24-hour average pain severity at the 8 week endpoint, with a 30% reduction from baseline at a visit at least 2 weeks prior to the last visit, and at least 20% reduction from baseline at every visit in between.</description>
          <units>%of participants with 30% pain reduction</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="29"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="60.9" lower_limit="48.6" upper_limit="73.1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>1 year and 5 months</time_frame>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Duloxetine</title>
          <description>Participants took 30 mg oral capsules once a day for 7 days, then 60 mg per mouth once per day for 21 days. After 4 weeks if pain had decreased, subjects continued 60 mg. per mouth once per day for 4 weeks. If pain had not decreased, subjects took 60 mg twice per day per mouth for 4 weeks. 5 Questionnaires were administered at baseline and every 2 weeks for 8 weeks; medication was tapered at the end of study.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="29"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>2.9</frequency_threshold>
        <default_vocab>CTCAE (Unspecified)</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="7" subjects_at_risk="29"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Constipation</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="6" subjects_affected="6" subjects_at_risk="29"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>nausea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="6" subjects_affected="6" subjects_at_risk="29"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Heartburn</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="3" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="29"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Fatigue</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="7" subjects_affected="7" subjects_at_risk="29"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Headache</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="5" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="29"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dry mouth</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="5" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="29"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Drowsiness</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="4" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="29"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Anxiety</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="3" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="29"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dr. Norah L. Henry</name_or_title>
      <organization>University of Michigan Comprehensive Cancer Center</organization>
      <phone>734-936-4991</phone>
      <email>norahh@umich.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

