<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01022515</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2007/081/HP</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2007-AO1004-49</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01022515</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Specificity of Elevated Plasma EM66 Levels in Pheochromocytoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>PHEO</acronym>
  <official_title>Clinical Application of New Pheochromocytoma Markers: INSERM Pilot Study of the Specificity of Elevated Plasma EM66 Concentrations in Patients With Pheochromocytoma or Paraganglioma Compared to Patients With Essential Hypertension</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Rouen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Rouen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pheochromocytoma or paraganglioma are tumors generating hypertension as a symptom. Different
      biological tests are currently available to diagnose these tumors. However, they all lack
      specificity since they do not distinguish cases of hypertension without pheochromocytoma or
      paraganglioma. To improve the diagnostic specificity of these tumors, the investigators are
      testing a new marker called EM66.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Neuroendocrine tumors (NT) correspond to neoplasms that develop from endocrine and
      neuroendocrine cells scattered throughout the body. They are characterized by the occurrence,
      in their cytoplasm, of dense-core secretory vesicles containing hormones, neuropeptides and
      acidic proteins such as granins. The diversity of NT (from hypophysis, pancreas, adrenal,
      gastrointestinal tract) makes very difficult the identification and evaluation of the
      different types of tumors by the diagnostic and prognostic tools currently available. We have
      thus established a research program aimed at identifying new biological markers for the
      detection, the prognosis and the follow-up of NT by seeking in tumor and plasma samples of
      patients, granin-derived peptides. Our program was initiated on one type of NT :
      pheochromocytoma. These neoplasms correspond to tumoral chromaffin cells mainly originating
      from the adrenal medulla. It is considered that 10 % of pheochromocytoma patients will
      develop metastases and, currently, except in the presence of metastases, there are no means
      to predict malignancy of the tumor. We setup a radioimmunoassay of EM66 (a secretogranin
      II-derived peptide) that allowed us to demonstrate that (i) plasma concentrations of the
      peptide are significantly elevated in pheochromocytoma patients, (ii) combined with other
      biological tests EM66 measurement increase the diagnostic sensitivity for these neoplasms,
      (iii) after surgical removal of the tumor, plasma EM66 concentrations rapidly return to basal
      level and, (iv) intra-tumoral EM66 concentrations are higher in benign than in malignant
      pheochromocytomas (Yon et al., 2003, Guillemot et al., 2006). These results reveal that EM66
      constitutes a novel tool for the diagnosis, prognosis and follow-up of pheochromocytoma. In
      the frame of a clinical use of an EM66 measurement test, it is necessary to evaluate the
      specificity of this marker. For instance, renal deficiency, hypergastrinemia, reduction of
      renal clearance, type A gastritis, Crohns disease, or proton-pump inhibitory treatment, lead
      to increase plasma chromogranin A (CgA) concentrations (false-positive cases). In addition,
      while hypertension account for one of the symptoms of pheochromocytoma patients, in essential
      hypertensive patients, CgA levels are higher than in normotensive individuals. The main
      objective of our clinical transfer research project consists to study the specificity of the
      measurement of EM66 as a diagnostic and prognostic marker of pheochromocytoma. This
      multicentric study will allow us to compare plasma EM66 levels in pheochromocytoma patients
      with a cohort of essential hypertensive patients. At the same time, in a long-range prospect,
      due to the lack of malignancy markers for these tumors, we will investigate if plasma or
      tumor EM66 levels are correlated to the differentiation status of pheochromocytomas, and if
      the expression level of a set of genes that we identified by a transcriptomic approach
      developed in the laboratory, is associated with the malignant status of the tumors. The
      stakes of this transfer research, involving our laboratory and the Center for Clinical
      Investigations (CIC) of Rouen and Lille, are to provide an easy and simple novel tool to
      practitioners and anatomo-pathologists for the screening, the evaluation and the follow-up of
      patients with neuroendocrine tumors.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma EM66</measure>
    <time_frame>two years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Chromogranin A levels</measure>
    <time_frame>before treatement</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Pheochromocytoma</condition>
  <condition>Paraganglioma</condition>
  <condition>Essential Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>patients with pheochromocytoma</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with pheochromocytoma / paraganglioma are being followed as recommended according to international standards. No intervention is expected except regular measurement of plasma CgA (as usual) and EM66 (research purpose) levels.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with essential hypertension</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with essential hypertension will be selected as controls. EM66 and CgA plasma levels will be assessed in these patients after having excluded the presence of a pheochromocytoma / paraganglioma with normal urinary metanephrines / normetanephrines excretion levels.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>plasma EM66 &amp; CgA levels assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>After inclusion checking to eliminate the presence of pheochromocytoma / paraganglioma, a blood sample will be drawn to assess plasma EM66 and CgA levels.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with essential hypertension</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>usual follow up with regular EM66 &amp; Cga levels assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with pheochromocytoma / paraganglioma will be followed-up as the international standards recommend.
Regularly, blood samples will be drawn for the usual assessment of CgA levels and also EM66 (research purpose) levels.</description>
    <arm_group_label>patients with pheochromocytoma</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      5 ml blood sample on EDTA to collect 2,5 ml plasma, kept at -80°C, once a year.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        two distint population will be involved :

          -  patients with pheochromocytoma or paraganglioma

          -  patients with essential hypertension
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patients with pheochromocytoma/paraganglioma

        Inclusion criteria :

          -  men &amp; women, age &gt; 18 years old

          -  Newly diagnosed patient : suspicion of pheochromocytoma or paraganglioma with
             elevation of urinary metanephrines and/or normetanephrines along with evidence of
             tumor which surgical removal is considered (histological findings following surgery
             will be the gold standard for final diagnosis and inclusion in the study)

          -  During follow-up of a patient with known genetic predisposition to
             pheochromocytoma/paraganglioma : suspicion of pheochromocytoma or paraganglioma with
             or without elevation of urinary metanephrines and/or normetanephrines along with
             evidence of a tumor which surgical removal is considered (histological findings
             following surgery will be the gold standard for final diagnosis and inclusion in the
             study) ,

          -  Patients with known pheochromocytoma/paraganglioma, whether malignant or not, whether
             with metanephrine secretion or not, With tumor sites at inclusion in the study

          -  Patients informed and willing to participate in the study

          -  Patients with medical insurance (French social security) Non inclusion criteria

          -  Patients newly diagnosed, recently operated and the histological findings disprove
             pheochromocytoma or paraganglioma.

          -  patient imprisoned or under legal protection.

        Patients with essential hypertension Inclusion criteria

          -  men &amp; women, age &gt; 18 years old

          -  paired with a patient with pheochromocytoma/paraganglioma for : gender, age (± 5
             years) and centre

          -  patient with hypertension. No aetiology was found after initial check up.

          -  Normal 24 hours urinary excretion of metanephrines &amp; normetanephrines

          -  For women of childbearing potential : effective contraceptive method and negative
             urinary pregnancy test

          -  Patients informed and willing to participate in the study

          -  Patients with medical insurance (French social security) Non inclusion criteria

          -  Treatment with proton-pump inhibitors in the 8 days before inclusion in the study

          -  Treatment with beta-blockers, antidepressants, Benzodiazepins, dopa, alphamethyl dopa,
             if this treatment cannot be interrupted during the study (i.e. for approximately 10
             days)

          -  patient imprisoned or under legal protection.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anne F Cailleux, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rouen University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CIC 9301</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lille</city>
        <zip>59000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Endocrinology Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lille</city>
        <zip>59000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Inserm U982/EA 4310; Rouen University (DC2N)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mont Saint Aignan</city>
        <zip>76800</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cardiology Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75012</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CIC 9304</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75012</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cic-Crb 0204</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rouen</city>
        <zip>76000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Endocrinology Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rouen</city>
        <zip>76000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Endocrinology Department, Gustave-Roussy Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Villejuif</city>
        <zip>94000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 17, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 30, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 1, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 18, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 18, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 19, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pheochromocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>paraganglioma</keyword>
  <keyword>hypertension</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pheochromocytoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paraganglioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carotid Body Tumor</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

