<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01021098</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IDCRP-045</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01021098</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Acute Respiratory Infection Consortium</brief_title>
  <acronym>ARIC</acronym>
  <official_title>A Multi-center Military Consortium for Clinical Research Into the Natural History, Host Response, and Potential Therapy of Acute Respiratory Infection in Military Members and Their Families</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Recently, the emergence and rapid global dissemination of novel swine-origin influenza A
      virus (H1N1) with unique epidemiologic characteristics has heightened awareness and concern
      of this viral pathogen, and its potential for major disruption of both civil and military
      stability. Although advances in medical and scientific technologies have improved our basic
      understanding of respiratory disease, many questions about the epidemiology and immunology of
      ARI remain unanswered. This study plans to initiate a multi-site, multi-disciplinary research
      collaboration, termed the Acute Respiratory Infection Consortium (ARIC) for the purpose of
      studying the etiology, epidemiology and immunology of influenza-like illness (ILI) in order
      to describe the natural history and risk factors for disease, as well as the characteristics
      of the host immune response.

      At the core of the ARIC is the proposed observational, longitudinal study of the Natural
      History Study of ILI among active duty military members, healthy retirees, and their
      dependents recruited from both inpatient and outpatient settings of military treatment
      facilities (MTF) in the continental US to be followed for a total of four (4) visits over a
      28-day period. Additionally, the investigators also propose to conduct a household-based
      study of influenza (Family Transmission Study) in which individuals who have a
      laboratory-confirmed influenza illness will be recruited and enrolled along with their family
      members for the purpose of studying transmission of influenza within households. Taken
      together, these studies will establish a longitudinal cohort of ILI among active duty members
      and their families, as well as a repository of biological specimens relevant to the
      epidemiology and immunology of infection. Ultimately, these studies will serve as a solid
      foundation on which future investigations of ARI epidemiology, treatment and prevention can
      be based.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an observational, longitudinal study of ARI/ILI among otherwise healthy active duty
      military members, retirees, as well as their spouses and dependents. An additional cohort of
      HIV-infected adults will also be evaluated. We will collect data from clinical findings,
      medical chart review, and diagnostic, virologic, and immunologic assays to describe the
      epidemiology and immunology of ARI/ILI. Subject recruitment will take place in both inpatient
      and outpatient settings of military treatment facilities (MTF) in the continental US.
      Additionally, subject self-referral will be encouraged through institutional review board
      (IRB) approved advertisements. Both adults under 65 years of age and children will be
      eligible for participation. Subjects will be followed for a total of up to 4 visits over a
      28±7-day period. After their final visit (Day 28±7 applicable window), participants may only
      re-enroll into the study after 3 months have passed.

      Nasal swabs, blood specimens (if consented to), buccal cytobrush samples (if consented to),
      and rectal swabs (in select subgroups of consenting inpatients) will be collected in order to
      characterize the etiologic, epidemiologic, and immunologic characteristics of ARI in the
      study population. In the HIV- positive cohort, additional clinical data and blood will be
      collected for HIV-specific factors (e.g., CD4 counts, HIV RNA levels) and for additional
      immunologic studies at days 0 and 28 (± 7) of the study. This is a prospective longitudinal
      study which will use data from clinical findings, medical chart review, and diagnostic,
      virologic and immunologic laboratories to describe the epidemiology and immunology of
      ARI/ILI.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Develop a consortium of Department of Defense research sites capable of collecting detailed prospective clinical data, and biologic samples from active duty members and their families with ILI.</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Develop and validate an influenza severity scale</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Study the relationship between health and fitness of young adults to outcomes of influenza and other respiratory viruses</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Examine the relationship of cell-mediated and humoral immune response to the severity of influenza and other respiratory viruses.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Describe patterns of viral shedding in different influenza types and subtypes.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlate clinical severity and cytokine/humoral response with underlying host genotype.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Natural History Study</arm_group_label>
    <description>The core Natural History Study of ILI is an observational, longitudinal cohort study using data from clinical findings, medical chart review, and diagnostic, virologic and immunologic laboratories to describe the epidemiology and immunology of ILI. This study aims to describe the clinical history of influenza and other viral respiratory pathogens in a population of US military active duty members and their dependents. The primary focus will be the etiology, natural history and immunology of ILI in otherwise healthy adults and children. We will recruit subjects with ILI in both the outpatient and inpatient setting, and will serially collect biological specimens (e.g. nasal/throat swabs, blood, rectal swabs) over a 28-day period. In addition, we will collect a single buccal (cheek) swab.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HIV-Positive Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>In addition, given a number of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-infected subjects who serve in the active duty force, we will also examine a subset of HIV-positive military beneficiaries as part of this consortium. An additional objective of the study will be to descriptively examine the clinical and laboratory characteristics of ILI events among HIV-infected persons using the military's substantial experience in following a stable HIV-infected population. We will recruit subjects with ILI in both the outpatient and inpatient setting, and will serially collect biological specimens (e.g. nasal/throat swabs, blood, rectal swabs) over a 28-day period. In addition, we will collect a single buccal (cheek) swab.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      nasal swabs with storage of multiple harvested (expanded) first generation viral isolates
      (all must opt in); buccal swab storage (may opt out) rectal swab storage (may opt out) serum
      storage (may opt out)
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Males and females ages 17-55 and of military (including active duty enlisted and active
        duty officers from all branches of service), healthy retirees, and their dependents
        (spouses and children) presenting to inpatient/outpatient facilities with ILI will be
        eligible for participation. 17 year old enrollees must be active duty and therefore
        considered adults per DoDI 3216.02.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Natural History Study

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Between 18 and 55 years of age (inclusive), or a 17 year old military service member

          -  Eligible for care in DoD facilities (DEERS eligible).

          -  Have an acute influenza-like illness (ILI) or severe acute respiratory infection
             (SARI) for &lt;/= 7 days

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Proven Group A Streptococcal infection

        Note that proven Group A Streptococcal infection will not be exclusionary IF it is proven
        to be a co-infection with another respiratory pathogen.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>17 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Timothy H Burgess, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences/Infectious Disease Clinical Research Program</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jacqueline Owens Milzman, MS</last_name>
    <phone>301-881-2387</phone>
    <email>jowens@idcrp.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Chris Coles, PhD</last_name>
    <email>ccoles@idcrp.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Naval Medical Center, San Diego, CA</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92134</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John C Arnold, MD</last_name>
      <phone>619-532-7452</phone>
      <email>john.c.arnold.mil@mail.mil</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sara Echols, RN</last_name>
      <phone>619-532-5683</phone>
      <email>sara.j.echols.ctr@mail.mil</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alona Diem</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Martin Army Community Hospital, Fort Benning, GA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>31905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Natasha Law, MA</last_name>
      <phone>706-544-6583</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Arile Hadley</last_name>
      <phone>7065443496</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>CPT Naimyah Yehudah, PA-C</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Walter Reed National Military Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20814</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Heather Burris</last_name>
      <phone>301-295-5542</phone>
      <email>heather.h.burris.ctr@mail.mil</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sheila Taylor-Means</last_name>
      <email>sheila.m.taylor-means.ctr@mail.mil</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Stagliano, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anuradha Ganesan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>San Antonio Military Medical Center/Wilford Hall</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78234</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Charlotte Rhodes</last_name>
      <phone>210-916-5570</phone>
      <email>charlotte.e.rhodes.ctr@mail.mil</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Joanne Holloway</last_name>
      <phone>210-808-2335</phone>
      <email>joanne.p.holloway.ctr@mail.mil</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Patrick Danaher, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Naval Medical Center, Portsmouth, VA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portsmouth</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23708</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rezalina Tant</last_name>
      <phone>757-953-5603</phone>
      <email>rezalina.g.tant.ctr@mail.mil</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Realisha Smith</last_name>
      <phone>757-953-6971</phone>
      <email>realisha.b.smith.ctr@mail.mil</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tahaniyat Lalani, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Madigan Army Medical Center (MAMC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tacoma</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98431</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susan Chambers, RN</last_name>
      <phone>253-968-1643</phone>
      <email>susan.e.chambers4.ctr@mail.mil</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Debra Angell, CCRP</last_name>
      <phone>253-968-4596</phone>
      <email>debra.a.angell.ctr@mail.mil</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mary Fairchok, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christina Schofield, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 10, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 25, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 26, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 22, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 22, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 23, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Timothy Burgess, MD, MPH</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>CAPT Timothy Burgess, MD, MPH</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>influenza</keyword>
  <keyword>illness</keyword>
  <keyword>active-duty</keyword>
  <keyword>virus</keyword>
  <keyword>flu</keyword>
  <keyword>military</keyword>
  <keyword>Influenza-like-illnesses</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Tract Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>We plan to directly share de-identified data with the third party Menssana Research Inc. for a substudy of an investigational device for the diagnosis of influenza. This data will include basic demographic information, flu diagnostic results, smoking status, and symptom history. This data will be de-identified and shared directly with the third party via secure file transfer. This applies only to participants recruited into the substudy at the site San Antonio Military Medical Center.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

