<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01025752</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IIR 09-058</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01025752</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Interactive Voice Response (IVR)-Based Treatment for Chronic Low Back Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>IVR-based Cognitive Behavior Therapy for Chronic Low Back</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study will test how well an innovative method, interactive voice response (IVR),
      can be used for delivering an treatment for chronic low back pain. The use of IVR will
      improve the accessibility of treatment to Veterans. IVR is a computerized interface that
      allows patients to use their telephone to: 1) obtain pre-recorded didactic information, 2)
      report data regarding pain-related symptoms and adherence to pain coping skill practice, and
      3) receive personalized therapist feedback. Although CBT has been shown to be effective in
      reducing pain intensity, traditional CBT requires patients to make frequent office visits.
      The use of IVR will allow Veterans to access CBT from their home via a touch-tone telephone,
      thereby allowing them to access treatment at their convenience without travel to the VA for
      an outpatient appointment. Veterans with chronic low back pain will be randomized in equal
      numbers to receive either standard CBT or IVR-based CBT. Veterans in both conditions will
      receive 10 session of treatment designed to help them manage their chronic pain using pain
      coping skills. The primary outcome measure will be pain intensity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: The primary purpose of this study is to test the efficacy of an innovative
      method, interactive voice response (IVR), for delivering an empirically validated
      psychological (cognitive behavior therapy [CBT]) treatment for chronic pain in order to
      improve access and sustainability of this intervention. The primary clinical equivalence
      hypothesis states that Veterans with chronic low back pain (CLBP) receiving IVR-based CBT
      (ICBT) will demonstrate, relative to standard face-to-face CBT (CBT), equivalent declines in
      reports of pain intensity as measured by the numeric rating scale at post-treatment and
      follow-up. The secondary hypothesis states that Veterans with CLBP receiving ICBT, relative
      to CBT, will demonstrate equivalent declines in reports of pain-related interference and
      emotional distress at post-treatment and follow-up.

      RESEARCH DESIGN: A randomized design will be employed in which standard CBT (CBT) is compared
      to an Interactive CBT (ICBT) treatment condition. Participants will be randomized in equal
      numbers to both conditions. Repeated assessments of key outcome domains will occur at
      pretreatment/baseline and at 3 and 6 months following baseline.

      METHODOLOGY: Subjects will be 230 patients receiving care at the VACHS who report chronic low
      back pain. The primary criteria for inclusion are constant pain of at least three months
      duration with at least a moderate level of average pain (i.e., scores of 4 or greater on a 0
      (no pain) to 10 (worst pain imaginable) on a numerical rating scale of average pain. All
      patients must have access to a touch-tone telephone. Excluded will be patients with life
      threatening or acute physical illness, current alcohol or substance abuse or dependence,
      current psychosis, suicidal ideation, dementia, and individuals seeking surgical pain
      treatment. Comprehensive evaluations will be conducted at each assessment interval. Following
      completion of written consent and an initial baseline evaluation, participants will be
      randomized to one of the two treatments. Sessions will be audiotaped to ensure the fidelity
      of the face-to-face CBT sessions and the personalized therapist feedback in the IVR-based CBT
      condition. Both conditions will involve 10 outpatient therapy sessions with a psychologist
      trained experienced in the delivery of these treatments. Adherence to coping skill practice
      will be assessed using IVR for both treatment groups. Analysis of primary and secondary
      outcome measures will employ mixed-effects models, which will account for the clustering
      induced by repeated measures on individual patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Numeric Rating Scale of Pain Intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>post-treatment (12 weeks), 3 and 6 months post-baseline</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Multidimensional Pain Inventory Interference subscale</measure>
    <time_frame>post-treatment (12 weeks), 3 and 6 months post-baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Roland Morris Disability Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>post-treatment (12 weeks), 3 and 6 months post-baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SF36V</measure>
    <time_frame>post-treatment (12 weeks), 3 and 6 months post-baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Profile of Mood States</measure>
    <time_frame>post-treatment (12 weeks), 3 and 6 months post-baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Depression Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>post-treatment (12 weeks), 3 and 6 months post-baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index</measure>
    <time_frame>post-treatment (12 weeks), 3 and 6 months post-baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Stages of Change Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>post-treatment (12 weeks), 3 and 6 months post-baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Catastrophizing Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>post-treatment (12 weeks), 3 and 6 months post-baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survey of Pain Attitudes</measure>
    <time_frame>post-treatment (12 weeks), 3 and 6 months post-baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">134</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Low Back Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ten session IVR-based cognitive behavior therapy for chronic low back pain</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ten session face to face cognitive behavior therapy for chronic low back pain</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Face to face cognitive behavior therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Ten session face to face cognitive behavior therapy for chronic low back pain</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IVR based cognitive behavioral therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Ten session cognitive behavior therapy for chronic low back pain using interactive voice response therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  presence of at least a moderate level of pain (i.e., pain scores of &gt; or = 4) and
             presence of pain for a period of &gt; or = 3 months

          -  ability to participate safely in the walking portion of the intervention as evidenced
             by ability to walk at least one block

          -  availability of a touch-tone telephone and computer with internet access in the
             participant's residence

          -  Veteran receiving care at VA Connecticut Healthcare System

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  life threatening or acute medical condition that could impair participation (e.g.,
             severe COPD, lower limb amputation, terminal cancer);

          -  psychiatric condition (e.g., active substance abuse, psychosis or suicidality) that
             could impair participation

          -  surgical interventions for pain during their participation in this study

          -  sensory deficits that would impair participation (e.g., hearing loss to a degree that
             telephone usage is not possible).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alicia A. Heapy, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Connecticut Healthcare System West Haven Campus, West Haven, CT</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Connecticut Healthcare System West Haven Campus, West Haven, CT</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06516</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Heapy AA, Higgins DM, LaChappelle KM, Kirlin J, Goulet JL, Czlapinski RA, Buta E, Piette JD, Krein SL, Richardson CR, Kerns RD. Cooperative pain education and self-management (COPES): study design and protocol of a randomized non-inferiority trial of an interactive voice response-based self-management intervention for chronic low back pain. BMC Musculoskelet Disord. 2016 Feb 16;17:85. doi: 10.1186/s12891-016-0924-z.</citation>
    <PMID>26879051</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 3, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 3, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 4, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 15, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>chronic pain</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive behavior therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>low back pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>June 1, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>October 23, 2017</returned>
    <submitted>October 31, 2017</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

