<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03023228</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2009-354</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03023228</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diabetes To Go: An Inpatient Diabetes Survival Skills Education Program</brief_title>
  <official_title>Diabetes To Go: A Pilot Feasibility and Preliminary Efficacy Evaluation of an Inpatient Diabetes Self-management Survival Skills Education Program</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medstar Health Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sanofi</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medstar Health Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A learner-centered diabetes survival skills self-management education program was provided to
      adults with uncontrolled diabetes in the hospital and generated preliminary evidence of
      impact on medication adherence and a trend toward reduction in hospital and emergency
      department admissions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study was a prospective, nonrandomized pilot study conducted among adults with
      uncontrolled diabetes admitted to the Medicine Service of an urban tertiary teaching hospital
      were consented to participate in a pilot study which provided diabetes survival skills
      education. Based on knowledge deficits identified on a diabetes knowledge pre-test the
      patient was directed to view video content corresponding to those deficiencies and content on
      sick days and diabetes complications. Evaluation measures were diabetes knowledge, medication
      adherence, and hospital admissions plus emergency department visits at and/or 3months before
      baseline and at 2 weeks and 3 months post-discharge. There was improvement in diabetes
      knowledge and medication adherence, which was sustained to 3 months. A trend was observed
      toward reduction in emergency department and/or hospital admissions from 3 months
      pre-intervention to 3 months post-discharge for uncontrolled diabetes. This knowledge-based
      program successfully provided survival skills education to hospital patients with
      uncontrolled diabetes and demonstrated preliminary evidence of a positive impact on
      medication adherence and a trend toward reduction in hospital and emergency department
      admissions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of change in Diabetes knowledge as measured by an 11-item diabetes knowledge survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline score obtained before receiving the education intervention. Post test score obtained immediately after the education intervention was completed during the hospital stay, usually within 24 hours or less from the baseline score</time_frame>
    <description>11-item diabetes knowledge survey administered pre- and post- education intervention during the same hospital stay. Baseline score and post intervention score obtained within a 24 hour period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Readmissions to the hospital and the emergency department</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months pre- and 3 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported historic and post-intervention visits to ED and or admissions to the hospital</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication adherence (Modified Morisky Medication Adherence Scale 4-item)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline pre intervention then at 2 weeks after intervention and at 3 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Modified Morisky Medication Adherence Scale 4-item</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">125</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <condition>Hyperglycemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>diabetes self-management education</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Diabetes survival skills self-management education (DSME) program content was aligned with American Diabetes Association and Joint Commission suggested key areas for hospital diabetes education. Content areas were as follows: when and how to take diabetes medications; glycemic goals and self-blood glucose monitoring; definition, prevention, recognition, and treatment of hypoglycemia and hyperglycemia; what to do before you see the dietitian; sick day management; and when to call the doctor or go to the ED. Program content was created for delivery via either DVD or print format.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>diabetes self-management education</intervention_name>
    <description>1-group, pre-test/post-test design feasibility and preliminary efficacy evaluation of diabetes survival skills self-management education delivered at the hospital bedside.</description>
    <arm_group_label>diabetes self-management education</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>survival skills education</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  English speaking with a diabetes mellitus diagnosis (ICD 9 codes 250.xx)

          -  an admitting blood glucose level of &gt; 200 mg/dL or ≤ 40 mg/dL, and

          -  an anticipated hospital stay of ≥ 2 days, as estimated by the medical staff, to allow
             sufficient time for delivery of program content

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  pregnancy

          -  admission to an intensive care unit, and

          -  any medical condition or cognitive dysfunction that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, would preclude active participation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>michelle f magee, MD, MBBCh,</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medstar Health Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Magee MF, Khan NH, Desale S, Nassar CM. Diabetes to Go: Knowledge- and Competency-Based Hospital Survival Skills Diabetes Education Program Improves Postdischarge Medication Adherence. Diabetes Educ. 2014 May;40(3):344-350. Epub 2014 Feb 20.</citation>
    <PMID>24557596</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 4, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 13, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 18, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes mellitus</keyword>
  <keyword>Hyperglycemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Inpatient</keyword>
  <keyword>self-management education</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperglycemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

