<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02357602</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-2797</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02357602</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dose Proportionality of TFV-DP After a Single Dose of GS-7340 in Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Dose Proportionality of TFV-DP in Mucosal Tissue, and Endogenous Nucleotide Quantification, After a Single Dose of GS-7340 in Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Gilead Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Purpose:

      The purpose of this study is to characterize the dose-proportionality in the distribution of
      tenofovir alafenamide (TAF) and tenofovir (TFV) in plasma and mucosal tissues, and
      TFV-diphosphate (TFV-DP) in peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) and mucosal tissues of
      healthy female subjects following a single oral dose of GS-7430 at 5mg, 10mg, and 25mg.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants:

      This study will consist of approximately 24 premenopausal healthy volunteer women between
      18-49 years of age with an intact cervix, uterus, and gastrointestinal tract. Women will be
      enrolled in the study within 42 days of screening depending on the timing of their menstrual
      cycle in comparison to the screening visit, and then will be on study for 14 days, with
      follow-up 1-14 days after the end of study sampling. All study visits will be conducted in
      the North Carolina Translational and Clinical Sciences (NCTraCS) Clinical Translational
      Research Center (CTRC) at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.

      Procedures (methods):This is a Phase 1, single center, open-label, dose-ranging
      pharmacokinetic study of TFV and TFV-DP mucosal tissue concentrations measured after a single
      dose of GS-7340. Each arm is divided into three dosing groups: 5, 10, or 25mg. Participants
      will take a single dose of study drug within 7-14 days following the end of the subjects'
      menstrual period. Participants will be sequentially assigned to one of the three TAF doses
      and four biopsy schedules. Two women from each of the dosing groups will be assigned to one
      of four biopsy schedules for a total of 8 women per dosing group. Samples of blood plasma,
      cervicovaginal fluid (CVF), cervical tissue, vaginal tissue, and rectal tissue will be
      collected from participants at varying time points over the 14 days post-dose. Subjects will
      return to clinic within 14 days after the last sampling to complete a follow-up safety visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Dose-Proportionality</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 1, 3, 6, 12, 24 hours, and 3, 7, 10, and 14 days following single dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the dose-proportionality in the distribution of TAF and TFV in the plasma of healthy female subjects following a single oral dose of GS-7340 at 5mg, 10mg, and 25mg. This will be used to develop a predictive pharmacokinetic model for TAF which will allow for TFVdp exposure predictions given a specific dose and dosing interval.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tissue Dose-Proportionality</measure>
    <time_frame>At 3, 6, 12 and 24 hours and 3, 7, 10 and 14 days following single dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the dose-proportionality in the distribution of TAF and TFV in mucosal tissues, and TFV-DP in mucosal tissues of healthy female subjects following a single oral dose of GS-7340 at 5mg, 10mg, and 25mg. This will be used to develop a predictive pharmacokinetic model for TAF which will allow for TFVdp exposure predictions given a specific dose and dosing interval.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PBMC Dose-Proportionality</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 3, 6, 12, 24 hours and 3, 7, 10, and 14 days following single dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the dose-proportionality in the distribution of TFV-DP in PBMCs of healthy female subjects following a single oral dose of GS-7340 at 5mg, 10mg, and 25mg. This will be used to develop a predictive pharmacokinetic model for TAF which will allow for TFVdp exposure predictions given a specific dose and dosing interval.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra-subject variability in intracellular deoxyadenosine triphosphate (dATP) in peripheral blood</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 3, 6, 12, 24 hours and 3, 7, 10, and 14 days following single dose</time_frame>
    <description>To determine intra-subject variability in intracellular dATP in PBMCs and ratios of TFVdp:dATP.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inter-subject variability in intracellular deoxyadenosine triphosphate (dATP) in peripheral blood</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 3, 6, 12, 24 hours and 3, 7, 10, and 14 days following single dose</time_frame>
    <description>To determine inter-subject variability in intracellular dATP in PBMCs and ratios of TFVdp:dATP.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra-subject variability in intracellular deoxyadenosine triphosphate (dATP) in mucosal tissues</measure>
    <time_frame>At 3, 6, 12 and 24 hours and 3, 7, 10 and 14 days following single dose</time_frame>
    <description>To determine intra-subject variability in intracellular dATP in cervical, vaginal, and rectal tissues and ratios of TFVdp:dATP.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inter-subject variability in intracellular deoxyadenosine triphosphate (dATP) in mucosal tissues</measure>
    <time_frame>At 3, 6, 12 and 24 hours and 3, 7, 10 and 14 days following single dose</time_frame>
    <description>To determine inter-subject variability in intracellular dATP in cervical, vaginal, and rectal tissues and ratios of TFVdp:dATP.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cervicovaginal Fluid (CVF) Concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1, 3, 6, 12, 24 hours and 3, 7, 10, and 14 days following single dose.</time_frame>
    <description>To determine if TFV and TAF concentration in CVF changes in proportion to TFV, TAF, and TFV-DP concentration in cervical and vaginal tissue</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1. GS-7340 25mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The first 8 women on study will be assigned to take a single dose of 25mg TAF (1 tablet) orally.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2. GS-7340 10mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The 2nd group of 8 women will be sequentially assigned to take a single dose of 10mg TAF (1 tablet) orally.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3. GS-7340 5mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The final 8 women on study will be sequentially assigned to take a single dose of 5mg TAF (1/2 tablet) orally.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GS-7340</intervention_name>
    <description>Medication is supplied in 10 or 25mg tablets, so subjects will receive either 1/2 or one tablet in a single dose.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1. GS-7340 25mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2. GS-7340 10mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3. GS-7340 5mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TAF</other_name>
    <other_name>Tenofovir Alafenamide</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          1. Healthy pre-menopausal female subjects between the ages of 18 and 49 years, inclusive
             on the date of screening, with an intact gastrointestinal tract, uterus, and cervix.

          2. All subjects must have an estimated calculated creatinine clearance (eCcr) of at least
             80 mL/min

          3. All subjects must have negative pregnancy tests, and be using an acceptable form of
             birth control

          4. Body Mass Index (BMI) of approximately 18 to 34 kg/m²; and a total body weight &gt; 45 kg
             (99 lbs).

          5. Evidence of a personally signed and dated informed consent document indicating that
             the subject has been informed of all pertinent aspects of the trial.

          6. Willing and able to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plan, laboratory tests,
             and other trial procedures.

          7. Subject must have documentation of a normal pap smear within 36 months of the
             screening visit, no procedures for abnormal cervical/vaginal pathology in the last six
             months, at least one prior gynecological visit as part of subject's routine medical
             history.

          8. Subject must be willing to abstain from sexual intercourse, douching, and all
             intravaginal and intrarectal objects and products for at least 72 hours prior to Day 1
             until study completion.

          9. Subject must be HIV-1 and Hepatitis B surface antigen negative

         10. Subject must not be actively involved in the conception process.

         11. Subject must be able to swallow pills and have no allergies to any component of the
             study products

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. Evidence or history of clinically significant hematological, renal, endocrine,
             pulmonary, gastrointestinal, cardiovascular, hepatic, psychiatric, neurologic, or
             allergic disease (including documented drug allergies, but excluding untreated,
             asymptomatic, seasonal allergies at time of dosing).

          2. Subjects with a history of hysterectomy

          3. Subjects who are pregnant, possibly pregnant or lactating

          4. Subjects with a presence of vaginal discharge or genital bleeding at screening

          5. History of febrile illness within five days prior to first dose.

          6. Any condition possibly affecting drug absorption (eg, gastrectomy).

          7. A positive urine drug screen.

          8. A positive result for HIV, Hepatitis B or C

          9. An untreated-positive test for syphilis, gonorrhea, Chlamydia, or trichomonas at
             screening, or symptomatic bacterial vaginosis.

         10. Any laboratory chemistry or hematology result Grade 2 or greater according to the
             Division of Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome (DAIDS) Laboratory Grading Tables

         11. Treatment with an investigational drug within 4 months preceding the first dose of
             trial medication.

         12. History of regular alcohol consumption exceeding study limits

         13. Participation in a clinical trial involving vaginal or rectal biopsies within 6 months
             preceding the first dose of trial medication.

         14. Use of prescription or nonprescription drugs, vitamins, and dietary supplements within
             7 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) prior to the first dose of trial
             medication and unable to avoid use during the study period until after the last sample
             is collected.

         15. Blood donation of approximately 1 pint (500 mL) within 56 days prior to dosing.

         16. History of sensitivity to heparin or heparin-induced thrombocytopenia.

         17. Allergy to lidocaine or Monsel's solution.

         18. Allergy to latex.

         19. Abnormal pap smear in the past 36 months

         20. Any degree of ectopy or abnormality evident during the pelvic exam at screening.

         21. Any condition which, in the opinion of the investigator, is likely to interfere with
             follow-up or ability to take the study medication appropriately.

         22. Unwilling or unable to comply with the dietary and concomitant drug restrictions in
             regard to study drug administration as outlined in the study procedures and prohibited
             medications sections.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Angela DM Kashuba, PharmD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UNC Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 14, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 2, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 6, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 29, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 29, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 30, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Participants</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV-1 negative</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tenofovir</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

