<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02352714</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-011286</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02352714</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Pain Control With Hormonal IUS Insertion</brief_title>
  <acronym>SOPHI</acronym>
  <official_title>Study of Pain Control With Hormonal IUS Insertion (SOPHI Study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bayer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to compare pain during insertion of the Skyla® IUS using a 100mm visual
      analog scale (VAS) among 92 young women aged 14 to 22 years randomized to receive a
      paracervical (n=46) block versus a sham paracervical block (n=46).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Intrauterine systems (IUS) are among the most effective forms of reversible contraception.
      Numerous studies demonstrate their safety and efficacy. Despite this, uptake of IUSs among
      U.S. young women aged 14 to 22 years has been low. Increasing the use of this effective, long
      acting contraception among young women is an important public health goal, as it could help
      to reduce the high rates of unintended pregnancies in this population.

      A major barrier to young women's utilization of IUSs is fear of pain during insertion.
      Unfortunately, studies evaluating methods of pain control during IUS insertion have focused
      on adult women, leaving the question unanswered as to the best pain management method for
      young women. Compared to adult women, young women have less experience with pelvic exams and
      may therefore derive greater benefit from pain control measures during gynecologic
      procedures, such as IUS insertions. Young women and their providers are seeking effective
      pain control options; yet, there is a lack of high quality, comparative effectiveness
      research to guide decision making. This proposal seeks to fill this important gap.

      With the introduction of the Skyla IUS (Bayer Healthcare Pharmaceuticals, Inc.) to the U.S.
      market in January 2013, a new approach to pain management became possible. Skyla is smaller
      than existing IUSs and may therefore cause less pain during insertion. The pain response
      triggered during Skyla insertion may be better controlled by existing pain control options.
      This is the underlying premise of this study.

      In addition to the size of an IUS, theoretical and empirical data suggest that paracervical
      blocks have the greatest promise for pain control during IUS insertion compared to other pain
      control options. Paracervical infiltration of a local anesthetic into the cervix interrupts
      the visceral sensory fibers of the lower uterus, cervix, and upper vagina. Data from several
      clinical trials indicate that paracervical blocks provide clinically significant control of
      pain during multiple types of gynecologic procedures. One recently published study evaluated
      the effectiveness of paracervical blocks during IUS insertion and found a marginally
      significant reduction in pain, but the study was underpowered and focused on adult women. The
      value of a paracervical block in young women receiving an IUS remains unclear.

      The investigator propose to conduct a randomized, controlled single-blind trial comparing
      pain with Skyla IUS insertion among young women aged 14 to 22 years randomized to receive a
      paracervical block versus a sham cervical block. This study will provide important
      information for counseling young women about pain management during IUS insertion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative (At the time of insertion of the IUS)</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome will be assessed using a visual analogue scale (VAS). Assessment will occur at the time of the insertion of the IUS device. The IUS will be placed according to manufacturer's recommendation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">98</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Paracervical Nerve Block</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ten milliliters of 1% lidocaine paracervical anesthetic will be injected at three cervical locations: 1 mL at the tenaculum site (12 o'clock on a clock face) and 4.5 mL each at the 4 o'clock and 8 o'clock positions. A 3 minute waiting period will be used between the administration of the paracervical nerve block and the insertion of IUS to allow the paracervical block to take effect.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Paracervical Block</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>To perform the sham cervical block, the cervix will be touched with the blunt end of a Q-tip at the three locations described above for the paracervical block. The cervical mucosa will not be broken during the sham block. A 3 minute waiting period will again occur between administration of the sham block and IUS insertion to be consistent with the procedure used for the nerve block.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paracervical Nerve Block</intervention_name>
    <description>Block randomization to receive lidocaine paracervical nerve block vs sham cervical block</description>
    <arm_group_label>Paracervical Nerve Block</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>1 % Lidocaine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham Paracervical Block</intervention_name>
    <description>Block randomization to receive lidocaine paracervical nerve block vs sham cervical block</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Paracervical Block</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Blunt End of a Q-Tip</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Nulliparous (i.e., no pregnancy &gt; 24 weeks)

          -  Not currently pregnant

          -  Not pregnant in the past 6 weeks

          -  Willing to be randomized to a paracervical nerve block or sham paracervical block
             group

          -  Interested in using an intrauterine system (IUS)

          -  Able to read and provide written informed consent in English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  An allergy, hypersensitivity, or absolute medical contra-indication to using
             lidocaine, other amino-amide local anesthetics, or to non-steroidal anti-inflammatory
             agents, such as ibuprofen

          -  A history of epilepsy or peptic ulcer disease

          -  Moderate to severe asthma that precludes non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAID)
             use

          -  Hepatic or renal failure

          -  Moderate to severe cardiac disease

          -  Previous use of an IUS or a history of a prior failed IUS insertion

          -  Use of a narcotic or benzodiazepine in the past 24 hours

          -  Positive pregnancy test or reasonable risk of pregnancy

          -  Current cervicitis

          -  Intrauterine infection in the past 90 days

          -  Meet Centers for Disease Control Medical Eligibility Criteria (MEC) category 3 or 4
             classification for IUS use

          -  Currently breastfeeding
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>22 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aletha Y Akers, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thomas Jefferson University Hospitals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kavanaugh ML, Jerman J, Hubacher D, Kost K, Finer LB. Characteristics of women in the United States who use long-acting reversible contraceptive methods. Obstet Gynecol. 2011 Jun;117(6):1349-57. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0b013e31821c47c9.</citation>
    <PMID>21606745</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Finer LB, Jerman J, Kavanaugh ML. Changes in use of long-acting contraceptive methods in the United States, 2007-2009. Fertil Steril. 2012 Oct;98(4):893-7. doi: 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2012.06.027. Epub 2012 Jul 13.</citation>
    <PMID>22795639</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Finer LB. Unintended pregnancy among U.S. adolescents: accounting for sexual activity. J Adolesc Health. 2010 Sep;47(3):312-4. doi: 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2010.02.002. Epub 2010 Apr 9.</citation>
    <PMID>20708573</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kavanaugh ML, Frohwirth L, Jerman J, Popkin R, Ethier K. Long-acting reversible contraception for adolescents and young adults: patient and provider perspectives. J Pediatr Adolesc Gynecol. 2013 Apr;26(2):86-95. doi: 10.1016/j.jpag.2012.10.006. Epub 2012 Dec 31.</citation>
    <PMID>23287602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hubacher D, Reyes V, Lillo S, Zepeda A, Chen PL, Croxatto H. Pain from copper intrauterine device insertion: randomized trial of prophylactic ibuprofen. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2006 Nov;195(5):1272-7.</citation>
    <PMID>17074548</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Massey SE, Varady JC, Henzl MR. Pain relief with naproxen following insertion of an intrauterine device. J Reprod Med. 1974 Dec;13(6):226-31.</citation>
    <PMID>4612152</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heikinheimo O, Inki P, Kunz M, Parmhed S, Anttila AM, Olsson SE, Hurskainen R, Gemzell-Danielsson K. Double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled study on the effect of misoprostol on ease of consecutive insertion of the levonorgestrel-releasing intrauterine system. Contraception. 2010 Jun;81(6):481-6. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2010.01.020. Epub 2010 Mar 1.</citation>
    <PMID>20472114</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dijkhuizen K, Dekkers OM, Holleboom CA, de Groot CJ, Hellebrekers BW, van Roosmalen GJ, Janssen CA, Helmerhorst FM. Vaginal misoprostol prior to insertion of an intrauterine device: an RCT. Hum Reprod. 2011 Feb;26(2):323-9. doi: 10.1093/humrep/deq348. Epub 2010 Dec 15.</citation>
    <PMID>21159683</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edelman AB, Schaefer E, Olson A, Van Houten L, Bednarek P, Leclair C, Jensen JT. Effects of prophylactic misoprostol administration prior to intrauterine device insertion in nulliparous women. Contraception. 2011 Sep;84(3):234-9. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2011.01.016. Epub 2011 Mar 3.</citation>
    <PMID>21843686</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mody SK, Kiley J, Rademaker A, Gawron L, Stika C, Hammond C. Pain control for intrauterine device insertion: a randomized trial of 1% lidocaine paracervical block. Contraception. 2012 Dec;86(6):704-9. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2012.06.004. Epub 2012 Jul 6.</citation>
    <PMID>22770792</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bednarek PH, Micks EA, Edelman AB, Li H, Jensen JT. The effect of nitroprusside on IUD insertion experience in nulliparous women: a pilot study. Contraception. 2013 Apr;87(4):421-5. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2012.10.030. Epub 2012 Dec 4.</citation>
    <PMID>23218853</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McNicholas CP, Madden T, Zhao Q, Secura G, Allsworth JE, Peipert JF. Cervical lidocaine for IUD insertional pain: a randomized controlled trial. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2012 Nov;207(5):384.e1-6. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2012.09.018. Epub 2012 Sep 20.</citation>
    <PMID>23107081</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tangsiriwatthana T, Sangkomkamhang US, Lumbiganon P, Laopaiboon M. Paracervical local anaesthesia for cervical dilatation and uterine intervention. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2009 Jan 21;(1):CD005056. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD005056.pub2. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2013;9:CD005056.</citation>
    <PMID>19160245</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ahmad G, Duffy J, Watson AJ. Pain relief in hysterosalpingography. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2007 Apr 18;(2):CD006106. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2015;9:CD006106.</citation>
    <PMID>17443612</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Renner RM, Jensen JT, Nichols MD, Edelman AB. Pain control in first-trimester surgical abortion: a systematic review of randomized controlled trials. Contraception. 2010 May;81(5):372-88. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2009.12.008. Epub 2010 Jan 27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20399943</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Karabayirli S, Ayrim AA, Muslu B. Comparison of the analgesic effects of oral tramadol and naproxen sodium on pain relief during IUD insertion. J Minim Invasive Gynecol. 2012 Sep-Oct;19(5):581-4. doi: 10.1016/j.jmig.2012.04.004. Epub 2012 Jul 4.</citation>
    <PMID>22766124</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jensen HH, Blaabjerg J, Lyndrup J. [Prophylactic use of prostaglandin synthesis inhibitors in connection with IUD insertion]. Ugeskr Laeger. 1998 Nov 23;160(48):6958-61. Danish.</citation>
    <PMID>9846090</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rowbotham MC. What is a &quot;clinically meaningful&quot; reduction in pain? Pain. 2001 Nov;94(2):131-2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11690725</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Todd KH, Funk KG, Funk JP, Bonacci R. Clinical significance of reported changes in pain severity. Ann Emerg Med. 1996 Apr;27(4):485-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8604867</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allen RH, Bartz D, Grimes DA, Hubacher D, O'Brien P. Interventions for pain with intrauterine device insertion. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2009 Jul 8;(3):CD007373. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD007373.pub2. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2015;7:CD007373.</citation>
    <PMID>19588429</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sääv I, Aronsson A, Marions L, Stephansson O, Gemzell-Danielsson K. Cervical priming with sublingual misoprostol prior to insertion of an intrauterine device in nulliparous women: a randomized controlled trial. Hum Reprod. 2007 Oct;22(10):2647-52. Epub 2007 Jul 25.</citation>
    <PMID>17652452</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 22, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 28, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 2, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Adolescents</keyword>
  <keyword>Women's Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Contraception</keyword>
  <keyword>Reproduction</keyword>
  <keyword>Comparative Effectiveness Research</keyword>
  <keyword>Pregnancy Prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Intrauterine Device</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lidocaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

