<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02357537</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TLS-UC-003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02357537</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Decentralized Dietary UC Pilot Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study Investigating a Decentralized Approach to Studying Dietary Intervention in Patients With Ulcerative Colitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Transparency Life Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Transparency Life Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed to assess differences in remote and on-site patient study
      participation in the State of Massachusetts, as well as the significance of dietary
      interventions and their impact on UC. The study will activate one site with a Principal
      Investigator who will utilize each subject's local care system (local Gastroenterologist) to
      collect study data, along with telemonitoring and video visits, to make key study assessments
      and decisions regarding subjects' progression in the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Endoscopy Mayo Score Comparison (proportion of endoscopies to which an independent reader can successfully assign an endoscopic Mayo Clinic sub-score)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of the proportion of endoscopies to which an independent reader can successfully assign an endoscopic Mayo Clinic sub-score between Study Arms 1 and 2.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance (proportion of missing or non-evaluable records per patient and the proportion of patients who did not complete the study)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 7</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of the proportion of missing or non-evaluable records per patient and the proportion of patients who did not complete the study between Study Arms 1 and 2.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Combined Anti-inflammatory Diet (Change from baseline in fecal calprotectin/microbiome levels)</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 0, 5 and 7</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in fecal calprotectin/microbiome levels between Control (standard nutritional advice) and CAID (dietary intervention) arms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mayo Score and Patient Simple Clinical Colitis Activity Index Difference (Difference in partial Mayo Clinic sub-Score and Patient Simple Clinical Colitis Activity Index)</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 and 7</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in partial Mayo Clinic sub-Score and Patient Simple Clinical Colitis Activity Index between Control and CAID (dietary intervention).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Weekly through week 11</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in incidence of Adverse Events (AEs) and Serious Adverse Events (SAEs) between Study Arms 1 and 2 and between Control and CAID (dietary intervention) arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dietary Compliance Comparison</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 7</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of patient non-compliance events with dietary regimen between arms 1 and 2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant Satisfaction Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 7</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in reported patient satisfaction with trial participation between arms 1 and 2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mayo Score Discrepancy Frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 7</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of discrepancy between Principal Investigator-assessed and gastroenterologist-assessed Mayo Clinic Endoscopy Sub-Scores for Arm 2 patients at baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physician's Global Assessment Discrepancy Frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 7</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of discrepancy between Principal Investigator-assessed and gastroenterologist-assessed Mayo Clinic Physician's Global Assessment Sub-Score for Arm 2 patients at baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">51</enrollment>
  <condition>Colitis, Ulcerative</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Traditional</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in Study Arm 1 will undergo a screening process, and if randomized, will follow a traditional, site-based clinical trial model and undergo a baseline visit and 3 more in-person visits with the Principal Investigator (total of 4 visits).
Subjects in each Study Arm will be randomized (2:1) to follow one of two dietary regimens during the study: the Combined Anti-Inflammatory Diet (CAID) or Control (standard nutritional advice).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Remote</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in Study Arm 2 will undergo a screening process, and if randomized, will undergo one Baseline visit at the local Gastroenterologist's office and 4 video visits with the Principal Investigator. A mobile nurse will visit subjects at a distant location (such as their home) to obtain blood samples at visits 1 and 4.
Subjects in each Study Arm will be randomized (2:1) to follow one of two dietary regimens during the study: the Combined Anti-Inflammatory Diet (CAID) or Control (standard nutritional advice).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Combined Anti-inflammatory Diet (CAID)</intervention_name>
    <description>The CAID requires participants to modify their diet to include certain types of foods that may have anti-inflammatory properties. Participants on the CAID will be required to abstain from red meat and alcoholic beverages.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Traditional</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Remote</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males and females between the ages of 18 and 80, inclusive, who reside in the state of
             Massachusetts.

          2. Ability and willingness to provide documented informed consent and to comply with the
             study procedures, including in-person visits for Arm 1 and video visits for Arm 2.

          3. Documented history of moderate to severe active UC

          4. Disease duration of ≥12 weeks at the time of screening (diagnosed according to
             American College of Gastroenterology practice guidelines)

          5. Screening fecal calprotectin&gt;350 mg/g

          6. Diagnosis of moderately to severely active UC, including historical endoscopy sub
             score ≥2; a rectal bleeding sub score ≥1 and disease activity a minimum of 25 cm from
             the anal verge.

          7. Documented (via video or report) endoscopy performed within 2 years prior to
             randomization.

          8. Access to a computer or mobile device with internet connection and an active email
             address.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior extensive colonic resection, subtotal or total colectomy or planned surgery for
             UC

          2. Past or present ileostomy or colostomy

          3. Short bowel syndrome

          4. Diagnosis of indeterminate colitis, fulminant colitis, toxic megacolon

          5. Past or present fistula or abdominal abscess

          6. History or current evidence of colonic mucosal dysplasia

          7. Use of tube feeding, defined formula diets or parenteral alimentation/nutrition which
             has not been discontinued ≥3 weeks prior to study enrollment

          8. Use of anticoagulants, herbal supplements and omega-3/fish oil supplements during the
             study

          9. Crohn's Disease

         10. Significant uncontrolled co-morbidity, such as neurological, cardiac (e.g., moderate
             to severe heart failure NYHA class III/IV), pulmonary, renal, hepatic, endocrine or
             gastrointestinal disorders

         11. History of alcohol, drug or chemical abuse within 6 months prior to screening

         12. Pregnant females, those intending to become pregnant, and those who are lactating

         13. Current participation in any other clinical trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tomasz Sablinski, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Transparency Life Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Justine States</last_name>
    <phone>(617) 732-9110</phone>
    <email>dietaryUCTrial@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Crohn's and Colitis Center at Brigham and Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brookline</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02467</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Justine States</last_name>
      <phone>617-732-9110</phone>
      <email>dietaryUCTrial@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joshua Korzenik, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 23, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 2, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 6, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 5, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 5, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 6, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Telemedicine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colitis, Ulcerative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Inflammatory Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>March 29, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>June 15, 2017</returned>
    <submitted>September 19, 2017</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

