<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02352376</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11104413.6.0000.5152</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02352376</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Noninvasive Ventilation After Coronary Bypass Grafting</brief_title>
  <acronym>Physiotherapy</acronym>
  <official_title>Effects of Non Invasive Ventilation on Heart Rate Variability After Coronary Bypass Grafting: Comparison Between Different Ventilator</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Federal University of Uberlandia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Federal University of Uberlandia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, quantitative, randomized, crossover study. Were included in this study
      10 people in the Intensive Care Unit at University Hospital in Uberlandia, on the first day
      of the postoperative coronary artery bypass graft (CABG). For data collection was performed
      randomization on the block (2: 4), to determine the first technique to be used and then a
      wash-out period of one hour was allowed for the research subject reaches the systemic
      arterial pressure, heart rate, respiratory rate and oxygen saturation baseline. And after,
      for cross-over, the second technique was performed. Non-invasive ventilation was performed
      for 30 minutes each ventilator. All subjects underwent noninvasive ventilation using two
      models of ventilators, they are conventional (designed for invasive ventilation but is also
      used in non-invasive ventilation mode) and specific (designed for non-invasive ventilation).
      Hemodynamic, autonomic and respiratory variables are monitored. We use the hypothesis that
      non-invasive ventilation performed with two fan models can alter autonomic function and that
      there is hemodynamic changes related to autonomic function in different ventilators in
      postoperative coronary artery bypass grafting.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: The patients in postoperative coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) have impaired
      cardiac autonomic function. However, no studies have evaluated the influence of different
      ventilators during noninvasive ventilation (NIV) in the autonomic modulation associated with
      hemodynamic changes. Objective: Evaluate the autonomic behavior and hemodynamic changes
      during the execution of the NIV with two models of mechanical ventilators in subjects after
      CABG. Material and Methods: This is quantitative randomized, prospective, crossover study.
      The subjects were selected on first day postoperatively CABG and was performance NIV
      procedure using two different ventilators: conventional ventilator and specific ventilator
      for the use of NIV for 30 minutes, each. Block randomization was used to determine the
      technique that begins to approach then by crossover, perform the sequential technique. The
      heart rate variability (HRV), heart rate, respiratory rate, oxygen peripheral saturation and
      arterial pressure were evaluated before procedure, in the instants 5, 10, 15, 20, 25, 30
      minutes during NIV each and 15 minutes after the end of the NIV application. HRV was
      evaluated using the time and frequency domain.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Variability of heart rate front the use of noninvasive ventilation in two different ventilators in patients after cardiac surgery, measured by Polar RS800 CX.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The autonomic variables evaluated are: standard deviation of all normal RR intervals recorded in a time interval (SDNN); standard deviation of the mean of normal RR intervals every 5 minutes at a time, expressed in milliseconds (SDANN); percentage of R-Ri with adjacent difference of duration greater than 50 milliseconds (pNN50) and the square root of the average squared difference between the adjacent R-Ri normal in a period of time, expressed in milliseconds (rMSSD). All variables will be assessed by Polar RS800CX</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the indices of variability of heart rate, systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure and heart rate during noninvasive ventilation with two models of ventilatotors in patients after cardiac surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Bypass</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional ventilator</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>30 minutes of non-invasive ventilation was performed with conventional ventilator.The order of the procedures was determined by randomization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Specific ventilator</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>30 minutes of non-invasive ventilation was performed with specific respirator. The order of the procedures was determined by randomization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional ventilator</intervention_name>
    <description>A ventilator designed for invasive ventilation was used has mode non-invasive ventilation with leakage compensation (50% of the predetermined tidal volume).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional ventilator</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Specific ventilator</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Specific ventilator</intervention_name>
    <description>A ventilator was used designed for non-invasive ventilation has an algorithm that calculates the loss of pressure and automatically compensates for leak</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional ventilator</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Specific ventilator</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

          -  Age over 18 years .Who were breathing spontaneously with peripheral oxygen saturation
             (SpO2) ≥ 90% and supplemental oxygen ≤ 3 l / min.

          -  Indication for use of NIV

        Exclusion criteria

          -  Hemodynamic instability with hypertensive response being considered systolic blood
             pressure (SBP) greater than 180 mmHg and diastolic blood pressure (DBP) greater than
             110 mmHg, or difference in SBP and DBP less than 20 mmHg or framework shock
             considering SBP &lt;90 mmHg and / or DBP &lt;50 mmHg, since the normal SBP were between
             90-130 mmHg and DBP 60-90 mmHg

          -  Presence of active cardiac pacemaker

          -  Invasive mechanical ventilation more than 24 hours

          -  Use of intra aortic balloon

          -  Postoperatively Myocardial infarction after surgery

          -  Ineffective cough with bronchial hypersecretion

          -  Inability to adequately swallowing and/or protect the airway

          -  Abdominal distension

          -  Nausea

          -  Vomiting
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Valdeci C Dionísio, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Federal University of Uberlandia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Heart rate variability. Standards of measurement, physiological interpretation, and clinical use. Task Force of the European Society of Cardiology and the North American Society of Pacing and Electrophysiology. Eur Heart J. 1996 Mar;17(3):354-81.</citation>
    <PMID>8737210</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Carnevali L, Sgoifo A. Vagal modulation of resting heart rate in rats: the role of stress, psychosocial factors, and physical exercise. Front Physiol. 2014 Mar 24;5:118. doi: 10.3389/fphys.2014.00118. eCollection 2014. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24715877</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pantoni CB, Di Thommazo L, Mendes RG, Catai AM, Luzzi S, Amaral Neto O, Borghi-Silva A. Effects of different levels of positive airway pressure on breathing pattern and heart rate variability after coronary artery bypass grafting surgery. Braz J Med Biol Res. 2011 Jan;44(1):38-45. Epub 2010 Nov 19.</citation>
    <PMID>21085891</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ozyilmaz E, Ugurlu AO, Nava S. Timing of noninvasive ventilation failure: causes, risk factors, and potential remedies. BMC Pulm Med. 2014 Feb 13;14:19. doi: 10.1186/1471-2466-14-19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24520952</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sasaki K, Maruyama R. Consciously controlled breathing decreases the high-frequency component of heart rate variability by inhibiting cardiac parasympathetic nerve activity. Tohoku J Exp Med. 2014 Jul;233(3):155-63.</citation>
    <PMID>24965685</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Radaelli A, Raco R, Perfetti P, Viola A, Azzellino A, Signorini MG, Ferrari AU. Effects of slow, controlled breathing on baroreceptor control of heart rate and blood pressure in healthy men. J Hypertens. 2004 Jul;22(7):1361-70.</citation>
    <PMID>15201553</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pinsky MR. Cardiovascular issues in respiratory care. Chest. 2005 Nov;128(5 Suppl 2):592S-597S. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16306058</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zhu GF, Wang DJ, Liu S, Jia M, Jia SJ. Efficacy and safety of noninvasive positive pressure ventilation in the treatment of acute respiratory failure after cardiac surgery. Chin Med J (Engl). 2013 Dec;126(23):4463-9.</citation>
    <PMID>24286408</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zarbock A, Mueller E, Netzer S, Gabriel A, Feindt P, Kindgen-Milles D. Prophylactic nasal continuous positive airway pressure following cardiac surgery protects from postoperative pulmonary complications: a prospective, randomized, controlled trial in 500 patients. Chest. 2009 May;135(5):1252-1259. doi: 10.1378/chest.08-1602. Epub 2008 Nov 18.</citation>
    <PMID>19017864</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yang LX, Zhou YJ, Wang ZJ, Li YP, Chai M. Impact of invasive treatment strategy on health-related quality of life six months after non-ST-elevation acute coronary syndrome. J Geriatr Cardiol. 2014 Sep;11(3):206-11. doi: 10.11909/j.issn.1671-5411.2014.03.003.</citation>
    <PMID>25278968</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yan TD, Padang R, Poh C, Cao C, Wilson MK, Bannon PG, Vallely MP. Drug-eluting stents versus coronary artery bypass grafting for the treatment of coronary artery disease: a meta-analysis of randomized and nonrandomized studies. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2011 May;141(5):1134-44. doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2010.07.001. Epub 2010 Dec 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21167508</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 10, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 28, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 2, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 28, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 28, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 2, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Federal University of Uberlandia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Célia Regina Lopes</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>EFFECTS OF NON INVASIVE VENTILATION ON HEART RATE VARIABILITY AFTER CORONARY BYPASS GRAFTING: COMPARISON BETWEEN DIFFERENT VENTILATORS</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Noninvasive ventilation</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart rate variability</keyword>
  <keyword>Thoracic surgery</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

