<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02359214</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>855/13/AT/CSN</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02359214</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Vitamin D3 Supplementation on Cardiometabolic Risk</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Vitamin D3 Supplementation on Cardiometabolic Risk Factors in a Cohort of Overweight and Obese Adults in the UK</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Chester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Chester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Supplementation studies with vitamin D have been performed where cardiometabolic risk markers
      have been assessed but these are few, and results are inconsistent. Hence, the purpose of
      this study is to determine:

        1. Whether administering supplemental Vitamin D3 at a dose of 5000IU/day (125µg) in
           overweight and obese adult participants for 8 weeks will significantly increase
           circulating concentrations of 25(OH)D or achieve optimal vitamin D status.

        2. Whether administering supplemental Vitamin D3 at a dose of 5000IU/day (125µg) in
           overweight and obese participants for 8 weeks will significantly improve the
           cardiometabolic parameters measured.

        3. To evaluate the relationship between these variables and 25(OH)D concentration. We
           hypothesise that there will be a significant increase in plasma 25(OH)D following 8
           weeks (56days) supplementation of oral vitamin D3 at a dose of 5000IU/day (125µg);
           Administering supplemental Vitamin D3 at a dose of 5000IU/day (125µg) in overweight and
           obese participants for 8 weeks will significantly improve the cardio metabolic
           parameters measured, and there will be a relationship between these variables and
           25(OH)D concentrations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a parallel randomised, double-blind placebo - controlled trial which will be
      conducted at the University of Chester, Chester, United Kingdom. Ethical permission has been
      obtained through the University of Chester Faculty Research Ethics Committee(855/13/AT/CSN).
      Participants, especially students/staff will be recruited from the University of Chester by
      email, posters/leaflets.

      Males were chosen for this study due to their higher risk of developing cardiometabolic
      diseases compared to premenopausal women. The participants will be randomised to receive
      either a vitamin D supplement (5000IU (125µg)/d) or placebo for eight weeks. A computer
      generated random number sequence will be used to assign participants to the intervention and
      placebo group. Eligibility will be based on 25(OH)D assessment made at a screening visit
      before the baseline visit, and participants with plasma 25(OH)D level ≤ 75nmol/l will be
      invited to participate in the study. To ensure compliance with the intervention, participants
      will be sent reminders about the intervention appointments by email or phone calls. The study
      will be performed according to the declaration of Helsinki. All participants will provide
      written consent. Study participants will be instructed to store the study supplements at room
      temperature. All unconsumed supplements will be returned and counted to assess compliance.

      MEASUREMENTS Dietary intake will be estimated at baseline and post intervention using a three
      day food diary and information about health conditions, medications and health related
      behaviors will be assessed by a pre-screen test questionnaire, physical activity will be
      evaluated as the average of the metabolic equivalent of task (MET-min/week) using the
      International Physical Activity Questionnaire. Participants will be assessed at baseline (day
      0), days 28 and 56. The plasma samples will be batch analyzed at the end of the trial.

      ANTHROPOMETRIC MEASUREMENTS Height (m2) will be measured without shoes at baseline, using a
      stadiometer to the nearest 0.1cm precision, Body weight (kg) will be measured without shoes
      at baseline through post intervention using a digital scale with participants wearing light
      indoor clothing, BMI will be calculated as weight in kilograms divided by the square of
      height in meters (kg/m2), and waist circumference at the iliac crest will be measured with a
      tape measure with the subject standing.

      PULSE WAVE VELOCITY AND BLOOD PRESSURE MEASUREMENTS Participants will be given a glass of
      water and allowed to rest for 5 minutes in a supine position and afterwards the pulse wave
      velocity meter (Arteriograph) cuff, for measuring arterial stiffness and blood pressure will
      be placed tightly round the dominant arm. Overall, three measurements will be performed but
      only the mean of two measurements will be taken.

      BIOCHEMICAL MEASUREMENTS A morning blood sample will be collected by venepuncture from the
      antecubital vein according to standard protocols, with participants in a sitting position
      after an overnight fast of at least 8 hours. Blood samples will be drawn into 10ml lithium
      heparin and EDTA tubes to avoid clotting after which they will be immediately transferred
      into an ice box and then centrifuged for 10 minutes at four degrees Celsius at 3500rpm.
      Afterwards the centrifuged plasma will be transferred into aliquots and stored at -80 degrees
      Celsius until analyzed.

      CONDUCT OF THE STUDY

      This study will require the participants to attend four clinic sessions on four separate
      days.

      Clinic 1(day 0): Participants are expected to complete a consent form and screening test
      questionnaire after which their weight, height and waist circumference are to be measured.
      Afterwards, approximately 0.5ml of blood will be collected by finger prick and put in a
      heparin tube to avoid clotting for vitamin D status screening to ascertain if participant is
      eligible to partake in the study. Eligible participants will be invited to take part in the
      study.

      Clinic 2 (week 0): Weight, height, waist circumference and blood pressure and body fat
      measurements will be performed. Afterwards, 25ml of blood will be collected to assess the
      cardiometabolic risk markers. Participants will then be randomised to receive either vitamin
      D or placebo (without the active ingredient) supplements for the intervention period.

      Clinic 3 (week 4): The procedure performed in clinic 2 will be repeated in this clinic.

      Clinic 4 (Week 8): The procedure performed in clinic 2 will be repeated. It is anticipated
      that the maximum length of each clinic visit will be 45mins.

      Participants will be expected to complete a three-day food diary and physical activity
      questionnaire at Clinic 2 and 4.

      SAMPLE SIZE ESTIMATION

      The estimated sample size will be 58 (29 per group), this sample size will allow for the
      detection of a treatment difference at 95% power, 0.97 effect size and 5% significance. The
      power calculation was based on a study by (Witham et al., 2012), and the primary outcome FMD
      (flow mediated dilation) a parameter of endothelial function from which an estimate of 29 per
      group was obtained, to allow for loss to follow up, sample size was increased to 37 (25%) per
      group (n= 74). Sample size estimation was conducted using G. Power version 3.1 software.

      DATA ANALYSIS

      Data will be checked for a normal distribution by using Shapiro-Wilk since n = 74, and a
      homogenous variance will be assessed by Levene's statistic. if assumptions of a normal
      distribution and homogenous variance have been met , a parametric approach will be adopted,if
      not, a non parametric approach will be adopted

      To assess the difference between the groups and the repeated measurement, i will perform a
      Mixed Model Anova,and any difference observed will be further analysed by a post- hoc, Tukey
      test.

      To check for a relationship between variables and 25(OH)D, Pearson's correlation will be
      conducted if assumptions were met or spearman's correlation if assumptions were not met .

      Descriptive statistics will be consulted to determine where findings differ from baseline
      values.The mean and standard deviation will provide information about changes that will
      occur.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulsewave Velocity</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Arterial Stiffness</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Aix Brachial</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Aix Aortic</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Arterial Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulse Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Systolic Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Diastolic Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>E-selectin</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>LDL Cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>HDL Cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Total Cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Triacylglycerols</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Isoprostanes</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Renin</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma CRP</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Insulin</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>HOMA-IR</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Insulin Resistance</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma 25(OH)D</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma PTH</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Osteocalcin</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Aldosterone</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Angiotensin II</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4 and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">49</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Disease</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Bone Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin D3 Supplement</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive a daily dose of 5000IU (125µg) vitamin D3 (which is half of the recommended safe tolerable upper intake level of vitamin D for healthy individuals) for eight weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive 100% lactose placebo daily for eight weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin D3</intervention_name>
    <description>5000IU (125mcg) vitamin D3 tablet daily over 8 weeks (56 days).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin D3 Supplement</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cholecalciferol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>100% Lactose tablet daily over 8 weeks (56 days).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Non-active ingredient</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy males aged 18-65 years,

          -  Those with a BMI ≥ 25kg/m2

          -  Those with plasma 25(OH)D concentrations &lt; 75nmol/l

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Those with gastrointestinal disease, cardiovascular disease, diabetes, osteoporosis,
             renal and hepatic disorders

          -  Those taking weight loss drugs

          -  Those taking cholesterol lowering drugs

          -  Those currently on a weight reduction programme

          -  Those with blood pressure ≥ 160/90 mm Hg

          -  Those taking vitamin D/calcium supplements
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sohail Mushtaq, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Chester</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Chester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chester</city>
        <zip>CH1 4BJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 4, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 4, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 9, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Vitamin D</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiovascular disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiometabolic</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bone Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin D</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ergocalciferols</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cholecalciferol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>I intend to report IPD including participant characteristics, laboratory measurements and details of randomisation in my thesis after writing is complete by February 2017. IPD will possibly be published in nutrition and medical journals by September 2017.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

