<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02356861</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D1768-P</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1I21RX001768-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02356861</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>LED Light Therapy to Improve Cognitive &amp; Psychosocial Function in TBI-PTSD Veterans</brief_title>
  <official_title>LED Light Therapy to Improve Cognitive/Psychosocial Function in TBI-PTSD Veterans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to learn if an experimental treatment can help thinking ability,
      and memory in Veterans with mild or moderate traumatic brain injury (mTBI), and
      post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD). The experimental treatment is called transcranial,
      light-emitting diode (LEDs) therapy,and uses groups of LEDs mounted inside a helmet. The
      helmet is worn on the head, and the LEDs shine painless light on the sides, middle and front
      of the head through the scalp. The participants receive a series of LED treatments which take
      place as outpatient visits at the VA Boston Healthcare System, Jamaica Plain Campus. The LEDs
      contain near-infrared diodes. The FDA considers the LED device used here, to be a
      non-significant risk device. The LEDs do not produce heat.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rationale:

      The rational for using near-infrared LEDs is two-fold: 1) These wavelengths have been shown
      to improve adenosine triphosphate (ATP) production, especially in hypoxic or compromised
      cells. 2) Recent studies in humans have also shown an increase in regional cerebral blood
      flow subjacent to where the near-infrared LEDs were placed on the scalp (Schiffer et al.,
      2009; Nawashiro et al., 2012).

      General Explanation of the Light-Emitting Diode (LED) Treatment Procedure:

      The LED treatments take place as outpatient visits at the VA Boston Healthcare System (VABHS)
      Jamaica Plain Campus (JP Campus), 150 South Huntington Ave., Boston, MA, 02130.

      The Transcranial LED treatment procedure is painless, non-invasive and no heat is generated.
      It involves placing a lightweight helmet on the head. The helmet contains some light-emitting
      diodes (LEDs). The LEDs are not visible (near-infrared wavelengths of light).

      During some of the LED treatments, the lights are turned on. During some of the LED
      treatments, the lights are not turned on. All participants who are part of this study will
      receive some LED treatments when the LED lights are turned on.

      The participant will not feel anything when the LED lights are on; it is a painless,
      noninvasive treatment procedure. There are small fans built into the LED helmet (to assist in
      circulating air inside the helmet and help with cooling). The participant will always hear
      the fans, during each LED treatment, whether the LEDs are on, or they are not on.

      There are 3 sequential parts to each LED treatment visit, while the LED helmet is on the
      head:

      Part 1: The LEDs in the center of the helmet are on for 6 and a half minutes; then turned
      off.

      Part 2: The LEDs in the right side of the helmet are on for 6 and a half minutes; then off.

      Part 3: The LEDs in the left side of the helmet are on for 6 and a half minutes; then off.

      The entire treatment with the LED helmet in place on the head is about 20 minutes, per
      treatment visit. There is no potential for eye damage, because LED light is not a laser
      light.

      The participant will remain in street clothes, and will be treated in a soft recliner chair.
      Each visit lasts about 35 to 45 minutes, allowing time for record keeping.

      No liquids or gel are used to hold the LEDs in place on the head. Each participant will be
      provided with his/her own clear plastic liner for the LED helmet. This clear plastic liner
      will be assigned to each participant, and only used by that participant. It will be kept in a
      locked filing cabinet in the treatment room, and discarded after the participant's completion
      of the study.

      There are 12 visits in each LED treatment series; and each participant will participate in
      two LED treatment series. Each LED treatment series lasts for 6 weeks. Each LED treatment
      visit is scheduled twice per week, with at least 48 hours between each visit.

      All appointments are scheduled ahead, for a specific day and time of day, at the convenience
      of the participant. If the participant needs to miss an appointment, that appointment will be
      re-scheduled. However, if the participant misses more than 1 appointment in a row, over a
      two-week period, he/she will be withdrawn from the study. This is because it is very
      important to treat at least two times per week for the 6 weeks, until all 12 LED treatments
      have been completed, in each of the two LED treatment series.

      The length of time for participation in the actual treatment portion of this study is 3
      months (two treatment periods of about 1.5 months, each). The total time of participation
      including pre- testing, and final follow-up testing at 2 months after the last LED treatment
      visit, is about 5 months.

      This study is sponsored by the Department of Veterans Affairs, Clinical Science Research and
      Development. There are no potential conflicts of interest associated with this research.

      Referral and Screening of Potential Participants:

      After self-referral to this study, each potential participant is contacted by telephone, and
      a description of the full study protocol is explained, including the time required, and
      reimbursement for time and effort. After the initial contact by telephone, an initial visit
      to the VABHS, JP campus may be scheduled with Dr. Knight, the PI, or someone on his staff. At
      this time, the entire study will be explained and questions answered. If the potential
      participant wishes to do so, he/she may sign the Informed Consent Form (ICF) at this first
      visit.

      After the ICF has been signed, an appointment is then scheduled for Neuropsychological
      Screening testing. These tests measure the ability to think and remember recent information.
      If results from the Neuropsychological Screening tests show that the potential participant is
      eligible for entry into this study, an additional appointment is scheduled where Additional
      Neuropsychological Testing is performed, and Additional Health Information is obtained.

      The Additional Neuropsychological Tests also measure the ability to think and remember recent
      information. These tests take place at the VABHS, JP. They are administered by Dr. Knight or
      his staff, and they require a two-hour visit.

      During the same two-hour visit, Additional Health Information (paper and pencil) is acquired
      in the following areas: 1) any pain experienced on a regular basis; 2) fatigue that is
      experienced on a regular basis; and 3) questions regarding health - for example, how often in
      the past 30 days symptoms may have been present from each of nine body systems: cardiac,
      pulmonary, dermatological, gastrointestinal, genitourinary, musculoskeletal, neurological,
      and psychological.

      The Additional Neuropsychological Tests (and the Additional Health Information) are each
      acquired four times during participation in the study:

      Time 1) Within 1 or 2 weeks before the 1st LED Treatment

      Time 2) Within 1 week after the 12th LED treatment in the First Series of LED Treatments

      Time 3) Within 1 week after the 12th LED treatment in the Second Series of LED Treatments

      Time 4) At 2 months after the 12th LED treatment in the Second Series of LED Treatments

      In summary, there are a total of 4 visits for the areas of &quot;Additional Neuropsychological
      Tests and Additional Health Information,&quot;

      Statistical Analyses and Power Statement:

      There will be one group of 50 participants recruited. Each will serve as his/her own control
      in this within-subject, repeated measurement partial crossover design.

      A score for each of 3 cognitive domains will be analyzed pre- and post- LED intervention:

        1. Attention/Executive Function: Digit Span Subtests (WAIS-IV; Wechsler, 2008);
           Trail-Making Test (Delis, Kaplan, Kramer, 2001); and Stroop Test (&quot;Color-Word&quot; test)
           (Delis, Kaplan, Kramer, 2001)

        2. Learning and Memory: California Verbal Learning Test-II (CVLT-II; Delis, Kramer, Kaplan,
           &amp; Ober, 2000)

        3. Psychomotor/Visual Spatial; Continuous Performance Test (Administered on computer;
           RVisual CPT, NES3) (Letz &amp; Baker, 1988; Rosvold et al., 1956); Rey Osterrieth Complex
           Figure Test (ROCF) (Knight &amp; Kaplan, 2004)

      Power Analysis:

      Power was computed under the following assumptions for ANOVA: a) alpha = .05 (1-tail); b) to
      establish clinical relevance, Cohen's large effect size (.25) was used. Power = .86 to detect
      a significant between-group difference in change from Baseline to end of Treatment for an
      interim analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroop Test (&quot;Color-Word&quot; test) (Delis, Kaplan &amp; Kramer, 2001)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Week after the last LED treatment in each treatment series</time_frame>
    <description>Attention/Executive Function</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Digit Span Subtests (WAIS-IV; Wechsler, 2008) D-KEF Trails (Delis, Kaplan &amp; Kramer, 2001)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Week after the last LED treatment in each treatment series</time_frame>
    <description>Additional Attention/Executive Function</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>California Verbal Learning Test-II (CVLT-II; Delis, Kramer, Kaplan, &amp; Ober, 2000)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Week after the last LED treatment in each treatment series</time_frame>
    <description>Learning and Memory</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Depression inventory (BDI; Beck, 2006)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Months after the last LED treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Mood [ Time Frame:</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>hort Form-36V Plus (Ware et al., 2000) Health Symptom Checklist (HSC).</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Months after the last LED treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Data for General Physical Health. The HSC is a comprehensive list of 34 frequently reported health and mental health symptoms originally adapted from Bartone et al., (1989). It asks how often in the past 30 days each of the health symptoms was experienced. Symptoms from nine body systems are assessed (cardiac, pulmonary, dermatological, gastrointestinal, genitourinary, musculoskeletal, neurological, and psychological).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain Injury (TBI)</condition>
  <condition>Post-traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Real, Active LED Treatment Series</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>These participants will first receive a series of 12, sham LED treatments, At 1 week post completion of the Sham LED treatment series, participants in this group receive a series of 12 real LED treatments from the helmet housing LEDs that deliver photons of light in the infrared range.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham LED Treatment Series</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>These participants will first receive an initial series of 12 sham LED treatments from the helmet containing the sham LEDs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Photomedex Sham Helmet with Red/Near-Infrared Light-Emitting Diodes (LEDs) that are not turned on</intervention_name>
    <description>The LED helmet from Photomedex, Montgomeryville, PA will be used.
18 LED pods are in the helmet. Each LED pod:
Pod size: 19 cm2 Power output: 692.5 mW Power density: 36.5 mW/cm2
20 NIR diodes, 830 nm and 4 red diodes, 633 nm.
1 J/cm2 = 30.4 sec</description>
    <arm_group_label>Real, Active LED Treatment Series</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sham LED Treatment Series</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Inclusion Criteria:

        The participants for this study will be recruited from flyers posted within the VA Boston
        Healthcare System and Veterans who contact the study after hearing about it from an outside
        referral source who knows that the study is actively recruiting participants. Participants
        must have both mild or moderate TBI and PTSD

          -  Males or Females; Ages 18 - 65 years old

          -  Must be physically able to travel to the VA Boston Healthcare System, Jamaica Plain,
             for Neuropsychological testing and transcranial LED treatments

          -  Must meet screening criteria from the Neuropsychological Screening Tests

          -  Must meet screening criteria fro a PTSD diagnosis

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not meeting criteria for post-traumatic stress disorder and for mild or moderate
             traumatic brain injury

          -  Had Gulf War Veterans' Illnesses (GWVI), but did not answer 'Yes' to the following
             questions: 1) Difficulty concentrating and/or 2) Difficulty remembering recent
             information, on the Symptom Questionnaire

          -  Less than age 18, or greater than age 60

          -  Presence of a neurodegenerative disease such as Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS),
             Parkinson's, Dementia

          -  Presence of a life-threatening disease such as cancer

          -  Presence of a severe mental disorder such as schizophrenia, or severe depression

          -  Physical limitations that would prevent traveling to the VA Boston Healthcare System,
             Jamaica Plain, for Neuropsychological testing and transcranial LED treatments

          -  Current substance abuse or in active treatment

          -  Did not meet screening criteria from the Neuropsychological Screening Tests
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffrey A Knight, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Boston Healthcare System Jamaica Plain Campus, Jamaica Plain, MA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jeffrey A Knight, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(857) 364-4133</phone>
    <email>jeffrey.knight@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Margaret Naeser, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(857) 364-4030</phone>
    <email>Margaret.Naeser@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Boston Healthcare System Jamaica Plain Campus, Jamaica Plain, MA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02130</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maria Higgins</last_name>
      <phone>857-364-4802</phone>
      <email>maria.higgins@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffrey A Knight, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 2, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 2, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 5, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>photobiomodulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Veterans</keyword>
  <keyword>brain-injury</keyword>
  <keyword>TBI</keyword>
  <keyword>PTSD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

