<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02351830</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Birch Validation Study</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02351830</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Validation of Birch Pollen in the EEU</brief_title>
  <official_title>Controlled Birch Pollen Challenge in the Environmental Exposure Unit (EEU); Clinical Validation and Biomarker Exploration</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Queen's University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Queen's University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The EEU has proven effective in multiple studies evaluating various aspects of seasonal
      allergic rhinitis. All previous EEU clinical trials have utilized ragweed or grass pollen as
      the allergen of choice for dispersal, due to the local population, but many emerging
      treatments for allergic rhinitis are allergen specific, thus it is desirable to expand the
      repertoire of pollen selection for use in the EEU. Ragweed, grass and birch pollen have
      differing appearances and sizes but essentially, both have characteristics which promote the
      ability to keep the pollen grains suspended and hence, the ability to maintain proper
      concentrations within the EEU. Preliminary validation studies conducted in the EEU, absent of
      human volunteers, have confirmed our ability to release, disperse and maintain birch pollen
      concentrations in the EEU using the existing technology.

      This study aims to validate the use of birch pollen on a clinical scale. By adding non-
      allergic participants into the EEU, the investigators hope to determine if non-allergic
      persons exhibit differences at baseline in their &quot;epigenetic biomarkers&quot; from those who have
      pre-existing and established allergic airways inflammation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Environmental Exposure Unit (EEU) is a controlled allergen challenge model of allergic
      rhinitis ('hayfever') that has been used extensively to study various anti-allergic
      therapies. The EEU is a unique, internationally recognized research facility that allows for
      the exposure of groups of as few as 5 to as many as 150 volunteers simultaneously to ambient
      levels of airborne allergens such as ragweed pollen and provides a unique study environment
      ideally suited to evaluate efficacy and onset of action of various anti-allergic medications.
      This specialized facility, located within Kingston General Hospital, allows for the tight
      regulation of environmental variables such as air quality, temperature, humidity and CO2
      levels as well as the precise maintenance of allergen concentration within this specialized
      room. Thus the EEU provides a closed environment in which participants are exposed to a
      predetermined, controlled, constant level of airborne pollen. All previous studies have used
      either ragweed or grass pollen, and the investigators have not clinically validated the use
      of birch pollen in the EEU. This study will confirm that the birch pollen circulated in the
      EEU can generate allergic rhinitis symptoms similar to those seen in the 'real world', and
      will also provide an opportunity to collect blood from participants before and after allergen
      challenge in order to better understand allergic inflammation, to hopefully someday identify
      novel therapies in allergic disease.

      This study will consist of a Screening Visit and one pollen exposure visit. The duration of
      each participant's participation in the study from Screening to End of Study (EOS) will be
      approximately 3 weeks. The study population will consist of healthy, ambulatory male and
      female volunteers, 18-65 years of age with either a history of seasonal allergic rhinitis or
      a history of no allergic reactions. Approximately 55-75 participants will be screened to
      ensure 50 eligible participants are enrolled into the study (40 allergic, 10 non-allergic).

      All participants will give written informed consent prior to any study procedures being
      performed. Participants who meet all inclusion/exclusion criteria during the screening
      process will be asked to return to the EEU for their pollen exposure visit. At the Screening
      visit participants will provide a full medical history and undergo a physical examination.
      They will have their height/weight and vitals measured and skin testing will be performed to
      confirm allergic response to a panel of common aeroallergens (or lack of response for the
      non-allergic individuals). Women of child bearing potential will undergo a urine pregnancy
      test to rule out pregnancy. Eligible participants will be asked to return to the research
      site for one 4 hour exposure to birch pollen in the Environmental Exposure Unit (EEU).
      Peripheral blood samples will be collected before and after pollen exposure for measurement
      of potential biomarkers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Total Nasal Symptom Score from Baseline to each time point.</measure>
    <time_frame>Second and Final Visit (4 hour pollen exposure)</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will assess their symptoms every 30 minutes during the 4-hour pollen exposure session and the sum of the 4 nasal symptoms (runny nose, stuffy nose, sneezing and itchy nose) which create the Total Nasal Symptom Score (TNSS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of people achieving a TNSS of 6 or greater</measure>
    <time_frame>Second and Final Visit (4 hour pollen exposure)</time_frame>
    <description>The data will be evaluated to see how many participants achieved a TNSS of 6 or greater (out of a possible 12) at the second hour of pollen exposure. This is typically the time frame for qualification for randomization in a clinical trial.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of people achieving a TRSS of 10 or greater</measure>
    <time_frame>Second and Final Visit (4 hour pollen exposure)</time_frame>
    <description>The data will be evaluated to see how many participants achieved a TRSS of 10 or greater (out of a possible 24) during the second hour of pollen exposure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Total Rhinoconjunctivitis Symptom Score from Baseline to each time point.</measure>
    <time_frame>Second and Final Visit (4 hour pollen exposure)</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will assess their symptoms every 30 minutes during the 4-hour pollen exposure session and the sum of all of their symptoms (nasal symptoms listed above as well as itchy eyes, watery/tearing eyes, red burning eyes and itching of the ears/palate/throat) which create the Total Rhinoconjunctivitis Symptom Score (TRSS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Peak Nasal Expiratory Flow (PNIF) from baseline at each time point.</measure>
    <time_frame>Second and Final Visit (4 hour pollen exposure)</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will measure their nasal blockage using a Peak Nasal Inspiratory Flow meter every 30 minutes at the same time that they measure the rest of their symptoms. As the participant's nose become more congested this value should decrease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">59</enrollment>
  <condition>Allergic Rhinitis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Birch Pollen</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be exposed to birch pollen to activate their allergy symptoms therefore validating the unit.</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nasal Brushing</intervention_name>
    <description>To assess allergic biomarkers participants will provide a nasal sample which will be collected using a cytobrush. This procedure will be performed twice; once at screening and once following pollen exposure in the EEU.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  minimum 2 year document history of rhinoconjunctivitis during typical tree pollen
             season (mid March to early May) OR completely non-atopic (allergic) to all
             environmental allergens.

          -  positive skin test to birch allergen OR negative skin test to a panel of allergens at
             screening.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  participants with asthma.

          -  participant is pregnant, lactating or actively trying to conceive.

          -  participant is currently receiving allergen specific immunotherapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anne K Ellis, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Queen's University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kingston General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kingston</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K7L 2V7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 27, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 29, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 30, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 20, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 20, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 21, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Queen's University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Anne Ellis</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chair, Division of Allergy &amp; Immunology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis, Allergic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

