<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02353832</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU 092013-013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02353832</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Stereotactic Ablative Radiotherapy (SABR) for Low Risk Prostate Cancer With Injectable Rectal Spacer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of Stereotactic Ablative Radiotherapy (SABR) for Low Risk Prostate Cancer With Injectable Rectal Spacer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose is to determine if use of rectal spacers are effective at improving protection of
      rectum from high dose radiation, using rate of rectal ulceration as a surrogate measure of
      acute effects. It is also to determine whether it provides sufficient dosimetric benefits to
      warrant further clinical investigation in future SABR (Stereotactic Ablative Body Radiation)
      related clinical studies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A phase II study to assess safety and efficacy of the spacer injection process, ability of
      the spacer to effectively provide the space necessary to reduce acute events in the rectum,
      and also meet the SABR based rectal constraints, and to monitor stability of this process
      during SABR. Unlike IMRT, which uses smaller dose/fraction, when using such high
      dose/fraction, even a few mm of shift in spacer positioning may impact the dose that the
      rectum receives, and therefore, a rigorous study of stability of material during the SABR
      treatments will need to be determined. If there is some shift, by doing this study, we may be
      able to determine the margin of error that will be necessary in considering rectal organ
      dosimetry, based on the possible shift in positiong that may occur with the spacer over time.

      As the SABR therapy is strictly local, we will select for patients with prostate cancer
      locally confined to the prostate gland. As such, we will select eligibility criteria of low
      risk patients to minimize risk of extraprostatic spread, seminal vesicle invasion, and nodal
      spread. Hormonal therapy may also be used to shrink prostates that are massively enlarged as
      this may also help further reduce length of rectum that will be irradiated. As the primary
      toxicity will likely be mucosal damage, we will avoid enrolling patients with pre-existing
      mucosal dysfunction (including those with previous radiation, TURP, very large prostate
      glands, inflammatory bowel disease) and immunosuppressed individuals based on our phase I
      experience[13]. In this way, patients will be uniformly selected in a fashion that would
      identify patients likely to receive benefit from the therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 6, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 5, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute periprostatic rectal ulcer events</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>To reduce acute periprostatic rectal ulcer events from 90%+ to &lt;=20% (particularly in the anterior rectum)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Spacer related acute toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess for spacer related acute toxicity. Spacer related toxicity could be related to the procedure itself (bleeding, infection, pain), or secondary effects of spacer (erectile dysfunction, persistent pain and discomfort).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent rectal circumference</measure>
    <time_frame>one month</time_frame>
    <description>Determine spacer's ability to decrease percent rectal circumference (PRC) receiving 24 and 39 Gy by at least 50%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Spacer stability by dimensions</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Determine spacer's stability during course of therapy and to ensure that it is stable enough to reliably use for high dose SABR treatments (using cone beam CTs done during each treatments to measure spacer dimensions).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of creation of &gt;= 7.5 mm space</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess for spacer related acute toxicity. Spacer related toxicity could be related to the procedure itself (bleeding, infection, pain), or secondary effects of spacer (erectile dysfunction, persistent pain and discomfort).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Injectable Rectal Spacer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Injectable Rectal Spacer (SpaceOAR, Duraseal or equivalent)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Injectable Rectal Spacer (SpaceOAR, Duraseal or equivalent)</intervention_name>
    <description>Injectable Rectal Spacer (SpaceOAR, Duraseal or equivalent PEG based product</description>
    <arm_group_label>Injectable Rectal Spacer</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients must be willing and capable to provide informed consent to participate in
             the protocol.

          -  Eligible patients must have appropriate staging studies identifying them as AJCC stage
             T1 (a, b, or c) or T2a or T2b adenocarcinoma of the prostate gland. The patient should
             not have direct evidence of regional or distant metastases after appropriate staging
             studies. Histologic confirmation of cancer will be required by biopsy performed within
             180 days of registration.

          -  The patient's Zubrod performance status must be 0-2.

          -  The Gleason score should be less than or equal to 6 or 3+4 if &lt; 50% of a 12 core
             biopsy was involved.

          -  The serum PSA should be less than or equal to 10 ng/ml.

          -  Study entry PSA must not be obtained during the following time frames: 10 day period
             following prostate biopsy; following initiation of ADT; within 30 days after
             discontinuation of finasteride; or within 90 days after discontinuation of
             dutasteride.

          -  Age ≥ 18 years.

          -  Patients may have used prior hormonal therapy, but it should be limited to no more
             than 9 months of therapy prior to enrollment.

          -  The ultrasound, or CT based volume estimation of the patient's prostate gland should
             be ≤ 60 grams.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who have had previous pelvic radiotherapy or have had chemotherapy or surgery
             for prostate cancer.

          -  Subjects who have plans to receive other concomitant or post treatment adjuvant
             antineoplastic therapy while on this protocol including surgery, cryotherapy,
             conventionally fractionated radiotherapy, hormonal therapy, or chemotherapy given as
             part of the treatment of prostate cancer.

          -  Subjects who have undergone previous transurethral resection of the prostate (TURP) or
             cryotherapy to the prostate. Subjects who have significant urinary obstructive
             symptoms; AUA score must be ≤15 (alpha blockers allowed).

          -  Subjects who have a history of significant psychiatric illness.

          -  Men of reproductive potential who do not agree that they or their partner will use an
             effective contraceptive method such as condom/diaphragm and spermacidal foam,
             intrauterine device (IUD), or prescription birth control pills.

          -  Prior invasive malignancy (except non-melanomatous skin cancer) unless disease free
             for a minimum of 3 years (e.g., carcinoma in situ of the breast, oral cavity, or
             cervix are all permissible).

          -  Severe, active co-morbidity, defined as follows:

               -  Unstable angina and/or congestive heart failure requiring hospitalization within
                  the last 6 months.

               -  Transmural myocardial infarction within the last 6 months.

               -  Acute bacterial or fungal infection requiring intravenous antibiotics at the time
                  of registration.

               -  Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease exacerbation or other respiratory illness
                  requiring hospitalization or precluding study therapy within 30 days before
                  registration.

               -  Hepatic insufficiency resulting in clinical jaundice and/or coagulation defects;
                  note, however, that laboratory tests for liver function and coagulation
                  parameters are not required for entry into this protocol.

               -  Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS) based upon current CDC definition;
                  note, however, that HIV testing is not required for entry into this protocol. The
                  need to exclude patients with AIDS from this protocol is necessary because the
                  treatments involved in this protocol may be significantly immunosuppressive.
                  Protocol-specific requirements may also exclude immuno-compromised patients.

               -  Patients with history of inflammatory colitis (including Crohn's Disease and
                  Ulcerative colitis) are not eligible.

          -  Subjects with a known allergy to polyethylene glycol hydrogel (spacer material) or
             contraindication to spacer products (Duraseal or SpaceOAR).

          -  Subjects with evidence of extraprostatic extension (T3a) or seminal vesicle
             involvement (T3b) on clinical evaluation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Folkert, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT Southwestern Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT Southwestern Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 16, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 28, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 3, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

