<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02357030</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>K-PAX-002-2</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CDMRP- GW130047</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02357030</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Methylphenidate Plus GWI-Nutrient Formula as a Treatment for Patients With Gulf War Illness</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase IIa Open Label Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, and Efficacy of KPAX 002 (Methylphenidate Hydrochloride + K-PAX Synergy) as a Treatment for Gulf War Illness in Patients Meeting the Kansas Case Definition</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>K-PAX Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>VA Palo Alto Health Care System</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>K-PAX Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Gulf War Synergy Trial will evaluate the safety and efficacy of a currently available
      medication, methylphenidate (Ritalin®), combined with a GWI Nutrient Formula (K-PAX Synergy)
      to treat Gulf War Illness (GWI).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This trial will evaluate the safety and efficacy of a currently available medication,
      methylphenidate (Ritalin®), combined with a mitochondrial support nutrient formula (K-PAX
      Synergy) to treat Gulf War Illness (GWI).

      The nutrient formula to be used in this trial is a broad-spectrum micronutrient supplement.
      This nutrient formula provides GWI patients with vitamins, minerals, and other cofactors
      (amino acids, antioxidants, and mitochondrial cofactors) to complement the low-dose Central
      Nervous System (CNS) stimulant (methylphenidate). The low-dose CNS stimulant provides the
      necessary catalyst to augment the metabolism of cellular fuel and the production of cellular
      energy.Therapeutic dosages of micronutrients are provided to support the functioning of the
      nervous, endocrine, and immune systems to a level at which a lower than customary dosage of
      methylphenidate can produce positive clinical effects on GWI symptoms and also be well
      tolerated without further depleting or degrading these systems.

      The dose of methylphenidate (Ritalin®) being tested in this study is relatively low (5-10mg
      twice daily). This drug has been in clinical use for over 50 years for the treatment of
      Narcolepsy and Attention Deficit Disorder and has a well-described safety profile when used
      as recommended. GWI and Chronic Fatigue Syndrome (CFS) share a high degree of symptom
      overlap. They have both been linked to mitochondrial dysfunction. Methylphenidate alone has
      been studied as a treatment for CFS in the past and has been shown to produce mild benefits
      and be well-tolerated. When provided as innovative therapy, methylphenidate plus this CFS
      Nutrient Formula has produced substantial improvements in CFS symptoms in a limited number of
      patients, and demonstrated excellent tolerability.

      Use of low dose methylphenidate coadministered with a mitochondria support nutrient formula
      has not been previously evaluated in a controlled clinical study. The risk to patients using
      this combination is believed to be low, especially in the context of a well-controlled
      clinical study. Furthermore, this combination is not expected to increase the incidence or
      severity of adverse events associated with methylphenidate.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in patient reported Checklist Individual Strength (CIS) total score</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients with 20% or greater improvement in the CIS total score</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration Disturbances Subscore on the CIS</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration Disturbances Score by Visual Analog Scale (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fatigue Score by Visual Analog Scale (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Score by Visual Analog Scale (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep Score by Visual Analog Scale (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mitochondrial Function Assays</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>GWI Symptoms Assessment Tool (SAT) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events to Assess Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Gulf War Illness</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Methyl-P plus GWI Nutrient Formula</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Methylphenidate hydrochloride plus a GWI Nutrient Formula (K-PAX Synergy), both taken twice daily.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methyl-P plus GWI Nutrient Formula</intervention_name>
    <description>Week 1:
One tablet of Methyl-P (5mg) twice daily
Four tablets of GWI Nutrient Formula twice daily
Week 2 to Week 12 :
Two tablets of Methyl-P (10mg) twice daily
Four tablets of GWI Nutrient Formula twice daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Methyl-P plus GWI Nutrient Formula</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>KPAX 002</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        1. Male and female patients between the ages of 18 and 64, inclusive at the time of
             informed consent

          2. Patients who currently meet the Kansas Case Definition for GWI

          3. Patients who are otherwise in good health based on medical history and screening
             evaluation as determined by Investigator (see below for specific exclusion criteria)

          4. Willingness to not take any multivitamin, nutritional or herbal supplements other than
             the study treatment during the course of the trial; at least a one week washout of
             current nutritional supplements will be required between the screening and baseline
             visits. Nutritional supplements that are exempted from this requirement are limited to
             the following (other exemptions require a waiver by the Medical Monitor):

               1. Probiotic supplements (L. acidophilus, Bifidobacterium, etc.)

               2. Fiber supplements

               3. Fish oil supplements

               4. Digestive enzymes

               5. Melatonin &lt; 10mg per day

               6. Calcium &lt; 600mg per day

               7. Magnesium &lt; 400mg per day

               8. Vitamin D &lt; 400 i.u. per day

          5. Willingness to not consume any caffeine-containing supplements during the study period
             (coffee, tea and chocolate are exempt). These supplements include but are not limited
             to the following:

               1. Red Bull®

               2. Monster®

               3. Rockstar®

               4. 5-hour® energy shots

          6. Willingness to not consume any prescription stimulants (i.e. Provigil®, Nuvigil®,
             Adderall®, Ritalin®, amphetamines) during the study period.

          7. Willingness to not consume any pseudoephedrine-containing products during the study
             period.

          8. Willingness of females to practice effective contraception.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnancy or lactation

          2. Active substance or alcohol abuse and/or a history of prescription stimulant abuse

          3. Hospitalization within the past five years for any of the following:

               1. Active substance or alcohol abuse and/or a history of prescription stimulant
                  abuse

               2. Major Depressive Disorder (MDD)

               3. Post Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD)

          4. Previous or current diagnosis of schizophrenia or bipolar disorder

          5. Currently taking any prescription medication to treat anxiety on a daily basis

          6. Use of any of the below medications more than 3 times per week within the past 3
             months:

               1. MAO inhibitors

               2. Anti-psychotic medications

               3. Prescription stimulants (i.e. Provigil®, Nuvigil®, Adderall®, Ritalin®, or any
                  other amphetamines)

               4. Coumarin anticoagulants (Coumadin®)

          7. Daily concurrent use of more than one antidepressant medication except if one of the
             two antidepressant medications are one of the following (unless specifically granted a
             waiver by the Medical Monitor):

               1. Amitriptyline ≤ 100 qhs

               2. Trazodone ≤ 100 qhs

               3. Doxepin ≤ 50 qhs

          8. Active medical conditions including:

               1. Glaucoma

               2. Diabetes mellitus

               3. Current stomach or duodenal ulcer

               4. Uncontrolled hypertension (blood pressure at screening of systolic &gt;160 or
                  diastolic &gt;90)

               5. Heart disease (including a history of cardiac arrhythmia, cardiac ischemia,
                  syndrome of Torsade de Pointes, myocardial infarction or cerebrovascular event)

               6. Motor tics or a diagnosis or family history of Tourette's syndrome

               7. Previous history of seizures

               8. A diagnosis of any of the following conditions:

                    -  Cancer (receiving systemic treatment either currently or within the past 12
                       months)

                    -  Chronic Renal Disease

                    -  Chronic Liver Disease

                    -  HIV Infection

                    -  Chronic Hepatitis B or C

                    -  Systemic Lupus Erythematosus

                    -  Multiple Sclerosis

                    -  Rheumatoid Arthritis

                    -  Parkinson's Disease

                    -  Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS)

                    -  Any chronic infectious disease lasting six months or longer

          9. Clinically significant laboratory test values as determined by the Medical Monitor

         10. Clinically significant ECG abnormalities as determined by the Medical Monitor

         11. The taking of another investigational treatment either currently or within 30 days of
             the screening visit

         12. Compliance criteria: A subject will not be eligible if he/she, in the opinion of the
             Investigator, will be unable to comply with any aspect of this study protocol,
             including the visit schedule.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jon D. Kaiser, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>K-PAX Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Holodniy, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Palo Alto Health Care System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jessica Lopez</last_name>
    <phone>(650) 493-5000</phone>
    <phone_ext>62219</phone_ext>
    <email>jessica.lopez@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Danya Adolphs</last_name>
    <phone>(415) 381-7599</phone>
    <email>d.adolphs@kpaxpharm.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Veterans Administration Palo Alto Health Care System (VAPAHCS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jon D. Kaiser, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Holodniy, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 25, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 2, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 6, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 13, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 13, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 15, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gulf War Illness</keyword>
  <keyword>nutrients</keyword>
  <keyword>methylphenidate</keyword>
  <keyword>mitochondria</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methylphenidate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

