<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02355912</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU00101767</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02355912</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Adaptive Recalibration of Prosthetic Leg Neural Control System</brief_title>
  <official_title>Adaptive Recalibration of Prosthetic Leg Neural Control System</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shirley Ryan AbilityLab</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shirley Ryan AbilityLab</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is for transfemoral amputees to walk with an experimental robotic
      prosthesis. Electric signals will be measured from their muscles and used to help control an
      artificial leg. The investigators will record from sensors placed on a prosthesis and
      electric signals measured from muscles in the participants leg to see if the investigators
      can develop better computer programs to help predict subject actions and prostheses function.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators propose to use a powered knee-ankle prosthesis that is not yet commercially
      available. The hierarchical control framework the investigators are developing will be
      equally applicable to any prosthetic leg that needs to be transitioned between ambulation
      modes, including microprocessor-controlled passive devices.

      The overall objective is to develop and evaluate an adaptive framework for controlling lower
      limb prostheses that compensates for changes in EMG signals. When a participant walks on a
      lower limb prosthesis, the output of the high-level controller (or ambulation mode predictor)
      directly influences patterns generated by the participant. After the participant has
      completed the subsequent stride, a gait pattern estimator (GPE), will provide a label of what
      the participant actually did. This may differ from the ambulation mode predictor output if
      there was a misclassification. The label will then be used to update the ambulation mode
      predictor algorithm such that future steps are predicted with higher accuracies. Finally, the
      resulting system will be transferred to an embedded system and tested in real-time with
      transfemoral amputees and compared to a non-adaptive system.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Decreased error rates for pattern recognition system used to predict ambulation modes</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at approximately 2 months and 6 months after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Pattern recognition algorithms have been used to allow seamless and automatic transitioning between ambulation modes. Classification errors result in the prosthesis predicting the wrong ambulation mode. A decrease in errors results in improved mode prediction by the prosthesis. EMG from the participant and mechanical sensor data from the prosthesis are processed with the use of a phase-based-dependent pattern recognition classification method. The data collection will yield three groups of 10 real-time trials. The investigators primary analysis will be a repeated measures ANOVA with a planned contrast between the groups. The investigators will also complete a secondary analysis using the data collected while the participants ambulated outside of the laboratory. The total number of misclassifications will be computed. This will allow the investigator to evaluate the rate at which the overall classification system adapted.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Amputation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Evaluate a real-time adaptive neural control system</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The prosthesis will be tuned, for each subject: level-ground walking, walking up and down slopes and walking up and down stairs. We anticipate that participants will visit the laboratory approximately 6-9 times over 2 months (2-3 visits for socket duplications and modifications, 2-3 visits for control system tuning, and an additional 2-3 visits for practice using the tuned system). By the end of these visits, the goal is to have a properly fitting socket and for the subjects to ambulate proficiently with the powered prosthesis. After tuning, the subjects will complete 20 ambulation circuits (level ground walking, walking up and down slopes, up and down stairs). This will provide training data for our pattern recognition control systems.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Powered knee and ankle prosthesis</intervention_name>
    <description>A powered knee and ankle prosthesis developed by Vanderbilt University.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Evaluate a real-time adaptive neural control system</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Amputee Subjects

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Lower Limb Amputees

          -  K2/K3/K4 ambulators

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Over 250lbs body weight

          -  Inactive, physically unfit

          -  cognitive deficits or visual impairment that would impair their ability to give
             informed consent or to follow simple instructions during the experiments

          -  Pregnant women

          -  co-morbidity that interferes with the study (e.g. stroke, pace maker placement, severe
             ischemia cardiac disease, etc.)

        Able-bodied Subjects:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  no injury on either lower extremity

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  inactive, physically unfit

          -  over 250 lbs body weight

          -  cognitive deficits or visual impairment that would impair their ability to give
             informed consent or impair their ability to follow simple instructions during the
             experiments

          -  Pregnant women (status determined by self-reporting)

          -  co-morbidity that interferes with the study (e.g. stroke, pace maker placement, severe
             ischemia cardiac disease, etc.)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Levi Hargrove, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Shirley Ryan AbilityLab</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Levi Hargrove, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>312-238-2084</phone>
    <email>l-hargrove@northwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Suzanne Finucane, MS</last_name>
    <phone>312-238-0937</phone>
    <email>sfinucane@ric.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rehabilitation Institute of Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Suzanne Finucane, MS</last_name>
      <phone>312-238-0937</phone>
      <email>sfinucane@ric.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 16, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 30, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 4, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 11, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Shirley Ryan AbilityLab</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Levi Hargrove</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Neural Engineering for Prosthetics and Orthotics Laboratory</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Transfemoral</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

