<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02359448</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14/0382</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02359448</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Melatonin for Nocturia in Parkinson's Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Single-centre Open Label Exploratory Phase IIb Pilot Study of Exogenous Oral Melatonin for the Treatment of Nocturia in Adults With Parkinson's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University College, London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University College, London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an an open label clinical trial of sustained-release Melatonin 2mg once daily for 12
      weeks in patients with Parkinsons's Disease reporting nocturia, defined as getting up
      regularly at night &gt; twice to pass urine. The primary objective of this study is to evaluate
      the effects of exogenous melatonin on bother related to nocturia. Secondary objectives are to
      evaluate: 1) Mean night time urinary frequency 2)Volume of urine voided at night
      3)Incontinence and other lower urinary tract symptoms (LUTS) 3)Quality of sleep 4) Quality of
      life 5) Sleep disturbance of partners 6)Safety
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase IIb, open label single-site trial of sustained-release Melatonin 2mg in
      patients with PD, reporting nocturia, defined as getting up regularly at night &gt; twice to
      pass urine. The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the effects of exogenous
      melatonin on bother related to nocturia. Secondary objectives are to evaluate: 1) Mean night
      time urinary frequency 2)Volume of urine voided at night 3)Incontinence and other lower
      urinary tract symptoms (LUTS) 3)Quality of sleep 4) Quality of life 5) Sleep disturbance of
      partners 6)Safety.

      Patients will be asked to fill out questionnaires, diaries and to wear a wrist actiwatch for
      2 weeks prior to starting melatonin and during the last 2 weeks of the 6 weeks treatment. A
      research nurse will telephone patients weekly whilst the patient is on Melatonin to enquire
      about medication use and any adverse events.

      After taking consent, the investigator will take a history covering urinary symptoms, and
      causes for nocturia, e.g. medications. Participants will be examined and severity of PD
      assessed using Hoehn and Yahr staging and UPDRS (Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale).
      Height, weight and supine/standing blood pressure will be recorded.

      Urodynamics will be performed according to ICS Good Urodynamic Practice and will include
      uroflowmetry, bladder scan, filling cystometry and pressure flow study.

      This pilot study aims to evaluate any effect that melatonin may have on nocturia related
      bother in Parkinson's Disease. Chi square test will be used to analyse change in bother
      related to nocturia (primary outcome) and number of nocturia episodes and questionnaire
      scores (Secondary outcomes).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>April 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in bother related to nocturia as measured by a standardised validated questionnaire(ICIQ-N)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome of this study is improvement on bother related to nocturia, as measured by the International Consultation on Incontinence Questionnaire Nocturia Module (ICIQ-N).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in mean night time urinary frequency assessed from the frequency volume chart and a standardised validated questionnaire(ICIQ-N)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in the Nocturnal polyuria index, percentage of volume of urine voided at night, calculated from the frequency volume chart.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in overall lower urinary tract symptoms (LUTS), assessed by standardised validated questionnaires, ie. Urinary Symptom Profile</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement on sleep disturbances, assessed using a standardised validated questionnaire, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index, sleep diary and Actigraphy</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep disturbance in partners/careers assessed by sleep diary and Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Nocturia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Melatonin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be prescribed and dispensed from pharmacy sustained -release Melatonin (Circadin) 2mg. This will be taken every night for twelve weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Melatonin</intervention_name>
    <description>An open label clinical trial of sustained-release Melatonin 2mg once daily for 6 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Melatonin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Circadin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adults male and female(&gt; 18 years) with clinically diagnosed PD according to the Brain
             Bank Criteria

          2. Reporting nocturia to NMSQuest item 9 -&quot;Getting up regularly at night to pass urine&quot;
             and getting up to pass urine two or more times at night. Although the International
             Continence Society (ICS) defines nocturia as waking up at night one or more times to
             void, a recent population based study has shown that two voids or more is associated
             with bother and impaired health related quality of life.

          3. Able to provide informed written consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MOCA) score &lt; 26

          2. History suggestive of REM sleep behaviour disorder

          3. Congestive heart failure, liver failure or kidney failure as determined by medical
             history

          4. Uncontrolled diabetes, or significant microalbuminuria in patients with diabetes

          5. Using medications such as benzodiazepines and Z-drugs (e.g. Zaleplon, Zolpidem and
             Zopiclone)

          6. Presence of urinary tract infection as determined by the clinician

          7. Evidence for incomplete bladder emptying, i.e., post void residual urine of more than
             100 mL as determined by ultrasound (bladder scan)

          8. Presence of significantly enlarged prostate as determined by the clinician using the
             European Association of Urology (EAU) guidelines based on urodynamic findings

          9. Females of childbearing potential must be willing to use an effective method of
             contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) from the time
             consent is signed until 6 weeks after treatment discontinuation.

         10. Females of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test within 7 days
             prior to being registered for trial treatment.

         11. Females must not be breastfeeding.

         12. Allergies to excipients of IMP

         13. Smokers

         14. Patient with autoimmune disease

         15. Patients taking carbamazepine, rifampicin and cimetidine

         16. Patients with rare hereditary problems of galactose intolerance, the LAP lactose
             deficiency or galactose malabsorption

         17. Excessive alcohol consumption as defined by the investigator
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jalesh Panicker</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UCL</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Adedayo Akinyemi</last_name>
    <email>a.akinyemi@ucl.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Hospital for Neurology and Neurosurgery and UCL Institute of Neurology</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>WC1N 3BG</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 4, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 4, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 10, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 4, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 4, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 10, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nocturia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melatonin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

