<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02355132</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00007327</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL107647</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02355132</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessing a Medicaid Randomized Insurance Experiment Within Community Clinics</brief_title>
  <acronym>AMRIC</acronym>
  <official_title>Assessing a Medicaid Randomized Insurance Experiment Within Community Clinics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oregon Health and Science University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kaiser Foundation Hospitals, Center for Health Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ochin, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oregon Health and Science University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study examines the impact of a randomized insurance experiment on preventive services
      receipt and healthcare utilization in safety net patients using linked public insurance
      claims and safety net clinics' electronic health record (EHR) data.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In 2008, the Oregon Medicaid program used a &quot;lottery&quot; (Oregon Experiment) to allocate limited
      insurance resources to low income adults who did not categorically qualify for traditional
      Medicaid coverage. Thousands were randomly selected to apply for Medicaid; many others were
      not selected. This &quot;natural policy experiment&quot; is the first population-level randomization of
      insurance coverage since Rand's 1971-1982 experiment. We will use data from safety net
      clinics that share a common electronic health record (EHR) operated by OCHIN, a non-profit
      organization in Portland, Oregon. As one of the nation's largest linked community health
      center networks, the OCHIN EHR database records nearly all visits to safety net clinics in
      Oregon with one patient chart linked across &gt;100 community health centers. We will link
      Medicaid claims data and the OCHIN database to determine patients that had applied to
      participate in the Oregon Experiment, as well as to determine those that gained insurance via
      this experiment. We will test the hypothesis that public insurance coverage is associated
      with higher rates of receiving preventive care services and increased healthcare utilization
      among persons with a usual source of primary care. To that end, we will analyze preventive
      care and utilization patterns among the OCHIN clinic patients affected by Oregon's Medicaid
      Experiment. This study capitalizes on two unique opportunities: an EHR database linking &gt;100
      community health centers, and the quasi-experimental design of Oregon's randomized Medicaid
      experiment.

      The specific aims related to the Oregon Experiment are:

      1) To compare post-intervention rates of preventive services receipt among OCHIN patients
      randomized to the Oregon Experiment group (intervention group), compared to those not in the
      coverage group (comparison group); and 3) To compare post-intervention rates of ambulatory
      healthcare utilization among OCHIN patients randomized to the Oregon Experiment group
      (intervention group), compared to those not in the coverage group (comparison group).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Preventive service receipt</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months post Oregon Experiment selection (post-period)</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients with receipt of the following preventive services in the post-period (each outcome assessed individually by whether person met age, gender, and diagnosis criteria (if applicable): body mass index, blood pressure, smoking, pap test, mammography, colorectal cancer screening, chlamydia screening, lipid test, flu vaccination, pneumococcal vaccination, HbA1c test, glucose test) using ICD-9-CM diagnosis and procedure codes, CPT and HCPCS codes, LOINC codes, medication codes, relevant code groupings and codes specific to the OCHIN EHR.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ambulatory healthcare utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months post Oregon Experiment selection (post-period)</time_frame>
    <description>Number of visits in the post-period for the following services: total primary care office visits, total behavioral/mental health visits, labs, referrals, immunizations, imaging)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">308283</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Disease</condition>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Insurance Intervention Arm</arm_group_label>
    <description>Oregon OCHIN patients that put their names on the reservation list for the Oregon Experiment and were randomly chosen to apply for insurance coverage via the Oregon Experiment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <description>Oregon OCHIN patients that put their names on the reservation list for the Oregon Experiment and were not chosen to apply for insurance coverage via the Oregon Experiment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Insurance Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Random selection to apply for Medicaid coverage through Oregon Experiment drawings held between March and October 2008</description>
    <arm_group_label>Insurance Intervention Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adult individuals on the Oregon Experiment 'reservation list' (applied for the Oregon
        Experiment) linked to individual patients in an Oregon safety net clinic that is part of
        the OCHIN, Inc network using Link Plus software and demographic variables common to both
        datasets.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  must have applied for the Oregon Experiment in 2006

          -  must have been a patient in an Oregon safety net clinic that is part of the OCHIN, Inc
             network

          -  for preventive services outcomes only, matched patients had to have been at a clinic
             with an electronic health record system by 3/11/08

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  under 19 years of age

          -  over 64 years of age

          -  not alive at the end of the 36 month post-period

          -  unknown/missing gender
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer E DeVoe, MD, DPhil</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Oregon Health and Science University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Heather Angier, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Oregon Health &amp; Science Univerisity</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 30, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 30, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 4, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 18, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 18, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 19, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Oregon Health and Science University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jennifer E DeVoe, MD DPhil</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Medicaid</keyword>
  <keyword>public insurance</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiovascular disease</keyword>
  <keyword>prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>community health centers</keyword>
  <keyword>electronic health records</keyword>
  <keyword>cancer prevention</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

