<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03193710</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>WestChinaHospital</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03193710</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of General Anesthetics on Lymphocytes in Patients Undergoing Colorectal Cancer Resection and Mechanism Involved</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of the Effects of Total Intravenous Anesthesia and Inhalation Anesthesia on Lymphocytes in Patients Undergoing Colorectal Cancer Resection and the Mechanism Involved: a Single-center, Randomized, Prospective Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Guizhi Du</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>West China Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The body immunity is important to the development of tumor. The immune system is in charge of
      monitoring and cleaning tumor cells in circulation. Anesthesia may alter the immune response
      and affect the elimination of tumor cells. The purpose of the trial is to test whether
      inhalational anesthetic is relevant to tumor metastasis and recurrence of patients undergoing
      colorectal cancer resection through depression of lymphocytes-mediated immunity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      With the increasing number of patients diagnosed with colorectal cancer, the proportion of
      patients undergoing surgical resection with general anesthesia increased. However, the
      operation can lead tumor cells releasing into the blood or peritoneal implantation, and the
      impaired immune response can make patients susceptible to the development of tumor metastasis
      and recurrence which is the the main reason of death. It is well known that B lymphocytes and
      T lymphocytes are the main immune cells, and B lymphocytes by secreting antibodies are
      related to humoral immunity and T lymphocytes which play the most important role in antitumor
      are related to cell-mediated immunity. Surgery stress leads to metabolic and neuroendocrine
      changes causing significant depression of immunity. Although general anesthesia could reduce
      surgical stress, studies indicated general anesthetics including intravenous and inhalational
      agents both have variable effects on tumor cells growth by immuno-modulation and some
      cytokines. A number of studies have demonstrated deleterious effects on the function of
      lymphocytes associated with the administration of volatile inhalational anesthetic agents. It
      was suggested that the use of volatile inhalational agent may augment tumor cells growth by
      inhibiting the activity of lymphocytes, NK cells and dendritic cells which are important for
      recognizing, capturing and killing tumor cells, however, the alternative propofol has a
      converse (beneficial) effect by decreasing the plasma level of cytokines secreted by
      activated lymphocytes, macrophages and NK cells. The detailed mechanism of how volatile
      anesthetics affect the activity of antitumor cells remains unknown. Thus the investigators
      will conduct the clinical investigation to study the effect of volatile anesthetics on the
      immune response and metastasis in patients undergoing colorectal cancer resection, exploring
      molecular mechanism involved if inhalational anesthetics show an effect. The findings of this
      study would be valuable for anesthetic regimen guidance of colorectal cancer patients
      undergoing surgical resection in terms of long-term survival.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline lymphocytes within postoperative 5 years</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Blood will be drawn preoperatively ( at least 24 hours before surgery), prior to anesthesia induction, immediately postoperatively, 24 hours postoperatively, and at postoperative appointments for testing CD4+/CD8+, B lymphocytes, dendritic cells, natural killer cells</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cancer free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years or as available</time_frame>
    <description>Patients who remain alive without known colonal or rectal tumor recurrence</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cancer recurrence rate</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Patients who remain alive with known colonal or rectal tumor recurrence</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cancer metastasis rate</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Patients who remain alive with known colonal or rectal tumor metastasis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Re-operation</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Patients who have a surgery under general anesthesia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anesthesia scheme for re-operation</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Total intravenous anesthesia, inhalational anesthesia or combined anesthesia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiotherapy rate for any cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Patients have radiotherapy for any cancer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Chemotherapy rate for any cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Patients have chemotherapy for any cancer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating tumor cells</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Blood will be drawn preoperatively (at least 24 hours before surgery), prior to anesthesia induction, immediately postoperatively, 24 hours postoperatively, and at postoperative appointments for testing circulating tumor cells</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration of cytokines</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Blood will be drawn preoperatively (at least 24 hours before surgery), prior to anesthesia induction, immediately postoperatively, 24 hours postoperatively, and at postoperative appointments for testing IL, TNF-α, IFN-γ and GCSF</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Colorectal cancer antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Blood will be drawn preoperatively (at least 24 hours before surgery), prior to anesthesia induction, immediately postoperatively, 24 hours postoperatively, and at postoperative appointments for testing CEA, CA199, GP87 and TPA.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Re-operation during hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>From end of colorectal cancer resection surgery to discharge, up to one month</time_frame>
    <description>Patients receive a reoperation for any reason during hospitalization</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Days of hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>From end of colorectal cancer resection surgery to discharge, up to one month</time_frame>
    <description>The duration of patients stay in hospital</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">260</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer Metastatic</condition>
  <condition>Survival Rate</condition>
  <condition>General Anesthetics Toxicity</condition>
  <condition>Lymphocyte Destruction</condition>
  <condition>Molecular Mechanism of Pharmacological Action</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Total intravenous anesthesia group</arm_group_label>
    <description>The anesthesia of patients in the total intravenous anesthesia group will be maintained with propofol and remifentanil.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Inhalational anesthesia group</arm_group_label>
    <description>The anesthesia of patients in the inhalational anesthesia group will be maintained with sevoflurane and remifentanil.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Propofol</intervention_name>
    <description>Propofol will be used for anesthesia maintenance in the total intravenous anesthesia group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Total intravenous anesthesia group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Diprivan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sevoflurane</intervention_name>
    <description>Sevoflurane will be used for anesthesia maintenance in the inhalation anesthesia group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Inhalational anesthesia group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Abbvie</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Remifentanil</intervention_name>
    <description>Remifentanil will be used for analgesia in both groups.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Total intravenous anesthesia group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Inhalational anesthesia group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>YiChang HumanWell Pharmaceutical Co.，LTD. China</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood of the enrolled patients will be sampled at different time-points for examination of
      lymphocytes.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with colonal or rectal cancer undergoing cancer resection with general anesthesia
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All the patients diagnosed with colonal or rectal cancer

          -  Aged 18-65

          -  ASA I-III

          -  Assigned to receive resection surgery under general anesthesia, with an expected
             duration of 2 hours or more

          -  Agree to participate and give signed written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe organic heart, liver and kidney diseases

          -  Diabetes or hemopoietic disorders

          -  Allergy to general anesthetics

          -  Family historical malignant hyperthermia

          -  Cognition dysfunction

          -  End-stage cancer or with over 2 cancer metastasis, pathological results were benign
             tumor or TNM stage was over T1- 3N0 - 2M0

          -  Other primary malignant tumor

          -  Immune deficiency or dysfunction or autoimmune disease or long-term usage of
             corticoids or immunosuppressants

          -  Receiving general anesthesia within the last 3 months before the resection surgery

          -  Perioperative transfusion
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jin Liu, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Anesthesiology, West China Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Guizhi Du, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+8618980602213</phone>
    <email>du_guizhi@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jin Liu, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+86 18980601549</phone>
    <email>scujinliu@foxmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West China Hospital of Sichuan University, Department of Anesthesiology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chengdu</city>
        <state>Sichuan</state>
        <zip>610041</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Guizhi Du, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+86-189-8060-2213</phone>
      <email>du_guizhi@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Guizhi Du, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yan Qiu, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sofra M, Fei PC, Fabrizi L, Marcelli ME, Claroni C, Gallucci M, Ensoli F, Forastiere E. Immunomodulatory effects of total intravenous and balanced inhalation anesthesia in patients with bladder cancer undergoing elective radical cystectomy: preliminary results. J Exp Clin Cancer Res. 2013 Feb 3;32:6. doi: 10.1186/1756-9966-32-6.</citation>
    <PMID>23374147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Qiao Y, Feng H, Zhao T, Yan H, Zhang H, Zhao X. Postoperative cognitive dysfunction after inhalational anesthesia in elderly patients undergoing major surgery: the influence of anesthetic technique, cerebral injury and systemic inflammation. BMC Anesthesiol. 2015 Oct 23;15:154. doi: 10.1186/s12871-015-0130-9.</citation>
    <PMID>26497059</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Möller Petrun A, Kamenik M. Bispectral index-guided induction of general anaesthesia in patients undergoing major abdominal surgery using propofol or etomidate: a double-blind, randomized, clinical trial. Br J Anaesth. 2013 Mar;110(3):388-96. doi: 10.1093/bja/aes416. Epub 2012 Nov 19.</citation>
    <PMID>23166149</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jaura AI, Flood G, Gallagher HC, Buggy DJ. Differential effects of serum from patients administered distinct anaesthetic techniques on apoptosis in breast cancer cells in vitro: a pilot study. Br J Anaesth. 2014 Jul;113 Suppl 1:i63-7. doi: 10.1093/bja/aet581. Epub 2014 Jul 9.</citation>
    <PMID>25009197</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buckley A, McQuaid S, Johnson P, Buggy DJ. Effect of anaesthetic technique on the natural killer cell anti-tumour activity of serum from women undergoing breast cancer surgery: a pilot study. Br J Anaesth. 2014 Jul;113 Suppl 1:i56-62. doi: 10.1093/bja/aeu200. Epub 2014 Jul 9.</citation>
    <PMID>25009196</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wigmore TJ, Mohammed K, Jhanji S. Long-term Survival for Patients Undergoing Volatile versus IV Anesthesia for Cancer Surgery: A Retrospective Analysis. Anesthesiology. 2016 Jan;124(1):69-79. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0000000000000936.</citation>
    <PMID>26556730</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Woo JH, Baik HJ, Kim CH, Chung RK, Kim DY, Lee GY, Chun EH. Effect of Propofol and Desflurane on Immune Cell Populations in Breast Cancer Patients: A Randomized Trial. J Korean Med Sci. 2015 Oct;30(10):1503-8. doi: 10.3346/jkms.2015.30.10.1503. Epub 2015 Sep 12.</citation>
    <PMID>26425050</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bayliss DA, Barrett PQ. Emerging roles for two-pore-domain potassium channels and their potential therapeutic impact. Trends Pharmacol Sci. 2008 Nov;29(11):566-75. doi: 10.1016/j.tips.2008.07.013. Epub 2008 Sep 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18823665</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pei L, Tan G, Wang L, Guo W, Xiao B, Gao X, Wang L, Li H, Xu Z, Zhang X, Zhao J, Yi J, Huang Y. Comparison of combined general-epidural anesthesia with general anesthesia effects on survival and cancer recurrence: a meta-analysis of retrospective and prospective studies. PLoS One. 2014 Dec 30;9(12):e114667. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0114667. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25548913</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shi C, Thum C, Zhang Q, Tu W, Pelaz B, Parak WJ, Zhang Y, Schneider M. Inhibition of the cancer-associated TASK 3 channels by magnetically induced thermal release of Tetrandrine from a polymeric drug carrier. J Control Release. 2016 Sep 10;237:50-60. doi: 10.1016/j.jconrel.2016.06.044. Epub 2016 Jul 1.</citation>
    <PMID>27374629</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 12, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 17, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 21, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>West China Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Guizhi Du</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Intravenous anesthesia</keyword>
  <keyword>Inhalational anesthesia</keyword>
  <keyword>Colorectal cancer resection</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphocytes</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastasis</keyword>
  <keyword>Survival</keyword>
  <keyword>Molecular mechanism</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Propofol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Remifentanil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sevoflurane</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All the study outcomes</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

