<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03190382</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17-053</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03190382</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SHOWME-PAD (Peripheral Artery Disease)</brief_title>
  <official_title>SHOW-ME PAD (Peripheral Artery Disease)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Saint Luke's Health System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Saint Luke's Health System</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall goal of SHOWME-PAD is to make the existing evidence-base on treatment outcomes
      -focusing on health status outcomes that reflect the patients' perspective - more
      transparently available to patients and providers, such that more informed, evidence-based
      shared treatment decisions occur. INTEGRITY-PAD has the potential to radically reorganize
      care delivery to patients with PAD such that more value for the patient and society will be
      created.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Peripheral arterial disease (PAD) is a burdensome condition that affects 10% of the
      population and increases to 15-20% among those ≥70 years. In PAD, the underlying
      pathophysiologic process, atherosclerosis, presents itself as blockages in patients' leg
      arteries that prevent adequate blood flow and can result in burning calf (or buttock) pain
      while walking and that is relieved upon rest ('intermittent claudication'). In extreme cases,
      PAD can progress to critical limb ischemia, characterized by ulceration, gangrene, and
      threatened limb viability. Patients with PAD have significant atherosclerotic risk factors
      and impaired health status - thus creating 2 therapeutic goals, prevention of cardiovascular
      events and improved symptom control and quality of life. While the onset of PAD tends not to
      be as abrupt as for other cardiovascular conditions, such as stroke or myocardial infarction,
      leg symptoms can severely affect patients' health status (their symptoms, functional status,
      and quality of life). In addition, patients' risk of having a cardiovascular event is
      disproportionately high, as compared with other cardiovascular diseases. One-year
      cardiovascular event rates - including cardiovascular death, myocardial infarction, or
      stroke, or other hospitalizations for atherothrombotic events - are estimated to be over 21%
      in patients with PAD, as compared with 15% for coronary artery disease and stroke.9 Mortality
      rates are 15-30% 5 years after diagnosis. Part of these disproportionate event rates may be
      explained by under recognition and under treatment of PAD and its underlying atherosclerotic
      process. Finally, PAD not only impacts patients' individual lives and their families; it also
      has a tremendous impact on society at large. It is estimated that annual costs associated
      with vascular-related hospitalizations in PAD patients in the US exceeds $21 billion.

      The primary treatment goals for PAD are symptom relief, quality of life improvement, and
      cardiovascular risk reduction. Several treatment options are available for PAD, ranging from
      invasive revascularization procedures, including peripheral percutaneous intervention (PPI)
      and surgical revascularization to non-invasive options, including supervised and home-based
      exercise therapy, PAD-specific medications, and cardiovascular risk management. While there
      is no &quot;gold-standard&quot; treatment for PAD, less invasive options are recommended as a
      first-choice treatment. Despite these recommendations, invasive procedures are often first
      offered to patients, with no alternative options being discussed. In treatment scenarios with
      a lot of clinical equipoise (i.e. uncertainty about what treatment would be best) and a
      rapidly growing market for newly-introduced technologies, including medical devices for
      invasive PAD procedures (e.g. stents for endovascular treatment), with limited performance
      measurement and accountability criteria, there is a high risk of unwanted variation in
      treatment practices, misallocation of treatments, and unnecessary costs.

      Given this context, some of the current challenges in current PAD care include: 1) limited
      access to the evidence-base in routine clinical care for patients and providers; 2) the
      potential mismatch of PAD treatments to patient preferences and profiles; and 3) patients not
      being informed or engaged in medical decision making. These challenges may leave patients
      uninformed about treatment risks and benefits, increase the risk of misallocating treatments
      to patients, and may unnecessarily increase costs. A very promising strategy to overcome
      these challenges is the use of evidence-based, decision support tools. Importantly, it is
      currently unknown whether patient-centered PAD decision-tools can be designed to improve the
      alignment of patients' values with respect to their treatment choice and whether these tools
      can improve patients' knowledge and access to the evidence-base related to PAD treatment and
      outcomes. The critical next step, therefore, is to create such tools and pilot their
      implementation as a foundation for broader integration of precision medicine and shared
      decision-making in clinical care.

      Shared decision-making takes into account the latest evidence about all available treatment
      options and their outcomes, as well as patients' values and preferences with regards to
      treatment and potential outcomes that matter to them. Shared decision-making is extremely
      useful in treatment situations where there is clinical equipoise and where the choice of
      treatment should be greatly influenced by patients' preferences. Decision aids that
      facilitate this process of shared decision-making, have been consistently associated with
      better knowledge about the disease and treatments, less decisional conflict, and potential
      cost savings due to less invasive options being preferred by patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 24, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Decisional Conflict</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome of this study will be decisional conflict as measured by the Decisional Conflict Scale.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Peripheral Artery Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Received Decision Tool</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Peripheral artery disease patients that received the decision support tool.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Decision Support Tool</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients enrolled in the study will receive the decision tool prior to the first PAD clinic visit and the medical decision making conversation with the provider.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Received Decision Tool</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All race and ethnicity categories, English speaking, men and women

          -  Age ≥18 years

          -  New onset complaints of PAD symptoms or exacerbation of previous PAD symptoms

          -  The diagnostic enrollment criterion includes a positive result for one of the
             following

          -  Doppler resting ankle-brachial index (ABI)≤0.90 or a significant drop in post exercise
             ankle pressure of ≥20 mmHg.

          -  Duplex

          -  CTA

          -  MRA

          -  TCOM

          -  Angiogram

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-compressible ankle-brachial index (ABI ≥ 1.30)

          -  A lower limb revascularization procedure in the ipsilateral leg (same leg) where the
             patient is currently having symptoms in the past year (atherectomy, endarterectomy,
             bypass surgery, angioplasty)

          -  Peripheral intervention that occurs before the baseline interview

          -  Current episode of critical limb ischemia (ischemic rest pain, ulceration or gangrene)
             (Fontaine III, IV or Rutherford IV-VI)

          -  Patients with dementia

          -  Patients who are prisoners

          -  Patients who are unable to provide informed consent

          -  Non-English speaking patients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kim G Smolderen, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Missouri Kansas City; Saint Luke's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nancy M Stone, MEd</last_name>
    <phone>816-932-5367</phone>
    <email>nanstone@saint-lukes.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Connor AM. Validation of a decisional conflict scale. Med Decis Making. 1995 Jan-Mar;15(1):25-30.</citation>
    <PMID>7898294</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Graaff JC, Ubbink DT, Kools EI, Chamuleau SA, Jacobs MJ. The impact of peripheral and coronary artery disease on health-related quality of life. Ann Vasc Surg. 2002 Jul;16(4):495-500. Epub 2002 Jun 27.</citation>
    <PMID>12085126</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rooke TW, Hirsch AT, Misra S, Sidawy AN, Beckman JA, Findeiss LK, Golzarian J, Gornik HL, Halperin JL, Jaff MR, Moneta GL, Olin JW, Stanley JC, White CJ, White JV, Zierler RE; Society for Cardiovascular Angiography and Interventions; Society of Interventional Radiology; Society for Vascular Medicine; Society for Vascular Surgery. 2011 ACCF/AHA Focused Update of the Guideline for the Management of Patients With Peripheral Artery Disease (updating the 2005 guideline): a report of the American College of Cardiology Foundation/American Heart Association Task Force on Practice Guidelines. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2011 Nov 1;58(19):2020-45. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2011.08.023. Epub 2011 Oct 6.</citation>
    <PMID>21963765</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 14, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 14, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 16, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 16, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Arterial Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

