<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03199352</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>280-17-FB</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03199352</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hand-sewn and Linear-stapled Roux-en-Y Gastric Bypass: Outcomes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of Hand-sewn and Linear-stapled Roux-en-Y Gastric Bypass: Outcomes in Stricture, Ulceration, and Gastritis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Nebraska</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Nebraska</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The technique of laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass (RYGB) has evolved significantly over
      the past few decades to minimize complication risks such as strictures. Three different
      anastomotic techniques are currently widely used hand-sewn (HS), linear-stapled (LS) and
      circular stapled (CS). Studies are contradictory as to the best technique to avoid
      complications. Many studies have focused on the stricture and infection rates of these
      procedures, and minimized the examination of ulceration, gastritis, and anastomotic leak. The
      purpose of this study is to prospectively examine how the use of linear-stapled and hand-sewn
      anastomotic techniques affect complication rates of marginal ulceration, gastritis, leak and
      stricture in patients who undergo RYGB. The goal of this study is to compare the long-term
      complication rates between hand-sewn robotic RYGB and linear-stapled laparoscopic RYGB.
      Eligible patients are men and women age 19-65 who are to undergo RYGB, have a BMI between
      35-45, and RYGB is the primary procedure. The main outcomes to be measured are complications
      in marginal ulceration, gastritis, leak, and stricture rate at 2 and 6 weeks, and 3, 6, 9,
      12, and 24 months postoperatively.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. Screening and Informed Consent Subjects will be screened on a weekly basis for eligibility
      of enrollment. If eligible, patients will be approached by study staff at the initial
      surgical consultation. The purpose of the study and risks of the procedures will be explained
      to the subject and the consent process must be documented accordingly in the medical record.
      Subjects who agree to study participation must sign an IRB approved informed consent form.
      Subjects will be informed that their participation in this study is voluntary and they may
      refuse to participate or discontinue from the study at any time. Subjects will be given the
      opportunity to ask the investigator questions so that they are adequately informed about the
      research. A copy of the signed informed consent must be provided to the subject and the
      informed consent process will be documented in source documents. If new information becomes
      available that may affect a subject's decision to continue to take part in the study, this
      information will be discussed with the subject by the investigator.

      Failure to meet submission requirements:

      Each patient will be required to meet their individual insurance companies requirements for
      submission of bariatric surgery approval. Subjects who provide study consent but then do not
      submit for insurance approval or are denied will be considered &quot;discontinued&quot; and will not
      require additional study follow-up visits. The reason for the discontinuation will be clearly
      delineated on the applicable case report form. Subjects in whom the robotic RYGB procedure is
      begun but not completed will be considered &quot;discontinued&quot; once discharged from the hospital
      and not require any additional study follow-up visits. Reasons for discontinuation will be
      recorded in the case report form. Additionally, female patients of child bearing age will
      undergo a standard of care pregnancy test at the time of the pre-operative surgical testing
      (2/3 weeks before surgery) and always the morning of surgery by urine HCG.

      Surgical Procedures:

      The operation will be performed per standard of care for both the laparoscopic RYGB and the
      robotic RYGB. The main difference between the two procedures is that in the robotic
      procedure, the intestinal anastomosis will be hand-sewn and in the laparoscopic RYGB, the
      anastomosis will be performed using a linear staple. Subjects will be maintained on a
      low-calorie diet for the first post-operative month, as per standard of care. In addition,
      multivitamin supplements, calcium, and iron should be prescribed and maintained per standard
      of care.

      Schedule:

      Subjects will be evaluated preoperatively, during the procedure, at discharge, and at 2
      weeks, 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months, and 12 months. Assessments to be conducted/data
      collected at each visit are listed below and in the study assessments table.

        1. Pre-operative Assessment

           The following assessments will be performed pre-operatively prior to the scheduled
           surgical procedure and the results recorded on the appropriate subject report form:

           Verification of pre-operative eligibility criteria Subject demographics (gender, age,
           race, ethnicity, smoking history) Height, weight, and body mass index (BMI) Comorbidity
           assessment (prevalence and duration of type 2 diabetes mellitus, sleep apnea,
           hypertension, dyslipidemia/hyperlipidemia, and other clinically relevant comorbidities
           as determined by the treating physician), including medications Fasting labs (glucose,
           hemoglobin, HbA1C, hematocrit, ferritin, albumin, total protein, calcium, parathyroid
           hormone, vitamin A, Vitamin B1, Vitamin B12, Vitamin D2/3, Vitamin 3, Vitamin K, folic
           acid, insulin, lipid panel, triglycerides, total cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein
           (HDL), low-density lipoprotein (LDL), C-peptides, iron, copper, and zinc) Surgical
           history Health- related Quality of life, as measured by the SF-36 assessment
           Gastrointestinal symptom rating scale, as measured by the GSRS form GERD HR-QL
           Pre-operative Dietary Restrictions

        2. Operative Assessment The following procedures and assessments will be performed on the
           day of/during the procedure: Weight and BMI American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA)
           grade operative time (defined as skin to skin time) anesthesia start and stop time
           estimated blood loss adverse events surgical technique surgical conversions to open
           concomitant procedures performed during the procedure

        3. Discharge Assessment

           The following procedures and assessments will be performed prior to discharge:

           Length of hospital stay Surgical site infection assessment Surgical site infection (SSI)
           Adverse events (see below)

        4. Post-operative follow-up assessments

           The following procedures and assessments will be performed at 2 weeks, 6 weeks, 3
           months, 6 months, 9 months and 12 months post procedure (+/- 7 days for 2 and 6 week
           follow-up, +/- 14 day days for all other months).

           Post-operative standard of care:

           Compliance with prescribed dietary supplements Weight and BMI EWL Comorbidity assessment
           (prevalence and duration of type 2 diabetes mellitus, sleep apnea, hypertension,
           dyslipidemia/hyperlipidemia, and other clinically relevant comorbidities as determined
           by the treating physician), including medications and relevant lab tests per standard of
           care at 3, 6, and 12 months (glucose, hemoglobin, HbA1C, hematocrit, ferritin, albumin,
           total protein, calcium, parathyroid hormone, vitamin A, Vitamin B1, Vitamin B12, Vitamin
           D2/3, Vitamin 3, Vitamin K, folic acid, insulin, lipid panel, triglycerides, total
           cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein (HDL), low-density lipoprotein (LDL), C-peptides,
           iron, copper, and zinc) Surgical site infection assessment at 1 month only
           health-related quality of life (HR-QOL) (SF-36), GERD-HRQL and GSRS questionnaire
           expressed as change from baseline at 3, 6 and 12 months only EGD at 1 year to assess
           stricture, marginal ulceration, and gastritis adverse events (see below)

        5. Adverse Events Adverse events for all bariatric procedures are tracked within our
           centers Metabolic and Bariatric Surgery Accreditation and Quality Improvement Program
           (MBSAQIP) database. All bariatric centers accredited by the American Society for
           Metabolic and Bariatric Surgery (ASMBS) are required to submit all bariatric surgery
           data to the MBSAQIP database for quality review. Our bariatric surgery team has open
           access to our centers data for quality review purposes and will compare adverse events
           for the robotic and laparoscopic RYGB to the other procedures performed by our center.
           Adverse events are categorized by organ system (wound, respiratory, urinary tract, CNS,
           cardiac, or other) as specified by the MBSAQIP. Any post-operative occurrence within 30
           days will be documented if related to the bariatric procedure. Bariatric related
           readmission and reoperations are also tracked per MBSAQIP guidelines.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stricture Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Examine the development of stricture at the anastomosis. Stricture will be determined by esophagogastroduodenoscopy (EGD) at 1 year post-surgery.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Leak rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Examine leak development at the anastomosis site. Leak is determined by clinical findings of pain, tachycardia, fever, and confirmed by a barium swallow study that indicates a hole at the anastomosis site</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life impact</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Examine the quality of life impact of the surgery, using the SF-36 questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">63</enrollment>
  <condition>Roux-en-y Anastomosis Site</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RYGB: Hand-sewn</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group would receive a Roux-en-y gastric bypass with the anastomosis hand-sewn using a minimally-invasive robotic surgical approach</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RYGB: linear-staple</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group would receive a Roux-en-y gastric bypass with the anastomosis sewn with a linear stapler using a laparoscopic surgical approach</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RYGB hand-sewn</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will have the RYGB anastomosis hand-sewn</description>
    <arm_group_label>RYGB: Hand-sewn</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RYGB linear-staple</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will have the RYGB anastomosis performed using a linear staple.</description>
    <arm_group_label>RYGB: linear-staple</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Eligible participants who have access to care at UNMC.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women age 19-70 who will receive their weight loss procedure at UNMC

          -  BMI of 35-45

          -  RYGB as the primary procedure

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  RYGB performed as a revisional procedure

          -  Prior foregut surgery

          -  H/o smoking, unless the patient quit more than 10 years ago

          -  Complication of bariatric procedure post-operatively that would significantly affect
             weight loss (extended period of TPN, clinically significant leak, major organ failure,
             severe protein malnutrition or failure to thrive)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Vishal Kothari, MD</last_name>
    <phone>402-559-6074</phone>
    <email>vishal.kothari@unmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Crystal Krause, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>402-559-2116</phone>
    <email>crystal.krause@unmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 22, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 22, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 26, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Nebraska</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Vishal Kothari</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>We do not currently plan to make individual participant data available to other researchers.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

