<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03195777</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017P000808</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03195777</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Novel PET/CT and Treatment Strategies to Reduce PTS Following DVT</brief_title>
  <official_title>Novel PET/CT and Treatment Strategies to Reduce PTS Following DVT</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to develop strategies that will improve outcomes for patients with
      deep vein thrombosis (DVT), using in vivo FDG-PET inflammation imaging to better predict the
      development of the post-thrombotic syndrome (PTS). New approaches are needed to improve the
      outcomes of patients with DVT, a disease that affects up to 600,000 patients per year in the
      US alone. DVT acutely places patients at risk of death from pulmonary embolism and causes
      50,000 deaths annually in the US. Moreover, up to 30-50% of patients will develop PTS, an
      illness characterized by inflammation-driven fibrotic vein wall injury, and persistent
      thrombus obstruction. PTS occurs despite anticoagulant therapy, and produces chronic
      disability from leg pain, heaviness, edema, skin pigmentation, and ulcers; some patients may
      even require amputation. PTS impairs quality of life to the same extent as chronic
      obstructive pulmonary disease or diabetes. Therefore new diagnostic insights into PTS are
      urgently needed.

      There are several major challenges to improve outcomes in PTS: A) Limited in vivo knowledge
      regarding inflammation and the development of PTS; B) L Lack of predictive approaches to
      identify patients at high risk for PTS that will preferentially benefit from novel therapies.
      Recently, our laboratories have harnessed FDG-PET molecular imaging to illuminate DVT
      inflammation in vivo, and to provide a new strategy to diagnose recurrent DVT, a vexing
      clinical problem (Hara et al. Circulation 2014). We now propose to further develop FDG-PET to
      improve outcomes in DVT and PTS.

      The objective of this application is to develop FDG-PET as an inflammation imaging approach
      to assess DVT inflammation and predict risk of developing PTS in human subjects;

      Hypothesis 1A: Inflammatory activity in DVT (quantified acutely, using FDG-PET imaging within
      0-7 days after DVT) will predict PTS incidence (primary) and severity (secondary) within a 24
      month follow-up period.

      Hypothesis 1B: Inflammatory activity in DVTs (quantified sub-acutely, using FDG-PET imaging
      within 21-28 days after DVT), will predict PTS incidence and severity.

      Eighty patients with DVT will be imaged using FDG-PET/CT acutely (0-7 days of DVT diagnosis),
      and sub-acutely (21-28 days after diagnosis). Subjects will be evaluated repeatedly for up to
      2 years to detect clinical evidence of PTS (Villalta score), ultrasound findings for
      structural venous injury, and soluble biomarkers of systemic inflammation. Subsequently, we
      will evaluate the relationship between FDG DVT activity and the development of PTS.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a one-center observational study examining DVT with PET/CT. 80 individuals with
      recent deep venous thrombosis (DVT) will be recruited from MGH. Imaging and clinical
      evaluation will be performed to look for predictors of a major complication of DVT: the
      post-thrombotic syndrome (PTS)

      There are 5 visits to attend. The imaging visits will last 2-3 hours. The clinical evaluation
      visits will last 1-2 hours.

        1. Screening - This visit will take place after initial DVT (deep venous thrombosis)
           diagnosis. It will involve clinical assessments and blood labs, to determine subject
           eligibility. If an ultrasound was not performed at the time of DVT diagnosis, an
           ultrasound should be performed.

        2. Visit 1 (0-7 days after DVT diagnosis) - Imaging Visit 1 - At this visit, patients will
           receive a positron-emission tomography/ computed tomography (PET/CT) scan, and
           contrast-enhanced CT of the lower extremity (CTA) and will have blood labs drawn.

        3. Visit 2 (21-28 days after DVT diagnosis) - Imaging Visit 2 - At this visit, patients
           will receive a PET/CT scan and will have blood labs drawn.

        4. Visit 3 (6 months after DVT diagnosis) - Clinical Evaluation - At this visit, patients
           will meet to evaluate symptoms of DVT and PTS. Blood labs will be drawn. An ultrasound
           will be performed as well.

        5. Visit 4 (24 months after DVT diagnosis OR time of PTS diagnosis) - Clinical Evaluation -
           At this visit, patients will meet to evaluate symptoms of DVT and PTS. Blood labs will
           be drawn. An ultrasound will be performed as well.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 20, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This study is a one-center observational study examining DVT with FDG- PET/CT. 80 individuals with DVT will be imaged with PET/CT and followed for development of PTS</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>Investigators who are analyzing images will be blinded to all clinical data, including clinical follow-up data to determine PTS</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PTS incidence</measure>
    <time_frame>24 month follow-up period</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of PTS (by Villalta score of ≥5) at any time during 24 months of observation after diagnosis of first proximal DVT</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PTS severity</measure>
    <time_frame>24 month follow-up period</time_frame>
    <description>Maximal severity of PTS (by Villalta score) during 24 month observation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Deep Venous Thrombosis</condition>
  <condition>Post-thrombotic Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm: Observation after Imaging</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is a single-arm study, where subjects will be monitored for development of PTS after baseline non-invasive imaging with FDG PET/CT. The experimental interventIon is the PET/CT imaging.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PET/CT</intervention_name>
    <description>PET/CT imaging will be performed (with fluorodeoxyglucose, [FDG] as a tracer). Thereafter, subjects will be monitored for development of PTS. We will then assess the ability of PET/CT top predict the subsequent development of PTS.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm: Observation after Imaging</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age above 30

          -  Patient presents with a first symptomatic, proximal DVT (with or without concurrent
             distal DVT or pulmonary embolism).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient has May-Thurner syndrome

          -  Patient has an expected life span of &lt; 6 months

          -  Patient can't receive anticoagulation therapy

          -  Patient received thrombolytic therapy for the initial treatment of acute DVT

          -  Patient has DVT signs of symptoms that occur more than 1 week prior to presentation,
             as assessed by clinical history

          -  Renal dysfunction (Serum creatinine &gt; 1.5 mg/ml or estimated creatinine clearance &lt; 60
             ml/min)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ahmed Tawakol, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617-726-0791</phone>
    <email>atawakol@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ahmed A Tawakol, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-726-0791</phone>
      <email>atawakol@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hara T, Truelove J, Tawakol A, Wojtkiewicz GR, Hucker WJ, MacNabb MH, Brownell AL, Jokivarsi K, Kessinger CW, Jaff MR, Henke PK, Weissleder R, Jaffer FA. 18F-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography/computed tomography enables the detection of recurrent same-site deep vein thrombosis by illuminating recently formed, neutrophil-rich thrombus. Circulation. 2014 Sep 23;130(13):1044-52. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.114.008902. Epub 2014 Jul 28.</citation>
    <PMID>25070665</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 20, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 20, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 22, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 31, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 31, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ahmed Tawakol</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Interim Director, Nuclear Cardiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thrombosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Venous Thrombosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Postthrombotic Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Postphlebitic Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

