<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03193281</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CTNZ-2012-08</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03193281</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>KISS Study: Kinase Inhibition With Sprycel Start up</brief_title>
  <acronym>KISS</acronym>
  <official_title>KISS Study: A Phase II Study of Dasatinib Followed by Imatinib in Newly Diagnosed, Previously Untreated Patients With Chronic Phase CML</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Auckland, New Zealand</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Leukaemia &amp; Blood Cancer New Zealand</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Auckland, New Zealand</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic myeloid leukaemia (CML) is due to a chromosomal abnormality in white blood cells
      which results in abnormal multiplication. CML in its earlier, slower growing chronic phase
      (CP) is well controlled by the tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI) drug imatinib, which targets
      the consequences of the chromosomal abnormality, inducing a response and subsequent remission
      (as measured using molecular techniques on patient blood or bone marrow samples in the lab).
      Dasatinib, a newer TKI drug, similar in design to imatinib, gives a more rapid molecular
      response, however the long term side-effects are less known than imatinib.

      This study will investigate the efficacy and safety of a treatment plan for patients with
      newly diagnosed CML-CP, where dasatinib will be used to more rapidly induce a molecular
      response (MR3.0) within 12 months, after which imatinib will be used to maintain the CML in
      that remission. It is hypothesised that imatinib is safe and effective in maintaining MR3.0
      in patients with CML who achieve MR3.0 at 12 months following initial induction therapy with
      dasatinib.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The KISS Study is a Phase II, multicentre, open-label, prospective non-randomised study of
      treatment modification in response to maintenance of MR3.0 at 12 months. Patients must be
      newly diagnosed with chronic phase CML (CML-CP) (&lt;3 months) and previously untreated with the
      exception of hydroxyurea.

      Patients will be recruited from hospital haematology clinics. The majority of patients will
      have been referred to a haematologist due to suspected CML. Written informed consent will be
      ensured before any study-specific procedures are undertaken or study data collected, however
      the majority of assessments carried out for this study are based on standard of care.

      Patients' eligibility will be determined by the usual procedures carried out for CML
      diagnosis. Results from both diagnostic procedures and confirmatory screening procedures will
      constitute baseline data. Once a patient has had their eligibility confirmed and has signed
      informed consent, they will be enrolled into the trial.

      The trial consists of two stages:

      Stage 1: The first 12 months after recruitment (before the possible switch to imatinib).

      Stage 2: Months 13 - 37.

      The following measurements/data will be recorded throughout the trial at protocol specified
      time points:

        -  Haematology and biochemistry.

        -  PB Q-PCR for BCR-ABL1.

        -  Chest x-ray, ECG, ECHO.

        -  Medical assessment including physical exam, ECOG performance, weight, vital signs,
           assessment of extra medullary disease (liver, lymph nodes and spleen), spleen
           measurement below left costal margin, adverse events and concomitant medications.

        -  Haematological and molecular response assessments.

        -  Treatment adherence assessment.

        -  Patient questionnaire (MDASI-CML).

      All patients will commence dasatinib (Sprycel®) 100 mg daily. Molecular monitoring of blood
      BCR-ABL1 transcripts to measure molecular response will occur 3 monthly by Q-PCR as per
      standard of care procedures. Patients who achieve a BCR-ABL1 level of ≤ 0.1% (MR3.0) by 12
      months on treatment will switch treatment to imatinib 400 mg daily if MR3.0 is confirmed at
      13 months (and they give their consent to switch). Those patients who do not achieve MR3.0 at
      12 months or MR3.0 is not confirmed at 13 months, will remain on dasatinib. Patients with
      confirmed MR3.0 who choose not to switch to imatinib will continue on dasatinib. Patients
      that are intolerant of dasatinib in the first 12 months, those that switch to imatinib at 12
      months and then lose MR3.0 or those intolerant of imatinib will be treated off study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 17, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A Phase II, multicentre, open-label, prospective non-randomised study of treatment modification in response to maintenance of MR3.0 at 12 months.
Molecular response will be measured 3 monthly. Patients who achieve MR3.0 by 12 months, with a confirmed response at 13 months on treatment, will switch treatment to imatinib. Those patients who do not achieve this confirmed response will remain on dasatinib.
For patients who achieve confirmed MR3.0 by 13 months we define two study stages. Stage 1 is the first 12 months after recruitment (i.e. before the possible switch to imatinib) and Stage 2 includes the months 13 - 37.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To estimate the proportion of patients who remain in MR3.0 for the duration of 2 years following a change of therapy from dasatinib to imatinib at 13 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To estimate progression free survival (PFS), failure free survival (FFS) and overall survival (OS) for patients that switch to imatinib at 13 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To estimate the proportion of patients who regain MR3.0 on dasatinib or another TKI therapy after having a confirmed loss of MR3.0 on imatinib, for patients that switch to imatinib at 13 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To estimate time to MR3.0, MR4.5 and MR5.0 for patients that switch to imatinib at 13 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To describe adverse event profiles on Stage 1 and Stage 2 of the study and overall for patients that switch to imatinib at 13 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To describe the quality of life on Stage 1 and Stage 2 of the study and overall for those that switch to imatinib at 13 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>To estimate PFS, FFS and OS for the following groups: 1) the entire cohort 2) patients not eligible to switch to imatinib at 13 months 3) patients that are eligible but do not switch.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>To estimate time to MR3.0, MR4.5 and MR5.0 for the following groups: 1) the entire cohort 2) patients not eligible to switch to imatinib at 13 months 3) patients that are eligible but do not switch.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>To describe adverse event profiles on each stage of study therapy for the following groups: 1) the entire cohort 2) patients not eligible to switch to imatinib at 13 months 3) patients that are eligible but do not switch.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>To describe the quality of life on each stage of study therapy for the following groups: 1) the entire cohort 2) patients not eligible to switch to imatinib at 13 months 3) patients that are eligible but do not switch.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dasatinib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will begin the study on dasatinib treatment (Sprycel® 100mg once daily oral administration). Those who reach MR3.0 at 12 months (end of Study Stage 1) and achieve a confirmed result at 13 months, will switch to imatinib treatment (Imatinib-AFT 400mg once daily oral administration) for the next 24 months (Study Stage 2).
Patients who do not achieve a confirmed MR3.0 result at 13 months will not be eligible to switch to imatinib treatment and will remain on dasatinib treatment, as per Study Stage 1.
Patients will be assessed on a 3-monthly basis throughout the study. Those who discontinue dasatinib treatment during the study for reasons other than the planned treatment switch to imatinib at 13 months, will also be followed up every 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dasatinib</intervention_name>
    <description>In order to test the study hypothesis patients need to stay on dasatinib (Sprycel) treatment for the first 12 months of the study (Stage 1).
Patients who do not reach MR3.0 at 12 months will remain on dasatinib treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dasatinib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sprycel</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Imatinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients who reach MR3.0 at 12 months (and the result is confirmed at 13 months) will switch to imatinib (Imatinib-AFT) treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dasatinib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Imatinib-AFT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Male or female patients ≥ 18 years of age.

          2. ECOG performance status score of 0-2.

          3. Patients must have all of the following:

               1. Be enrolled within 3 months of initial diagnosis of CML-CP (date of initial
                  diagnosis is the date of first cytogenetic analysis).

               2. Cytogenetic or molecular confirmation of Ph+ or variants of (9;22)
                  translocations.

                  patients may have secondary chromosomal abnormalities in addition to the Ph+.

               3. Documented chronic phase CML as defined by:

                    -  &lt; 15% blasts in peripheral blood and bone marrow.

                    -  &lt; 30% blasts plus promyelocytes in peripheral blood and bone marrow.

                    -  &lt; 20% basophils in peripheral blood.

                    -  ≥ 100 x 109/L platelets (unless considered related to hydroxyurea).

                    -  no evidence of extramedullary leukaemic involvement, with the exception of
                       hepatosplenomegaly.

               4. BCR-ABL1 transcript that can be monitored by Q-PCR.

               5. Baseline full blood count (within 7 days of enrolment) remains consistent with
                  chronic phase CML criteria.

          4. Voluntary written informed consent.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Any prior treatment for CML with other than hydroxyurea.

          2. Patients with the following laboratory values:

               1. serum bilirubin &gt; 2.0 x the institutional upper limit of the normal range (ULN).

               2. ALT &gt; 2.0 x the institutional upper limit of the normal range (ULN).

               3. creatinine &gt; 2.0 x the institutional upper limit of the normal range (ULN).

               4. International normalised ratio (INR) or partial thromboplastin time (PTT) &gt; 1.5 x
                  ULN, with the exception of patients on treatment with oral anticoagulants.

          3. Patients with uncontrolled medical disease such as diabetes mellitus, thyroid
             dysfunction, neuropsychiatric disorders or infection.

          4. Patients with:

               1. Grade 3/4 cardiac problems as defined by the New York Heart Association Criteria.

               2. Uncontrolled hypertension.

               3. Grade 3/4 respiratory dysfunction.

               4. Past or current history of pleural effusions or pulmonary arterial hypertension.

          5. Patients with known positivity for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV); baseline
             testing for HIV is not required.

          6. Patients who have undergone major surgery within 4 weeks of study Day 0, or who have
             not recovered from prior major surgery.

          7. Patients who are:

               1. pregnant.

               2. breast feeding.

               3. of childbearing potential without a negative pregnancy test on/prior to Day 0.

               4. male or female of childbearing potential unwilling to use barrier contraceptive
                  precautions throughout the trial (postmenopausal women must be amenorrhoeic for
                  at least 12 months to be considered of non-childbearing potential).

          8. Patients with another uncontrolled malignancy with the exception of basal cell skin
             carcinoma or cervical carcinoma in situ.

          9. Patients with positivity for hepatitis B antigen and / or hepatitis B core antibody
             (unless receiving prophylactic therapy with lamivudine or more potent agent)

         10. Patients with a history of non-compliance to medical regimens or who are considered
             potentially unreliable.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter Browett, MBChB</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Auckland, New Zealand</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lindsey Wylde, MSc(Res)</last_name>
    <phone>+6499234927</phone>
    <email>l.wylde@auckland.ac.nz</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sarah Benge, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+6499233585</phone>
    <email>s.benge@auckland.ac.nz</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Auckland City Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Auckland</city>
        <country>New Zealand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lindsey Wylde</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Browett</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Middlemore Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Auckland</city>
        <country>New Zealand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lindsey Wylde</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gordon Royle</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Christchurch Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Christchurch</city>
        <country>New Zealand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lindsey Wylde</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dunedin Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dunedin</city>
        <country>New Zealand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lindsey Wylde</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lucy Pemberton</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>New Zealand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 15, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 15, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 20, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 21, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 21, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Auckland, New Zealand</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Professor Peter Browett</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dasatinib</keyword>
  <keyword>Imatinib</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelogenous, Chronic, BCR-ABL Positive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Imatinib Mesylate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dasatinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The KISS Study also provides an opportunity for collaborative research groups at the University of Auckland to conduct sub-studies that aim to answer questions about CML biomarkers and off-target effects of tyrosine kinase inhibitor therapy.
The sub-studies include:
A CML Molecular Biomarker study which will further investigate a more sensitive genomic DNA-based assay of minimum residual disease and molecular profiling of additional mutations that predict for treatment response and resistance.
A Bone Study assessing the off-target effects of dasatinib on bone metabolism.
De-identified clinical data collected as part of the main KISS Study from patient medical records and study data sets will be used in these sub-studies. The data will relate to patients' response to treatments and molecular remission duration. Only Auckland patients will be able to take part in the sub-studies due to the assessments required.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

