<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03190642</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OMFSTEROIDS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03190642</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Evaluation of Perioperative Steroid Dosing on Postsurgical Edema in Orthognathic Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Evaluation of Perioperative Steroid Dosing on Postsurgical Edema in Orthognathic Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jean Charles Doucet</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Nova Scotia Health Authority</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nova Scotia Health Authority</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The current standard of care at the Oral and Maxillofacial Department at the CDHA is the use
      of one gram of methylprednisolone administered intravenously prior to orthognathic surgery.
      This is largely based on the work of Habal. The administration of one gram of
      methylprednisolone can be concerning for the anesthesiologist since this is an unusually
      large dose of steroid in comparison to use in other surgical specialties. As with most
      medications, the chances of steroid-related complications increase with increasing doses of
      steroids.

      The researchers are proposing a prospective, double-blind randomized control trial to
      determine if a smaller dose of methylprednisolone (125mg) can be used safely and effectively
      instead of one gram of methylprednisolone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Orthognathic surgery is a commonly performed surgery to correct facial functional and
      esthetic deformities. At the Atlantic Centre of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery in Halifax,
      Nova Scotia, over 300 of these surgeries are carried out yearly. Orthognathic surgery is
      comprised of procedures performed in both the maxilla and mandible which include Lefort 1,
      bilateral sagittal split and functional (BSSO) and functional genioplasty. Common sequelae
      after orthognathic surgery include post-operative pain and swelling.

      Swelling occurs almost universally to some degree after orthognathic surgery. Steroid therapy
      has long been advocated for the reduction of post-operative swelling in oro-facial surgeries,
      as there is good evidence to support its use for this purpose. In 1978, Habal showed that one
      gram of methylprednisolone administered in a controlled dog model reduced post-operative
      swelling. He later carried this over to his practice of cosmetic facial surgeries. His
      studies have laid the much of the ground work for the use of steroid therapy in head and neck
      surgeries today.

      Other studied benefits of steroid use in facial surgery include decreased post-operative
      pain, trismus, nausea and vomiting as well as decreased length of hospital stays.
      Complications of steroid use include compromised healing or infection, sleep disturbances,
      hyperglycemia, avascular necrosis of bone, steroid-related acne and adverse psychiatric
      effects.

      The use of perioperative steroids as a means of swelling control is the current standard of
      care in the practice of orthognathic surgery. Despite this fact, there is little consensus on
      the ideal steroid regimen (i.e. type and dosing) to use for surgery. As such, the use of
      steroids in Oral and Maxillofacial surgical practices are based primarily on surgeon's
      preference and familiarity with a particular steroid regimen. This is likely due to the weak
      evidence in published literature in favor of a steroid regimen to mitigate post-operative
      swelling.

      Most literature in favor of particular steroid regimens involves crude or arbitrary
      measurements of swelling. In 1978, Habal showed that one gram of methylprednisolone
      administered in a controlled dog model reduced post-operative swelling. This observation was
      made by a trained observer against a control group who received no steroid. Other studies
      have had trained observers look at post-operative photographs of patients who had undergone
      orthognathic surgery to stratify which had &quot;more&quot; or &quot;less&quot; swelling. Another study attempted
      to quantify the degree of post-operative swelling by measuring the distance between the
      earlobes under the chin. These authors acknowledged that this could be altered by the facial
      movements produced during orthognathic surgery and that better means of measurement of facial
      swelling should be employed in future research.

      The current standard of care at the Oral and Maxillofacial Department at the CDHA is the use
      of one gram of methylprednisolone administered intravenously prior to orthognathic surgery.
      This is largely based on the work of Habal. The administration of one gram of
      methylprednisolone can be concerning for the anesthesiologist since this is an unusually
      large dose of steroid in comparison to use in other surgical specialties. As with most
      medications, the chances of steroid-related complications increase with increasing doses of
      steroids.

      The researchers are proposing a prospective, double-blind randomized control trial to
      determine if a smaller dose of methylprednisolone (125mg) can be used safely and effectively
      instead of one gram of methylprednisolone, which is the current standard of care in our
      department. One hundred and twenty-five milligrams of methylprednisolone is a readily
      available dose of steroids and has been shown in several studies to be effective in the
      reduction of swelling after oral surgeries and other swelling-related conditions. In their
      systematic literature review of corticosteroid administration in oral and orthognathic
      surgery, Dan et al. concluded that a preoperative dose of methylprednisolone &gt;85mg results in
      a significant decrease in post-operative oedema. The researchers hypothesize that there will
      be little difference between groups with regards to primary study outcome measure of
      post-operative swelling.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative edema</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-operative period- post-op day 1 until braces off or until 100 weeks post-operatively, whichever comes first</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of post-operative edema using 3D facial scanner</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient perceived swelling</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-operative day 2</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of post-operative patient perceived swelling via survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-operative day 2</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of post-operative pain via survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative sleep</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-operative day 2</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of post-operative sleep via survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative nausea</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-operative day 2</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of post-operative nausea via survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Until discharge from hospital or post-operative day 100, which ever comes first</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of length of post-operative hospital stay</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of post-operative infection</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-operative period- post-op day 1 until braces off or until 100 weeks post-operatively, which ever comes first</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of post-operative infections</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Post-operative Edema</condition>
  <condition>Steroid Use</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1000mg methylprednisolone group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Evaluating effects of 1000mg of methylpresdnisolone administered immediately preoperatively and its effects on swelling.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>125mg methylprednisolone group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Evaluating effects of 125mg of methylpresdnisolone administered immediately preoperatively and its effects on swelling.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methylprednisolone</intervention_name>
    <description>Administration of 1000mg vs 125mg methylprednisolone preoperatively in orthognathic surgery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1000mg methylprednisolone group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>125mg methylprednisolone group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Solumedrol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients age 14 and over undergoing orthognathic surgery at the Atlantic Centre of
             Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery in Halifax, Nova Scotia will be included in our study.
             The clinic is located in the Victoria General Hospital in Halifax, Nova Scotia.
             Orthognathic surgery includes any combination of Lefort 1, Bilateral Sagittal Split
             Osteotomy (BSSO) and functional genioplasty procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with pertinent medical history that precludes the use of high-dose steroids
             will be excluded from our study. This includes:

               -  Known hypersensitivity to steroids

               -  Type 1 diabetic patients who may have a severe elevation of blood sugars with
                  steroid use.

               -  Systemic fungal infections

               -  Arrested tuberculosis

               -  Herpes simplex keratitis

               -  Acute psychoses

               -  Cushing's syndrome

               -  Peptic ulcer disease

               -  Pregnant patients and patients with current infections will be excluded Breast
                  feeding mother
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Matthew B Fay, DDS, BSc</last_name>
    <phone>902-473-2070</phone>
    <email>mfay@ualberta.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jean-Charles Doucet, DMD, MSc, MD</last_name>
    <phone>902-473-2070</phone>
    <email>jc.doucet@dal.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guernsey LH, DeChamplain RW. Sequelae and complications of the intraoral sagittal osteotomy in the mandibular rami. Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol. 1971 Aug;32(2):176-92.</citation>
    <PMID>5284103</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dan AE, Thygesen TH, Pinholt EM. Corticosteroid administration in oral and orthognathic surgery: a systematic review of the literature and meta-analysis. J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2010 Sep;68(9):2207-20. doi: 10.1016/j.joms.2010.04.019. Epub 2010 Jun 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20591548</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Habal MB, Powell RD. Experimental facial edema: treatment with methylprednisolone. J Surg Res. 1978 May;24(5):353-8.</citation>
    <PMID>651330</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Habal MB. Prevention of postoperative facial edema with steroids after facial surgery. Aesthetic Plast Surg. 1985;9(2):69-71.</citation>
    <PMID>4025052</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chegini S, Dhariwal DK. Review of evidence for the use of steroids in orthognathic surgery. Br J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2012 Mar;50(2):97-101. doi: 10.1016/j.bjoms.2010.11.019. Epub 2011 Feb 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21316821</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huamán ET, Juvet LM, Nastri A, Denman WT, Kaban LB, Dodson TB. Changing patterns of hospital length of stay after orthognathic surgery. J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2008 Mar;66(3):492-7. doi: 10.1016/j.joms.2007.08.025.</citation>
    <PMID>18280382</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Poetker DM, Reh DD. A comprehensive review of the adverse effects of systemic corticosteroids. Otolaryngol Clin North Am. 2010 Aug;43(4):753-68. doi: 10.1016/j.otc.2010.04.003. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20599080</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Precious DS, Hoffman CD, Miller R. Steroid acne after orthognathic surgery. Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol. 1992 Sep;74(3):279-81.</citation>
    <PMID>1407985</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Galen DM, Beck M, Buchbinder D. Steroid psychosis after orthognathic surgery: a case report. J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 1997 Mar;55(3):294-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9054921</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weber CR, Griffin JM. Evaluation of dexamethasone for reducing postoperative edema and inflammatory response after orthognathic surgery. J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 1994 Jan;52(1):35-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8263640</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Widar F, Kashani H, Alsén B, Dahlin C, Rasmusson L. The effects of steroids in preventing facial oedema, pain, and neurosensory disturbances after bilateral sagittal split osteotomy: a randomized controlled trial. Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2015 Feb;44(2):252-8. doi: 10.1016/j.ijom.2014.08.002. Epub 2014 Oct 7.</citation>
    <PMID>25304755</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van der Meer WJ, Dijkstra PU, Visser A, Vissink A, Ren Y. Reliability and validity of measurements of facial swelling with a stereophotogrammetry optical three-dimensional scanner. Br J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2014 Dec;52(10):922-7. doi: 10.1016/j.bjoms.2014.08.019. Epub 2014 Sep 15.</citation>
    <PMID>25219776</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lübbers HT, Medinger L, Kruse A, Grätz KW, Matthews F. Precision and accuracy of the 3dMD photogrammetric system in craniomaxillofacial application. J Craniofac Surg. 2010 May;21(3):763-7. doi: 10.1097/SCS.0b013e3181d841f7.</citation>
    <PMID>20485043</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Esen E, Taşar F, Akhan O. Determination of the anti-inflammatory effects of methylprednisolone on the sequelae of third molar surgery. J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 1999 Oct;57(10):1201-6; discussion 1206-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10513866</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ichinose M, Sugiura H, Nagase H, Yamaguchi M, Inoue H, Sagara H, Tamaoki J, Tohda Y, Munakata M, Yamauchi K, Ohta K; Japanese Society of Allergology. Japanese guidelines for adult asthma 2017. Allergol Int. 2017 Apr;66(2):163-189. doi: 10.1016/j.alit.2016.12.005. Epub 2017 Feb 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28196638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 11, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 15, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 19, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 26, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 26, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 28, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Nova Scotia Health Authority</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jean Charles Doucet</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Orthognathic Surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Swelling</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Edema</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone Hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone phosphate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>NO IPD will be shared with researchers outside of the study</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

