<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03193216</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00065861</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03193216</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Impact of Adjuvant Liquid Alginate on Endoscopic Ablation Therapy of Complicated Barrett's Esophagus</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Impact of Adjuvant Liquid Alginate on Endoscopic Ablation Therapy of Complicated Barrett's Esophagus: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of South Carolina</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of South Carolina</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the addition of an alginate based solution to twice daily proton pump
      inhibitor therapy (PPI) in patients undergoing ablative therapy for dysplastic Barrett's
      esophagus. The investigators hypothesize that the addition of this medication will help to
      achieve complete remission of Barrett's over a shorter period of time.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Barrett's esophagus (BE) is a pre-cancerous condition in the esophagus that results from
      constant acid exposure and is a precursor to esophageal adenocarcinoma (EAC). Surprisingly,
      EAC rates continue to rise despite efforts aimed at addressing BE. Patients with dysplastic
      BE are at increased risk for developing EAC and in high grade dysplasia (HGD), this risk can
      be as high as 6% per year. For these reasons, these patients are candidates for ablation
      therapy, either with cryotherapy, endoscopic mucosal resection (EMR), and/or radiofrequency
      ablation (RFA). In patients receiving ablative therapy, 3-5 treatments are typically required
      before there is resolution of all Barrett's epithelium while patients remain on twice daily
      proton pump therapy.

      A recent case study by the current authors demonstrated initial failed response of BE with
      HGD to RFA and subsequently cryotherapy. Only after initiation of a liquid alginate solution
      (Gaviscon Advance - UK formulation) was there a subsequent rapid and complete response to
      therapy. This case suggests that liquid alginate provided additional esophageal protection
      allowing mucosal healing and an overall enhanced response to treatment. This finding is
      mechanistically plausible given existing evidence demonstrating the carcinogenic properties
      of bile acids and injurious activity of pepsin in non-acid refluxate, and liquid alginate's
      unique ability to control these components and inhibit acid reflux. The investigators feel
      further investigation is warranted in studying the role of adjunct liquid alginate solution
      in patients undergoing treatment for BE.

      The ingredient of interest in is alginic acid (alginate), a polysaccharide found in the cell
      walls of brown algae. Alginates are unique in their ability to form a protective layer above
      gastric contents upon exposure to gastric acid, thus limiting exposure of esophageal
      epithelium to gastric acid, bile acid, pepsin, and other parts of the gastric contents.
      Concurrently, the bicarbonate in alginate-based solutions forms carbon dioxide in the
      presence of gastric acid, which converts the gel into foam which floats to the surface of the
      gastric contents. Hence, alginate solutions form &quot;rafts&quot; which provide a physical barrier to
      acid reflux, as well as a pH-neutral substitute which refluxes preferentially over gastric
      acid.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 25, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a pilot prospective cohort study at a single tertiary center who will be compared to historical controls.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12-18 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the duration of treatment required to achieve complete endoscopic eradication of BE in patients treated with the combination of PPI and liquid alginate solution vs. those treated with PPI alone</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of treatments</measure>
    <time_frame>12-18 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the number of treatment sessions required to achieve endoscopic eradication of BE in patients treated with the combination of PPI and liquid alginate solution vs. those treated with PPI alone.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Barretts Esophagus With Dysplasia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Alginate group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this group will be taking the study medication -- alginate solution in addition to standard of care twice daily proton pump inhibitor therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Alginates</intervention_name>
    <description>Liquid Alginate therapy will be added to twice daily PPI regimen. Patients will be asked to take the alginate solution four times daily (following meals and at bedtime) at 10ml/dose.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Alginate group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gaviscon Advance</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  (1) Age 18 (2) Biopsy-proven complicated BE (low/high grade grade dysplasia or IMC,
             confirmed by our institution's GI pathologist) As part of standard of care, all
             patients' biopsies will be confirmed with the institutions' GI pathologist and, either
             with outside biopsies or from biopsies completed at the primary institution.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1) Moderate to severe renal impairment, as defined by eGFR&lt; 60 for 2 consecutive
             readings (2) Lack of capacity for decision-making (3) Allergy to hydroxybenzoates (4)
             Patients with uncontrolled hypertension or decompensated heart failure (5) Pregnancy-
             patients of child-bearing potential will be tested. (6) Patients with elevated calcium
             or potassium on screening laboratory testing (labs completed within the last month)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Aisha Vanderhorst, BA</last_name>
    <phone>843-876-0783</phone>
    <email>vander@musc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Puja S Elias, MD, Mph</last_name>
    <phone>843-876-0783</phone>
    <email>eliasps@musc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University of South Carolina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29425</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Puja S Elias, MD/MPh</last_name>
      <phone>843-876-0783</phone>
      <email>eliasps@musc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Aisha Vanderhorsdt, BA</last_name>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 16, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 16, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 20, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Barrett's</keyword>
  <keyword>GERD</keyword>
  <keyword>reflux</keyword>
  <keyword>alginate solution</keyword>
  <keyword>proton pump inhibitor</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Barrett Esophagus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Proton Pump Inhibitors</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alginic acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

