<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03197792</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P17-37813005</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03197792</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Perioperative Portal Vein Pulsatility as a Postoperative Prognostic Indicator in Pulmonary Endarterectomy</brief_title>
  <acronym>PVP-ETO-CPC</acronym>
  <official_title>Perioperative Transesophageal Portal Vein Pulsatility as a Predictor of Persistent Organ Dysfunction Plus Death 7 Days After Pulmonary Endarterectomy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Chirurgical Marie Lannelongue</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Chirurgical Marie Lannelongue</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators aim to evaluate the utility of portal vein pulsatility as a predictor of
      the composite outcome of persistent organ dysfunction plus death in patients undergoing
      elective or urgent pulmonary endarterectomy for thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension. The
      investigators' hypothesis is that the portal vein pulsatility fraction, measured using
      transesophageal echocardiography immediately after weaning of cardiopulmonary bypass, is
      proportional to the risk of developing subsequent end-organ dysfunction in the postoperative
      setting.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      While transesophageal echocardiography is recommended in patients with known or suspected
      cardiovascular pathology which may impact outcomes, no study has evaluated it's perioperative
      use in pulmonary endarterectomy surgery.

      Most pulmonary endarterectomy patients suffer from severe pulmonary hypertension, right heart
      dysfunction and central venous hypertension. Postoperative complications are closely related
      to the importance of residual postoperative pulmonary hypertension and right ventricular
      dysfunction. A portal vein pulsatility fraction of 50% or more in the perioperative setting
      might indicate right ventricular dysfunction and/or hypervolemia-related severe venous
      congestion, which may be responsible for multiple organ dysfunction and significant morbidity
      or mortality in critically ill patients.

      The investigators believe pulmonary endarterectomy patients with a high portal vein
      pulsatility fraction immediately after weaning from cardiopulmonary bypass have a greater
      risk of developing postoperative persistent organ dysfunction and/or death. In this
      prospective descriptive study, the investigators will evaluate portal vein pulsatility as a
      predictor of the composite outcome of persistent organ dysfunction plus death 7 days after
      pulmonary endarterectomy.

      Left and right global longitudinal strain after weaning from cardiopulmonary bypass will also
      be evaluated as potential indicators of a higher risk of persistent organ dysfunction plus
      death 7 days after surgery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 26, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 24, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 24, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Patients with chronic post-embolic pulmonary hypertension eligible to pulmonary endarterectomy surgery will be evaluated for venous congestion and right ventricular failure after weaning of cardiopulmonary bypass, and followed until the 7th postoperative day for the development of postoperative organ dysfunction and/or death.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Persistent organ dysfunction plus death (POD + death) 7 days after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>On the morning of the 7th postoperative day</time_frame>
    <description>POD + death, defined as death or one of the following criterias (yes or no) present on the 7th postoperative day : (1) mechanical ventilation (excluding non-invasive ventilation) without breaks for more than 48 hours, (2) ongoing need for vasopressor therapy more than 2 hours per day (dopamine more than 5 mcg/kg/min, phenylephrine more than 50 mcg/min, norepinephrine, epinephrine, vasopressin), (3) ongoing need for mechanical circulatory support such as ECMO or IABP, and (4) continuous renal replacement therapy or new intermittent hemodialysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">39</enrollment>
  <condition>Pulmonary Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Thromboembolism, Pulmonary</condition>
  <condition>Perioperative/Postoperative Complications</condition>
  <condition>Venous Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Cardiac Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pulmonary endarterectomy patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>All patients</intervention_name>
    <description>TEE is performed before cardiopulmonary bypass (before the opening of the pericardium, if possible) and immediately after weaning from cardiopulmonary bypass and optimization of the hemodynamic status by the attending anesthesiologist. A detailed ultrasound examination including portal vein pulsatility, splenic vein pulsatility, right and left ventricular global longitudinal strain and right and left systolic and diastolic function is recorded. A measure of portal vein pulsatility using TTE is also recorded before the onset of general anesthesia and on the morning of the 7th postoperative day.
On the 7th postoperative day, the investigators will evaluate for the presence of the primary outcome, POD + death.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pulmonary endarterectomy patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years or older

          -  Elective or urgent pulmonary endarterectomy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  absolute or relative contraindication to the use of transesophageal echocardiography,

          -  hepatic cirrhosis,

          -  portal vein thrombosis,

          -  concomitant coronary artery bypass grafting,

          -  patient refusal or unable to give informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>MOORE ALEX, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>HOPITAL MARIE LANNELONGUE</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>TRAORE AMINATA, CEC</last_name>
    <phone>+33140948664</phone>
    <email>a.traore@ccml.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Marie Lannelongue</name>
      <address>
        <city>Le Plessis Robinson</city>
        <zip>92350</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>TRAORE AMINATA, CEC</last_name>
      <phone>+33140948664</phone>
      <email>a.traore@ccml.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>MOORE ALEX, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hahn RT, Abraham T, Adams MS, Bruce CJ, Glas KE, Lang RM, Reeves ST, Shanewise JS, Siu SC, Stewart W, Picard MH; American Society of Echocardiography; Society of Cardiovascular Anesthesiologists. Guidelines for performing a comprehensive transesophageal echocardiographic examination: recommendations from the American Society of Echocardiography and the Society of Cardiovascular Anesthesiologists. Anesth Analg. 2014 Jan;118(1):21-68. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0000000000000016.</citation>
    <PMID>24356157</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jenkins D. Pulmonary endarterectomy: the potentially curative treatment for patients with chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension. Eur Respir Rev. 2015 Jun;24(136):263-71. doi: 10.1183/16000617.00000815. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26028638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dittrich HC, Chow LC, Nicod PH. Early improvement in left ventricular diastolic function after relief of chronic right ventricular pressure overload. Circulation. 1989 Oct;80(4):823-30.</citation>
    <PMID>2791245</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Olson N, Brown JP, Kahn AM, Auger WR, Madani MM, Waltman TJ, Blanchard DG. Left ventricular strain and strain rate by 2D speckle tracking in chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension before and after pulmonary thromboendarterectomy. Cardiovasc Ultrasound. 2010 Sep 27;8:43. doi: 10.1186/1476-7120-8-43.</citation>
    <PMID>20875129</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marston N, Brown JP, Olson N, Auger WR, Madani MM, Wong D, Raisinghani AB, DeMaria AN, Blanchard DG. Right ventricular strain before and after pulmonary thromboendarterectomy in patients with chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension. Echocardiography. 2015 Jul;32(7):1115-21. doi: 10.1111/echo.12812. Epub 2014 Oct 18.</citation>
    <PMID>25327878</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 21, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 22, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 23, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 22, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 22, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 23, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Centre Chirurgical Marie Lannelongue</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Olaf Mercier, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of thoracic surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Transesophageal ultrasound</keyword>
  <keyword>TEE</keyword>
  <keyword>Portal vein pulsatility</keyword>
  <keyword>Splenic vein pulsatility</keyword>
  <keyword>Venous congestion</keyword>
  <keyword>Strain</keyword>
  <keyword>Right ventricular dysfunction</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>Venous hypertension</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension, Pulmonary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thromboembolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Postoperative Complications</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Embolism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

