<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03196037</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LCCC 1640</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2KR871712</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03196037</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Feasibility of an 8-week Tai Chi Chuan Intervention for Breast Cancer Survivors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Feasibility of an 8-week Tai Chi Chuan Intervention for Breast Cancer Survivors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UNC Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>North Carolina Translational and Clinical Sciences Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UNC Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Purpose:To gather preliminary data and to determine the feasibility and acceptability of an
      8-week Tai Chi intervention for adults cancer survivors (survivors) who report experiencing
      cognitive impairment, and to perform exploratory analyses to assess improvements in cognitive
      performance, health-related quality of life, brain activity, and blood-based biomarkers.

      Participants: Adult survivors (&gt; 18 years old) who report experiencing cognitive impairment
      and are within 60 months of completion of chemotherapy for treatment of a breast cancer
      diagnosis.

      Procedures (methods): A single arm pre-/post-test non-randomized study design in adult cancer
      survivors (Enrollment goal N=15; current age ≥ 18 years, treatment completed within 60
      months). Outcomes will be assessed at baseline and after the 8-week Tai Chi intervention, and
      consist of feasibility, acceptability, expectancy/credibility, health-related quality of
      life, cognitive performance, serum biomarkers, and brain activity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to gather preliminary data and to determine the feasibility
      and acceptability of an 8-week Tai Chi intervention for adults within 60 months of having
      completed chemotherapy for treatment of a cancer diagnosis who report experiencing cognitive
      impairment (cancer-related cognitive impairment; CRCI). Tai Chi is a form of physical
      activity that includes an inherent level of cognitive engagement into its performance. Rodent
      studies provide evidence that including a cognitive component to physical activity (PA)
      changes its effect on the brain, with aerobic PA inducing angiogenesis and cognitively
      engaging PA inducing synaptogenesis. Human research with older adults indicates that
      interventions that combine PA and cognitive engagement produce greater cognitive benefits
      than PA alone. Experimental and meta-analytic evidence have shown that participation in PA
      improves cognitive performance in nonclinical and clinical populations, including breast
      cancer survivors. Importantly, physical activity benefits the same cognitive domains that are
      negatively affected by CRCI (i.e., attention/processing, memory, executive function).
      Recently, meta-analytic evidence showed that PA might benefit CRCI. However, in most studies
      cognitive outcomes are limited to measures of subjective cognitive function rather than
      objective measures of performance such as neuropsychological assessments or brain activity
      (e.g., EEG). Research into the effects of Tai Chi on CRCI is sparse, yet promising.

      Additionally, research has shown positive effects from Tai Chi on health-related quality of
      life and cytokines in cancer survivors. To achieve our objective of examining feasibility and
      acceptability of an 8-week Tai Chi intervention, we will use a single arm pre-/post-test
      non-randomized study design in adult breast cancer survivors (Enrollment goal N=15; current
      age ≥ 18 years, treatment completed within 60 months). Outcomes will be assessed at baseline
      and after the 8-week Tai Chi intervention, and consist of feasibility, acceptability,
      expectancy/credibility, health-related quality of life, cognitive performance, serum
      biomarkers, and brain activity. This feasibility study will help identify barriers to
      recruitment and retention, determine the acceptability of a 8- week Tai Chi intervention for
      cancer survivors, and provide data for use in designing subsequent studies. Specifically, the
      findings will inform the design of a randomized controlled trial (RCT) that is sufficiently
      powered to examine efficacy. The ultimate goal of this research is to create and test a
      method of investigation into the use of Tai Chi to prevent or mitigate CRCI as well as a
      method of improving health-related quality of life in cancer survivors.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 5, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A single-arm pre-/post-test non-randomized study design.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility - Attendance</measure>
    <time_frame>post 8-week intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility will be achieved if we observe at least 80% attendance (i.e., at least 13 out of 16 sessions attended).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility Pre-Test Completion</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility will be achieved if we observe at least 80% completion. Completion rates will be the proportion of completed measures (number completed measures/total administered measures at pre-test).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility Post-Test Completion</measure>
    <time_frame>post 8-week intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility will be achieved if we observe at least 80% completion. Completion rates will be the proportion of completed measures (number completed measures/total administered measures at post-test).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment - Frequency Approached for Screening</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>We will describe the frequency approached for screening.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment - Proportion of Completed Screening</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>We will describe the proportion of completed screening (out of approached for screening)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment - Screened Eligible</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>We will describe those screened and found to be eligible (out of total screened).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Retention Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>post 8-week intervention</time_frame>
    <description>We will describe study retention (number who remain enrolled over 8 weeks/total number originally enrolled).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment - Enrollment Refusal</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>We will collect reasons for enrollment refusal (as part of the screening survey)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Retention - Withdrawals</measure>
    <time_frame>post 8-week intervention</time_frame>
    <description>We will collect reasons for study withdrawals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of the Different Recruitment Strategies - Screened</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>For each recruitment strategy, we will describe the frequency screened,</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of the Different Recruitment Strategies - Screened Eligible</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>For each recruitment strategy, we will describe those screened and found to be eligible (out of total screened).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of the Different Recruitment Strategies - Enrolled</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>For each recruitment strategy, we will describe those enrolled (out of total screened eligible).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Expectancy/Credibility</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The Expectancy/Credibility Questionnaire will be used to assess baseline expectancy and credibility effects of taking part in the Tai Chi intervention. Responses to six questions will be indicated with a 1 to 9 Likert-type scale, with higher numbers representing greater expectancy/credibility.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability</measure>
    <time_frame>post 8-week intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The Intervention Satisfaction Scale questions: 1) &quot;Overall, I really enjoyed the Tai Chi intervention&quot; and 2) &quot;I would recommend the Tai Chi intervention to other cancer survivors&quot; will assess acceptability. Acceptability will be achieved if the mean score is 3 or greater (response range: 0=Strongly disagree to 4=Strongly agree).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention Satisfaction Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>post 8-week intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Three close-ended questions will use a Likert scale (0= strongly disagree to 4=strongly agree) to assess whether the class length, frequency, and duration was satisfactory. Four open-ended questions will collect information on what participants liked or disliked about the Tai Chi intervention, and recommendations for changes to better address cancer survivors' needs and basic study procedures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer, Breast</condition>
  <condition>Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tai Chi</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Tai Chi intervention will be lead by an expert Tai Chi instructor with 15 years of teaching experience, and will take place at a local Yoga studio. The 8-week intervention entails two 75-minute sessions per week for a total of 16 sessions. Each session will begin with a 15- minute warm-up followed by 25 minutes of performing basic stances, footwork, upper-body/arm/hand movement, proper body alignment, mental/visual focus, and balance; 30 minutes of instruction in a choreographed form (first section of the Yang style long-form); and ending with a 5-minute cool-down.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tai Chi</intervention_name>
    <description>An 8-week Tai Chi intervention consisting of 75-minute group sessions held twice a week, over 8 weeks (i.e., total of 16 sessions).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tai Chi</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Was diagnosed with breast cancer (all stages accepted).

          -  Currently &gt; 18 years of age

          -  Age at cancer diagnosis &gt; 18 years.

          -  Able to engage in moderate intensity exercise as determined by their treating
             physician. If participant no longer has a treating physician, safety will be
             determined by following the American College of Sports Medicine (PAR-Q &amp; YOU) physical
             activity questionnaire. An answer of &quot;yes&quot; to &gt; one of the seven questions will
             require the participant to receive written permission from their physician prior to
             beginning the Tai Chi intervention.

          -  Not previously engaged in regular exercise training (&gt;1-2d/wk for &gt;30 min/d) in past 6
             months.

          -  Completed chemotherapy treatment for a breast cancer diagnosis.

          -  Cancer chemotherapy treatment completed within last 60 months. Defined as not
             currently scheduled for or undergoing active treatment (chemotherapy, radiation,
             surgery). Treatments to prevent or delay recurrence (e.g., breast cancer hormonal
             therapies) or for maintenance of remission are allowed.

          -  Report experiencing cognitive impairment following treatment for cancer.

          -  No psychiatric disorder with psychotic features.

          -  Able to receive emails from study staff (i.e. for receiving study reminders).

          -  Able to speak and read English.

          -  Able to provide informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unwilling or unable to complete study procedures.

          -  Currently participating in another study which would preclude participation in this
             study.

          -  Has a known additional malignancy that is metastatic, progressing, or requires active
             treatment.

          -  Has a neurocognitive disorder of other etiologies, such as Alzheimer's Parkinson's,
             etc., that might confound the analysis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aaron T Piepmeier, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Aaron T Piepmeier, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(919) 966-8586</phone>
    <email>atpiepme@med.unc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UNC Chapel Hill Program on Integrative Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599-7200</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aaron T Piepmeier, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>336-937-3757</phone>
      <email>atpiepme@med.unc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Douglas Mann, MD</last_name>
      <phone>919-966-7672</phone>
      <email>mannj@neurology.unc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 20, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 21, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 22, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 4, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No plan.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

