<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01387412</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Merck IISP 39619</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01387412</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Role of Genital Warts in HIV Acquisition in Peru</brief_title>
  <acronym>VIVA</acronym>
  <official_title>The Role of Genital Warts in HIV Acquisition Among MSM in Peru&quot;</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Espacio Comun</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Universidad Peruana Cayetano Heredia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to determine the role of genital warts (GW) on Human
      Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) acquisition among men who have sex with men (MSM) in Peru. The
      secondary objectives are to determine Human Papillomavirus (HPV) prevalence in HIV positive
      MSM in Peru, risk factors associated with GW, and the knowledge of HPV and HIV among MSM.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Persons with Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) infection are at higher risk of becoming
      infected with the Human Papillomavirus (HPV) compared to those who are HIV negative. The
      contrary is also true: individuals infected with HPV may be more likely to acquire HIV;
      however, the role of the clinical manifestation of HPV - genital warts (GW) - on HIV
      acquisition is currently unknown. Few studies have shown that GW are independently associated
      with HIV acquisition.

      The primary objective of this study is to determine the role of GW on HIV acquisition among
      MSM in Peru. The secondary objectives are to determine HPV prevalence in HIV positive MSM in
      Peru, risk factors associated with GW, and the knowledge of HPV and HIV among MSM. The
      specific aims of this study are:

        1. To estimate HIV incidence in Peruvian MSM by GW status.

        2. To determine the prevalence of HIV among Peruvian MSM by GW status.

        3. To determine the type-specific prevalence of anal HPV infection in HIV positive Peruvian
           MSM. Linear array testing will estimate prevalence of 37 HPV types including
           carcinogenic (16,18, 31, 33, 35, 39, 45, 51, 52, 56, 58, 59, 66) and non-carcinogenic
           types (6, 11, 26, 40, 42, 53, 54, 61, 62, 64, 67, 68, 69, 70, 72, 73, 81, 82, 82var, 83,
           84, and 89) as defined at the 2005 meeting of the International Agency for Research on
           Cancer.

        4. To identify risk factors associated with genital warts (penile, anal, and both) among
           Peruvian MSM.

        5. To assess the knowledge of Peruvian MSM of the role of HPV in HIV infection.

      The study will be conducted in the Gay Men's Community Health Center, Epicentro, the only
      center in Lima that specifically caters to men who have sex with men and sees a high burden
      of genital warts in their patient population. The study includes a population of 600 MSM (300
      with recent or current genital warts). Baseline HIV serostatus will be done by rapid testing,
      and follow-up for HIV incidence will be done every 6 months over a two year time period. We
      will determine HPV status in HIV-positive participants and refer them for free highly active
      antiretroviral therapy (HAART) treatment. We will examine participants for GW presence and
      collect information on history of GW. A survey will be administered at each visit which
      examines changes in risk behaviors over time.

      This novel study proposes to both measure the prevalence of GW in MSM presenting at a
      community clinic environment and prospectively measure HIV incidence in men with GW and those
      without GW. It will be the first study of its kind that we are aware of using HIV infection
      as an endpoint in men with and without GW and will help to better understand the relationship
      between genital warts and HIV infection among MSM in Peru.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV incidence</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>new cases of HIV in our cohort in either the group with or without genital warts</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Anogenital Warts</condition>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Genital warts</arm_group_label>
    <description>Those with and without ano-genital warts</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      serum, lesion biopsies
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Community sample
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Anatomical males 18-40 years of age,

          -  Self-reported anal sex with another man within 12 months prior to enrollment,

          -  Willing to provide informed consent for the collection of demographic and sexual
             behavior data, as well as blood for HIV and Syphilis testing, swabs of anal mucosa for
             HPV testing and urine for Chlamydia testing,

          -  Resident of metropolitan Lima.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior participation in an HPV vaccine clinical trial,

          -  Prior participation in an HIV vaccine clinical trial,

          -  Presence of a known immunodeficiency that increases risk of acquiring HIV.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brandon Brown, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jerome Galea, MSW</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Espacio Comun</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Espacio Comun</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barranco</city>
        <state>Lima</state>
        <country>Peru</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Peru</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith JS, Moses S, Hudgens MG, Parker CB, Agot K, Maclean I, Ndinya-Achola JO, Snijders PJ, Meijer CJ, Bailey RC. Increased risk of HIV acquisition among Kenyan men with human papillomavirus infection. J Infect Dis. 2010 Jun 1;201(11):1677-85. doi: 10.1086/652408.</citation>
    <PMID>20415595</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jin F, Prestage GP, Imrie J, Kippax SC, Donovan B, Templeton DJ, Cunningham A, Mindel A, Cunningham PH, Kaldor JM, Grulich AE. Anal sexually transmitted infections and risk of HIV infection in homosexual men. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2010 Jan;53(1):144-9. doi: 10.1097/QAI.0b013e3181b48f33.</citation>
    <PMID>19734801</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cáceres CF, Mendoza W. Monitoring trends in sexual behaviour and HIV/STIs in Peru: are available data sufficient? Sex Transm Infect. 2004 Dec;80 Suppl 2:ii80-4.</citation>
    <PMID>15572646</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bautista CT, Sanchez JL, Montano SM, Laguna-Torres VA, Lama JR, Sanchez JL, Kusunoki L, Manrique H, Acosta J, Montoya O, Tambare AM, Avila MM, Viñoles J, Aguayo N, Olson JG, Carr JK. Seroprevalence of and risk factors for HIV-1 infection among South American men who have sex with men. Sex Transm Infect. 2004 Dec;80(6):498-504.</citation>
    <PMID>15572623</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clark JL, Segura ER, Montano SM, Leon SR, Kochel T, Salvatierra HJ, Alcantara J, Cáceres CF, Coates TJ, Klausner JD. Routine laboratory screening for acute and recent HIV infection in Lima, Peru. Sex Transm Infect. 2010 Dec;86(7):545-7. doi: 10.1136/sti.2010.042697.</citation>
    <PMID>21113069</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldstone S, Palefsky JM, Giuliano AR, Moreira ED Jr, Aranda C, Jessen H, Hillman RJ, Ferris DG, Coutlee F, Liaw KL, Marshall JB, Zhang X, Vuocolo S, Barr E, Haupt RM, Guris D, Garner EI. Prevalence of and risk factors for human papillomavirus (HPV) infection among HIV-seronegative men who have sex with men. J Infect Dis. 2011 Jan 1;203(1):66-74. doi: 10.1093/infdis/jiq016.</citation>
    <PMID>21148498</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Li AH, Phanuphak N, Sahasrabuddhe VV, Chaithongwongwatthana S, Vermund SH, Jenkins CA, Shepherd BE, Teeratakulpisarn N, van der Lugt J, Avihingsanon A, Ruxrungtham K, Shikuma C, Phanuphak P, Ananworanich J. Anal squamous intraepithelial lesions among HIV positive and HIV negative men who have sex with men in Thailand. Sex Transm Infect. 2009 Dec;85(7):503-7. doi: 10.1136/sti.2009.036707. Epub 2009 Jun 11.</citation>
    <PMID>19525263</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen MS. Sexually transmitted diseases enhance HIV transmission: no longer a hypothesis. Lancet. 1998;351 Suppl 3:5-7. Review. Erratum in: Lancet 1998 Dec 19-26;352(9145):2026.</citation>
    <PMID>9652712</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fleming DT, Wasserheit JN. From epidemiological synergy to public health policy and practice: the contribution of other sexually transmitted diseases to sexual transmission of HIV infection. Sex Transm Infect. 1999 Feb;75(1):3-17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10448335</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grosskurth H, Mosha F, Todd J, Mwijarubi E, Klokke A, Senkoro K, Mayaud P, Changalucha J, Nicoll A, ka-Gina G, et al. Impact of improved treatment of sexually transmitted diseases on HIV infection in rural Tanzania: randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 1995 Aug 26;346(8974):530-6.</citation>
    <PMID>7658778</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 30, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 30, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 4, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 30, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 30, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 2, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Brandon Brown</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Faculty</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>genital warts</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>MSM</keyword>
  <keyword>Peru</keyword>
  <keyword>HPV</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Warts</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Condylomata Acuminata</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

