<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01380795</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0416-1cobr10</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01380795</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Feasibility of the Research for Mutation of K-ras and EGFR in CTCs From Metastatic Non Small Cells Bronchial Carcinomas</brief_title>
  <acronym>CTC-Poumon</acronym>
  <official_title>Biological Study of Feasibility Concerning the Research for Mutation of the Gene of EGFR and for K-Ras in Circulating Tumoral Cells(CTCs) of the Patients Carriers of Metastatic Non Small Cells Bronchial Carcinomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Georges Francois Leclerc</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Georges Francois Leclerc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The knowledge concerning the biology of the human tumors do not stop widening, in particular
      concerning the molecular mechanisms at the origin of the process of carcinogenesis and its
      ability to become perpetual. The identification and the increasing knowledge of these
      abnormalities allowed during these last years the development of therapeutic strategies
      targeting specifically the molecular pathways involved in the carcinogenesis. It quickly lead
      to numerous therapeutic successes in association with conventional chemotherapy, allowing a
      better individualization of the treatment according to the biological characteristics of the
      tumor of the patient.

      However such therapeutics are effective only if the patients carries specific genomic
      mutations making necessary the systematic research for one kind of mutation.

      The problem is that currently the mutational status is frequently made on the tissue
      resulting from the initial tumor biopsy, and as it is not excluded that the evolution of the
      biology of the metastasis reports a different genomic status, the only theoretical solution
      is then to make biopsy systematically on metastasis, what is not always technically possible.
      The problem still complicates when the investigators know that the biology of the tumor may
      evolve in time, particularly under treatment, with appearance of chemotherapy resistant
      clones. The monitoring of the genomic status of the tumor thus appears to be a crucial stake
      in the next years in cancer research as far as the efficiency of numerous therapeutic
      targeted put at the disposal of the clinician, depends on it largely. The repeated access to
      tumor tissue, during the follow-up of the patient in treatment, seems from then on
      indispensable to guide prematurely the therapeutics, in particular by stopping a targeted
      therapeutics which the investigators know that it is not any more going to be effective, and
      so avoiding exposing the patient to useless toxicity of a treatment often extremely
      expensive, and of which usage should have to be reserved to patient who could respond to it.

      The access to the circulating tumor cells in the blood of patients is a repeatable, not
      invasive technique (blood test) and henceforth accessible thanks to a technique using a
      magnetic sorting of the tumor cells selected by an antibody directed against the tumor
      antigen EpCAM. This new technology (CellSearch, Veridex system) totally standardized and
      automated, allows from a total sample of blood of the patient, to determine the quantity of
      circulating tumor cells (CTC).The number of CTC seems to constitute in recent studies, a
      powerful prognosis tool at the moment diagnosis, but also during treatment, according to its
      decrease or not under chemotherapy. In United States, the Food and Drug Administration (FDA)
      recently approved the use of this system for the quantification of the CTCs in the care of
      the patients affected by breast, colon, and prostate cancer. The CellSearch system will
      probably become in the future years an indispensable tool to help the clinicians to encircle
      better the prognosis of their patient. This technology already allows to realize besides a
      quantification, the isolation of viable CTCs, from which the genetic material can be
      extracted, amplified thus potentially analyzed. The investigators thus see all the interest
      which such a device can represent in the non invasive monitoring of the patients under
      treatment targeting molecular abnormality susceptible to evolve in time. The investigators
      thus propose to study thanks to the system CellSearch the feasibility of the research for the
      mutation of K-Ras and EGFR in the CTC of patients carriers of a metastatic non small cells
      bronchial carcinoma.

      Secondly, the investigators research will be interested in the possible conflicts existing
      between the primitive tumor and the CTCs for the various popular mutations. In case of
      feasibility of the method, and the good initial concordance between the genomic status of the
      CTCs and that of the tumor, the investigators shall describe the genomic evolution under
      treatment monitoring the CTCs of the patients under targeted therapeutics. The investigators
      shall describe then if the premature observation of modification precedes the appearance of
      an effective resistance in treatments.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2011</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>search for the mutation of EGFR and Kras in the CTC of the patient</measure>
    <time_frame>september 2012 (anticpated) up to 2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare EGFR/ K-ras status between CTC and the primitive tumor</measure>
    <time_frame>september 2012 (anticipated) up to 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Monitoring of the mutations of EGFR / K-ras in the CTC of the patients during treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>september 2012 (anticipated) up to 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-small Cell Lung Cancer Metastatic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Circulating Tumor Cell</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>blood sample CTC monitoring and CTC EGFR/K-ras status determination</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CTC</intervention_name>
    <description>every two cures of a standard chemotherapy patients will be taken sample of blood to monitor CTC presence and EGFR/ K-ras status of that CTC</description>
    <arm_group_label>Circulating Tumor Cell</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. men and women

          2. age over 18 y.o.

          3. signed informed consent form.

          4. Patients barriers of Non-small Cell Lung Cancer Metastatic

          5. chemotherapy non yet begun

          6. patients barrier of CTC

          7. Research for mutation of EGFR and Kras made on the primitive tumor

          8. Man and woman old enough to procreate under effective contraceptives

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. small cells bronchial cancer

          2. Non metastatic bronchial cancer

          3. Absence of detectable CTC at the patient

          4. Private individuals of freedom or under tutelage (including legal guardianship)

          5. Incapacity to sign the inform consent form or psychiatric, behavioural disorders or
             geographical situation precluding the follow-up of the protocol

          6. Pregnancy, lactating or refusal of the contraception for women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Georges François Leclerc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dijon</city>
        <zip>21000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 22, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 23, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 27, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 25, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 25, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 26, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>non-small cell lung cancer carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>circulating tumor cells</keyword>
  <keyword>EGFR</keyword>
  <keyword>K-ras</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Bronchogenic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

