<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01382862</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PHANTOM-S</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01382862</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PHANTOM-S: The Pre-Hospital Acute Neurological Therapy and Optimization of Medical Care in Stroke Patients - Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>PHANTOM-S</acronym>
  <official_title>PHANTOM-S: The Pre-Hospital Acute Neurological Therapy and Optimization of Medical Care in Stroke Patients - Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Berlin Firebrigade</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>MEYTEC GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>B.R.A.H.M.S GmbH ThermoFisher Scientific</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Federal Ministry of Education and Research via Center for Stroke Research Berlin (CSB)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>European Union</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Berlin Technology Foundation (EFRE)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Volkswagen Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>German Research Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this prospective study in acute ischemic stroke patients is to compare
      alarm-to-needle time during randomly allocated periods with and without availability of a
      specially staffed ambulance equipped with computed tomography (CT) and point-of care
      diagnostics. The investigators hypothesize that compared to regular care the investigators
      will reduce alarm-to-needle time by a minimum of 20 minutes by implementation of the stroke
      emergency mobile unit.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Time from symptom onset is crucial for the effectiveness of intravenous thrombolysis in acute
      ischemic stroke patients. Many patients receive tissue Plasminogen Activator (tPA) with
      considerable delay. The investigators developed an ambulance equipped with a CT-scanner,
      point-of-care laboratory, teleradiological support and an emergency trained neurologist on
      board. In the Pre-Hospital Acute Neurological Therapy and Optimization of Medical care in
      Stroke patients (PHANTOM-S)-study the investigators aim at a reduction of the current
      alarm-to-needle time by pre-hospital use of tissue Plasminogen Activator in an ambulance.

      The investigators hypothesize that compared to regular care we will reduce alarm-to-needle
      time by a minimum of 20 minutes by implementation of the stroke emergency mobile unit
      (STEMO).

      This is a prospective study comparing randomly allocated periods with and without STEMO
      availability.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>alarm-to-needle time</measure>
    <time_frame>day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Primary endpoint of the study is the time between activation of the emergency medical service and initiation of thrombolysis (alarm-to-needle time).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>three months after symptom onset</time_frame>
    <description>Functional outcome of patients will be assessed via modified Rankin Scale (mRS) during telephone follow-up after three months and mortality</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>other times</measure>
    <time_frame>day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Alarm-to-imaging Imaging-to-needle Alarm-to-point-of-care laboratory diagnostics (International Normalized Ratio (INR), platelet count) Alarm-to-INR normalization (&lt;1.5) in cases of intracerebral hemorrhage (ICH) and INR&gt;1.7</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Costs effectiveness will be assessed</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months (coinciding with the anticipated date of the completion of the last follow-up)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of stroke patients receiving tissue Plasminogen Activator (tPA)</measure>
    <time_frame>day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of stroke patients receiving tPA will be assessed and compared between regular care and STEMO.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Special referral</measure>
    <time_frame>day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients referred to specialized centres in case of:
Occlusion of distal carotid / proximal middle cerebral artery Space occupying cerebellar ICH (at least 6 mL) Intraventricular haemorrhage (&gt;/= 1 ventricle filled with blood)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>symptomatic intracerebral hemorrhage</measure>
    <time_frame>36 hours after symptom onset</time_frame>
    <description>symptomatic intracerebral hemorrhage (sICH) will be assessed according to European Cooperative Acute Stroke Study (ECASS) III and National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS) definition</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serious adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Serious Adverse Events (SAE) according to good clinical practice (GCP) classification</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>up to three months</time_frame>
    <description>In-hospital mortality (i.e. 7-days-mortality = primary safety outcome; safety analyses will include patients who received tissue Plasminogen Activator during the pilot phase of the study) and mortality three months after stroke will be assessed in stroke patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Proportions of patients treated in time intervals from onset</measure>
    <time_frame>day 1</time_frame>
    <description>According to time intervals 0-90, 91-180, 181-270 minutes as used in the pooled analysis of randomized controlled iv tPA trials(K. Lees et al., Lancet, 2010).
This outcome was specified before completion of data collection and will be used for cost-effectiveness analyses.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">614</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Regular Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Regular care for suspected stroke in Berlin consists of an ambulance with paramedics only, and neither computed tomography (CT) nor point-of-care diagnostics. In Berlin, emergency physicians are involved in prehospital care only in cases of special medical emergencies such as severe instability of vital parameters or loss of consciousness.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stroke Emergency Unit Mobile (STEMO)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The STEMO is equipped with a CT-scanner, a point-of-care laboratory and the infrastructure for tele-radiological as well as videoconferencing support. STEMO is operated by a team of experienced neurologists (n=6, half-time positions, with additional formal training in emergency medicine according to the requirements of the Berlin Medical Board), paramedics of the fire brigade (n=3, two years formal training in emergency care) and radiology technicians (n=3, three years formal training in radiology assistance and three months formal training in emergency care).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stroke Emergency Mobile Unit (STEMO)</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients treated in the STEMO may receive a CT-scan and point-of-care laboratory work up. This depends on the results of the neurological examination including assessment of medical history and the indication for scanning by the radiologist on call. In case of no contraindications patients with acute ischemic stroke will receive intravenous tissue Plasminogen Activator (0.9 mg/kg BW) according to the routine use of tissue Plasminogen Activator in Germany within 4.5 hours of symptom onset but with no formal upper age limit. (In other words, patients older than 80 years will not be excluded.) In case of increased INR and intracerebral hemorrhage patients will receive Prothrombin Complex Concentrate (PCC). All other indications will be treated according to national guidelines or as considered appropriate by the neurologist.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stroke Emergency Unit Mobile (STEMO)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pre-hospital thrombolysis</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients whose emergency call prompted the suspicion of stroke within 4 hours of
             symptom onset or with undetermined time of onset in the dispatch center

          -  Informed consent for documentation and follow-up provided by patients or legal
             representatives

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  age &lt; 18 years

          -  pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Heinrich Audebert, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charite - Universitätsmedizin Berlin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>10117</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 21, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 24, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 27, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 14, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 14, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 15, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Heinrich Audebert/ Prof. Dr. med.</name_title>
    <organization>Charité - Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Center for Stroke Research Berlin</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>acute ischemic stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>thrombolysis</keyword>
  <keyword>prehospital</keyword>
  <keyword>emergency medicine</keyword>
  <keyword>suspected acute stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>telemedicine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

