<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01388439</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TAM 027</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01388439</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacokinetics of Oseltamivir in Newborns and Infants</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pharmacokinetics of Oseltamivir in Newborns and Infants</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Louis Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Louis Children's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Oseltamivir dosing in infants &lt; 3 months of age is based on a single pharmacokinetic study in
      20 infants from a single center. This dataset is limited by a lack of robustness, because
      only 1 sample was collected from each participant. The investigators obtained two blood
      samples each from infants receiving oseltamivir after obtaining informed consent from the
      infant's parents. The investigators propose to analyze the blood samples to determine the
      amount of oseltamivir in the infant's blood. Measurement of these values will increase the
      understanding of the absorption and elimination of oseltamivir in preterm and term infants,
      and improve our ability to provide the correct doses to this high risk population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Oseltamivir pharmacokinetics in neonates and infants</measure>
    <time_frame>Two sample points, one 0-3 hours (baseline) and one 3-24 hours post dose</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacokinetic parameters calculated for individual subjects will include apparent distribution volume and elimination half-life of oseltamivir (OST) and OST carboxylate (CBX). Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) of OST and OST CBX will be determined using the trapezoidal method. A population pharmacokinetic model will be generated based on pooled pharmacokinetic data (2-compartment model for OST and 1-compartment model for OST CBX) utilizing maximum likelihood estimation. A weight-based dosing table will be generated to provide AUC exposures comparable to adults.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oseltamivir target level attainment</measure>
    <time_frame>Two sample points, one 0-3 hours (baseline) and one 3-24 hours post dose</time_frame>
    <description>OST target level attainment of the currently recommended dosing regimen in neonates and infants will be calculated. Currently recommended doses were utilized for all neonates and infants in our cohort. The target level attainment in this cohort will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">19</enrollment>
  <condition>Prematurity of Fetus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oseltamivir exposure</arm_group_label>
    <description>One infant in the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit (NICU) at St. Louis Children's Hospital experienced respiratory decompensation and tested positive for influenza virus type A by fluorescent antibody stain performed on a nasopharyngeal swab. This infant received treatment doses of oseltamivir. Subsequently, 27 other infants received oseltamivir prophylaxis for exposure to influenza virus type A. Exposed infants were those who shared a primary medical team, nursing care, respiratory therapist, physical therapist, or occupational therapist with the influenza A positive infant. Prophylaxis was deemed necessary by the attending neonatologist after consultation with the Infectious Diseases Division of the Department of Pediatrics at the Washington University School of Medicine.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oseltamivir</intervention_name>
    <description>Treatment dose was oseltamivir 3 mg/kg/dose by mouth (PO) twice daily. Prophylactic dose was oseltamivir 1 mg/kg/dose PO once daily to infants &lt; 28 weeks postmenstrual age (PMA), 1 mg/kg/dose PO twice daily to infants 28 - 38 weeks PMA, and 3 mg/kg/dose PO once daily to infants &gt; 38 weeks PMA. Dosing in infants &lt; 28 weeks PMA was chosen based on unpublished data from Acosta et al. This data was obtained from phone contact with Dr. Peter Gal, co-author of the study. Dosing in infants 28 - 38 weeks PMA was chosen based on published data from Acosta et al.1 Dosing in infants &gt; 38 weeks PMA and less than 3 months postnatal age was chosen based on data from Kimberlin et al. Dosing in infants &gt; 38 weeks PMA and greater than 3 months postnatal age was per the recommendations of the Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices of the United States Department of Health and Human Services.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oseltamivir exposure</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Two whole blood samples (0.5 mL) were obtained at steady state (day 3 of therapy or later),
      collected in K3EDTA mini-collection tubes labeled with a sample identification number. Plasma
      specimens were separated by centrifugation of 1500 g for 10 minutes at 4 degrees Celsius
      within 60 minutes of sample collection. Plasma supernatant was transferred into a cryovial
      labeled with the same sample identification number. Cryovials were immediately stored at -70
      degrees Celsius. Sample obtainment and processing was directly supervised by the principle
      investigator.

      The blood samples are currently being stored at -70 degrees Celsius in a research laboratory
      operated by medical faculty of the Washington University School of Medicine Department of
      Pediatrics Division of Infectious Diseases in the McDonnell Medical Sciences Building.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        One infant in the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit (NICU) at St. Louis Children's Hospital
        experienced respiratory decompensation and tested positive for influenza virus type A by
        fluorsescent antibody stain performed on a nasopharyngeal swab. This infant received
        treatment doses of oseltamivir. Subsequently, 27 other infants received oseltamivir
        prophylaxis for exposure to influenza virus type A. Exposed infants were those who shared a
        primary medical team, nursing care, respiratory therapist, physical therapist, or
        occupational therapist with the influenza A positive infant. Prophylaxis was deemed
        necessary by the attending neonatologist after consultation with the Infectious Diseases
        Division of the Department of Pediatrics at the Washington University School of Medicine.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All neonates and infants in the NICU at St. Louis Children's Hospital who received
             oseltamivir for treatment of or exposure to influenza virus type A were considered
             eligible for this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>6 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Louis Children's Hosptial</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Acosta EP, Jester P, Gal P, Wimmer J, Wade J, Whitley RJ, Kimberlin DW; National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases Collaborative Antiviral Study Group. Oseltamivir dosing for influenza infection in premature neonates. J Infect Dis. 2010 Aug 15;202(4):563-6. doi: 10.1086/654930.</citation>
    <PMID>20594104</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fiore AE, Fry A, Shay D, Gubareva L, Bresee JS, Uyeki TM; Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Antiviral agents for the treatment and chemoprophylaxis of influenza --- recommendations of the Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices (ACIP). MMWR Recomm Rep. 2011 Jan 21;60(1):1-24.</citation>
    <PMID>21248682</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 24, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 5, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 6, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 5, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 5, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 6, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Christopher McPherson</name_title>
    <organization>St. Louis Children's Hospital</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>oseltamivir</keyword>
  <keyword>influenza</keyword>
  <keyword>neonate</keyword>
  <keyword>premature</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Oseltamivir</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

