<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01381757</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999911175</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>11-I-N175</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01381757</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Utility of MODS for Diagnosis of MDR-TB and Second-Line Antituberculous Drug Susceptibility Testing in Mali</brief_title>
  <official_title>Uitlity of MODS for the Diagnosis of MDR-TB and Second-Line Antituberculous Drug Susceptibility Testing in Mali</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      -Tuberculosis (TB) is an infection of the lungs caused by bacteria. In Mali, TB is diagnosed
      with a test that is fast and inexpensive but not always accurate. The purpose of this study
      is to test a new method for diagnosing TB, called the microscopic-observation
      drug-susceptibility (MODS) test. The MODS test takes 7 days to show results. The test also
      gives information on which drugs will work best in each case.

      Objective:

      -To test a new method for diagnosing tuberculosis called the microscopic observation drug
      susceptibility test.

      Eligibility:

        -  Participants must be 12 years of age or older.

        -  They must have a diagnosis of TB from a sputum smear, or have symptoms of TB and an
           x-ray indicating that TB is present.

      Design:

        -  Participants will take part in the study from 6 months to 21 months and be assigned to
           one of three groups, depending on what type of TB they have.

        -  At the first visit, researchers ask questions about general health and symptoms of TB.
           They check vital signs, draw blood, and ask for a sputum sample. The blood is used to
           check for HIV infection and for the number of CD4 cells, which measures the severity of
           the HIV infection.

        -  The 2-, 5-, and 6-month visits are similar to the first. Those who do not have
           multidrug-resistant (MDR) TB will end their participation after the 6-month visit. MDR
           TB is tuberculosis that has not responded to isoniazid and rifampicin. Participants with
           MDR TB will remain in the study for 21 months.

        -  No treatment is provided as part of this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Approximately one-third of the world s population is infected with tuberculosis (TB), and
      over 1 million deaths occur annually worldwide because of it (1,2). Accurate diagnosis and TB
      drug susceptibility testing is necessary to treat the infection appropriately and bring this
      epidemic under control. Inappropriate treatment of TB, on the other hand, has led to the
      recent spread in multidrug-resistant TB (MDR-TB), estimated to affect over half of million
      people worldwide (2,4,5). Sputum smear microscopy, the diagnostic method commonly used in
      developing countries, is not as sensitive at detecting TB as culture-based techniques
      utilized in developed countries. Furthermore, drug-susceptibility testing is not routinely
      performed in resource-limited settings. Consequently, many individuals with TB in developing
      countries are treated with inadequate regimens, and MDR-TB continues to spread.

      The microscopic-observation drug-sensitivity (MODS) assay has been recently developed for
      rapid diagnosis of TB and simultaneous detection of resistance to first-line TB medications
      in resource-limited settings (11). MODS has been shown to be as sensitive as traditional
      culturebased methods for the detection of TB, providing results for drug susceptibility
      testing that are highly concordant with standard techniques (10).

      We propose to study the utility of the MODS assay for the diagnosis of TB in subjects who are
      sputum-smear positive or sputum-smear negative, and those with chronic TB. Susceptibility
      testing will be performed for first-line antituberculous drugs and, subsequently, second-line
      drugs, if subjects are found to have MDR-TB. The first primary objective is to calculate the
      sensitivity of detection of the MODS assay, compared with the Middlebrook culture method, in
      subjects suspected of having TB who are sputum-smear positive by microscopy. The second
      primary objective is to calculate the concordance of drug-susceptibility testing between the
      MODS assay and the agar proportion method for subjects who are sputum-smear positive,
      sputum-smear negative, or diagnosed with chronic TB.

      Secondary objectives include evaluating the utility of the MODS assay in the diagnosis of TB
      in subjects who are sputum-smear negative and those with chronic TB, the performance of
      second-line drug-susceptibility testing using the MODS assay in subjects diagnosed with
      MDRTB, the utility of the MODS assay in the diagnosis of TB in subjects coinfected with human
      immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-1 or -2, and the ability of the MODS assay to identify
      nontuberculous mycobacteria in subjects harboring these organisms.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 31, 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date>March 5, 2013</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">34</enrollment>
  <condition>Tuberculosis, Pulmonary</condition>
  <condition>Mycobacterium Tuberculous</condition>
  <condition>Antitubercular Agents</condition>
  <condition>Tuberculosis, Mulutidrug-Resistant</condition>
  <condition>Extensively Drug-Resistant</condition>
  <condition>Extensibely Drug-Resistant Tuberculosis</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Individuals (12 years of age) who meet the following criteria are eligible for enrollment
        in the study:

        Have a sputum smear that is positive for acid-fast bacilli by microscopy or have clinical
        symptoms and abnormal findings compatible with active TB on a previously performed chest
        radiograph.

        Have either completed at least 5 months of treatment with antituberculous therapy within
        the past year or have not received any antituberculous treatment in the preceding 5 years.

        Willingness to provide a sputum sample for the study.

        Ability to follow verbal instructions for producing sputum.

        Willingness to undergo testing for HIV.

        Willingness to allow storage of samples for future research.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Subjects who meet any of the following criteria are not eligible for enrollment in the
        study:

        Any condition that in the investigator s opinion places the subject at undue risk by
        participating in the study.

        Subjects younger than 12 years of age will be excluded from the study due to the difficulty
        of obtaining adequate sputum samples for the diagnosis of TB in this population and because
        there are no means for obtaining gastric aspirates at the reference centers.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sophia B Siddiqui, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID), 9000 Rockville Pi</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Bamako</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bamako</city>
        <country>Mali</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mali</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chan ED, Iseman MD. Multidrug-resistant and extensively drug-resistant tuberculosis: a review. Curr Opin Infect Dis. 2008 Dec;21(6):587-95. doi: 10.1097/QCO.0b013e328319bce6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18978526</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nathanson E, Nunn P, Uplekar M, Floyd K, Jaramillo E, Lönnroth K, Weil D, Raviglione M. MDR tuberculosis--critical steps for prevention and control. N Engl J Med. 2010 Sep 9;363(11):1050-8. doi: 10.1056/NEJMra0908076.</citation>
    <PMID>20825317</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gandhi NR, Nunn P, Dheda K, Schaaf HS, Zignol M, van Soolingen D, Jensen P, Bayona J. Multidrug-resistant and extensively drug-resistant tuberculosis: a threat to global control of tuberculosis. Lancet. 2010 May 22;375(9728):1830-43. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(10)60410-2.</citation>
    <PMID>20488523</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 5, 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 23, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 23, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 27, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Extensively Drug-Resistant Tuberculosis</keyword>
  <keyword>First-Line Antituberculous Drugs</keyword>
  <keyword>Second-Line Antituberculous Drugs</keyword>
  <keyword>Middlebrook Culture</keyword>
  <keyword>Agar Proportion Method</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease Susceptibility</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycobacterium Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis, Multidrug-Resistant</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis, Pulmonary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antitubercular Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

