<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01380561</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ASMP1001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01380561</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Metabolite Identification, Mass Balance, and PK Study of [14C]-Asimadoline to Healthy Adult Male Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Metabolite Identification, Mass Balance, and Pharmacokinetic Study of a Single Oral Dose of [14C]-Asimadoline Followed by Twice Daily Oral Dosing of 0.5 mg Asimadoline to Healthy Adult Male Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tioga Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tioga Pharmaceuticals</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an open label, single center, metabolite identification, mass balance, and PK study
      in healthy male volunteers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an open label, single center, metabolite identification, mass balance, and PK study
      in healthy male volunteers. The purposes of this study is to determine the excretion of total
      [14C] derived radioactivity and the metabolite profile after a single oral dose of [14C]
      asimadoline as well as to identify and quantitate the metabolites of asimadoline in plasma,
      urine, and feces after single and multiple oral doses of asimadoline.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Amount of [14C]derived radioactivity in urine and feces after a single oral dose of [14C]asimadoline</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 month</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration of metabolites of asimadoline in plasma, urine, and feces after single and multiple oral doses of asimadoline.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 month</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of plasma pharmacokinetics (e.g., Cmax, AUC, tmax, t1/2) of asimadoline and major metabolites</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 month</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 month</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm Study</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>asimadoline</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>asimadoline</intervention_name>
    <description>10mg [14]C labelled asimadoline Day 1 then 7 doses 0.5 mg asimadoline bid beginning on Day 2 and ending on Day 5.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm Study</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>EMD 61 753</other_name>
    <other_name>EMR 63 320</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Be informed of the nature of the study and have provided written informed voluntary
             consent

          -  Be healthy males, at least 18 years of age or the legal age of consent (whichever is
             greater) and less than 56 years of age

          -  Have a body mass index (BMI) &gt;=18.0 and &lt;32.0 kg/m2 and weigh at least 50 kg

          -  Be in good general health with no clinically relevant abnormalities based on the
             medical history, physical examination, clinical laboratory evaluations (hematology,
             clinical chemistry, urinalysis), and 12 lead electrocardiogram (ECG) that, in the
             opinion of the Investigator, would affect subject safety

          -  Agree to comply with the study procedures and restrictions.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any disease or condition that might affect drug absorption, metabolism, or excretion,
             or clinically significant cardiovascular, hematological, renal, hepatic, pulmonary,
             endocrine, gastrointestinal, immunological, dermatological, neurological, or
             psychiatric disease

          -  Receipt of a radioisotope with an effective half-life of 30 days or more within the
             previous 12 months

          -  Receipt of any diagnostic radiation procedures with an effective dose exceeding 1 rem
             in their lifetime

          -  Occupational exposure to radiation (e.g., those routinely required to wear a radiation
             monitoring badge)

          -  Receipt of any radiation treatments/therapy

          -  History of constipation or infrequent bowel movements (&lt;=6 bowel movements per week on
             average)

          -  Known or suspected hypersensitivity or allergic reaction to asimadoline or similar
             chemical compounds or any of the components of asimadoline tablets

          -  Chronic use of any systemic medications (with the exception of vitamins taken at
             standard supplement doses); use of a drug therapy (including herbal preparations,
             e.g., St. John's wort) known to induce or inhibit hepatic drug metabolism within 30
             days before the first dose of study medication; use of prescription medication within
             14 days before administration of study medication or over-the-counter products
             (including natural products) within 7 days before administration of study medication,
             except for topical products without systemic absorption, unless approved by the
             Sponsor

          -  Have smoked cigarettes or used nicotine-containing products over the last 3 months and
             not able to abstain from smoking for the duration of the confinement period

          -  If not sterile, cannot agree to use one of the following approved methods of
             contraception, from check-in until 3 months following Study Completion/Clinic
             Discharge: a male condom with spermicide; a sterile sexual partner; use by a female
             sexual partner of an intrauterine device with spermicide; a female condom with
             spermicide; contraceptive sponge with spermicide; a cervical cap with spermicide; or
             oral, implantable, transdermal, or injectable contraceptives with a reliable secondary
             back-up method

          -  Current history or evidence of drug or alcohol abuse or a positive screen for
             substances of abuse or alcohol at screening or admission

          -  Positive screen for hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), hepatitis C antibody, or
             human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) antibody

          -  Receipt of an investigational product or device, or participation in a drug research
             study within a period of 30 days (or 5 half lives of the drug, whichever is longer)
             before the first dose of study medication

          -  Blood loss or blood donation of &gt;550 mL within 90 days or plasma donation &gt;500 mL
             within 30 days before administration of study drug

          -  Any food allergy, intolerance, restriction, or special diet that, in the opinion of
             the Investigator, should preclude the subject's participation in this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>56 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dr. Philip Leese</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Quintiles Phase 1 Unit</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Quintiles Phase 1 Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Overland Park</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66211</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 13, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 23, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 27, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 14, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 14, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 18, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>asimadoline</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetic</keyword>
  <keyword>excretion of 14C-derived radioactivity</keyword>
  <keyword>metabolite profile</keyword>
  <keyword>14C-asimadoline</keyword>
  <keyword>metabolites</keyword>
  <keyword>single and multiple oral doses</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

