<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01382667</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SRLP06</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01382667</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Plasma Levels of Glucagon-like Peptide-2 and Dyspepsia in Patients With Extraintestinal Cancer During Chemotherapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Dyspeptic Symptoms in Oncological Frail Patients With Extraintestinal Cancer in Chemotherapy. Assessment of Circulating Levels of Glucagon-like Peptide 2 (GLP-2) in Relation to Mucositis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Azienda Ospedaliera Specializzata in Gastroenterologia Saverio de Bellis</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Azienda Ospedaliera Specializzata in Gastroenterologia Saverio de Bellis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The specific aim of the study is to investigate the relationship between the development of
      dyspepsia and GI dyspeptic symptoms in relation to circulating levels of peculiar GI peptides
      (such gastrin, pepsinogen and GLP-2) in patients with non-gastrointestinal neoplasm well
      controlled for emesis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The complications of anticancer treatment threaten the effectiveness of therapy because they
      lead to dose reduction, increase healthcare costs, and impair patients' quality of life.
      Gastrointestinal (GI) symptoms are the most frequent side effects of antineoplastic
      chemotherapy behind bone-marrow depression, with nausea and vomiting representing the mainly
      referred ones.

      Gastrointestinal (GI) mucositis, which represents injury of the rest of the alimentary tract
      beyond oral mucositis, is becoming recognized increasingly as a toxicity associated with many
      standard-dose chemotherapy regimens. Although clinicians consider them &quot;minor complaints&quot;,
      many patients (40-100%) treated with chemotherapy and/or exposed to ionizing radiation suffer
      from such a disease. After chemotherapy, GI mucositis is most prominent in the small
      intestine, but it also occurs in the esophagus, stomach, and large intestine. The GI symptoms
      related to mucositis mimic those from other GI disease (such as dyspepsia, reflux disease or
      abdominal pain and diarrhea). Alimentary tract mucositis increases morbility and mortality
      and contribute to rising health care cost.

      The comprehension of pathophysiology will shed light on the rationale for targeting specific
      pathways and so for the use of specific agents for prevention and treatment. Since the role
      of chemotherapy in the onset of GI motility disorders in addition to minor GI complaints has
      not been clarified yet. Understanding the pathophysiology of mucositis, its measures and
      scores, are essential for progress in research and care direct at this common side-effect of
      anticancer therapy. Currently, there is not strong evidence to support a recommendation for
      and against the use of certain agents (mucosal surface protectants, antiinflammatory or
      antimicrobial agents, growth factors, etc).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>GLP-2 plasma levels in cancer patients</measure>
    <time_frame>21 days</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of plasma levels of GLP-2 in patients with extraintestinal cancer before and after chemotherapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cancer associated dyspepsia syndrome, mucositis and GLP-2 plasma levels</measure>
    <time_frame>21 days</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the symptom profile related to CADS (cancer associated dyspepsia syndrome) before and after the first cycle of chemotherapy.
Assessment of possible relations between mucositis score, gastrointestinal symptom score and GLP-2 plasma levels.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Dyspepsia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GLP-2 and symptom evaluation</arm_group_label>
    <description>Before starting and at the end of the chemotherapy, along with a blood withdrawal for GLP-2 evaluation, a GSRS (gastrointestinal symptom rate scale) questionnaire will be filled by each patient to account for GI symptoms. In addition, minor complaints such as warm sensation after chemotherapy, susceptibility to nausea under specific condition, sweating and weakness will scored by visual analog score (VAS). Lastly, the NCI-CTC score for mucositis will be performed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      whole blood serum
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Twenty-five patients who had undergone surgical ablation of the primitive tumour (lung and
        breast cancer) as definitive primary treatment and attending the Oncology Day Hospital of
        our Institute,and the IRCCS Oncologico of Bari will be enrolled. They had to be scheduled
        for adjuvant therapies associated with a standard dosage of antiserotoninergic drugs
        according to ESMO recommendations
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with newly diagnosed cancer (lung and breast cancer),

          -  Patients currently free of active disease

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of cerebral edema, primary and secondary brain neoplasm with signs and
             symptoms of raised intracranial pressure and/or brain metastases,

          -  Signs of marked hepatic or renal dysfunction, cardiac failure

          -  Signs of dyspepsia, peptic ulcer, gastric surgery or prior diagnosis of other cancer

          -  Administration of drugs interfering with GI motility (i.e. antisecretory, prokinetic,
             or antibiotic drugs) as well as the exposition to radiotherapy, four weeks prior to
             the examination

          -  Referred episode of nausea of any severity within 24 h prior to antiemetic therapy, if
             they had experienced vomiting in the previous 24 h,

          -  Pregnancy or lactating

          -  Concomitant administration of agents known to have significant antiemetic activity,
             including benzodiazepines and other corticosteroids
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Caterina Clemente, ScD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Digestive Diseases IRCCS &quot;S. de Bellis&quot;</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute for Digestive Diseases IRCCS &quot;S. de Bellis&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Castellana Grotte</city>
        <state>Bari</state>
        <zip>70013</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Riezzo G, Chiloiro M, Russo F, Clemente C, Di Matteo G, Guerra V, Di Leo A. Gastric electrical activity and gastrointestinal hormones in dyspeptic patients. Digestion. 2001;63(1):20-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11173896</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Drucker DJ. Biological actions and therapeutic potential of the glucagon-like peptides. Gastroenterology. 2002 Feb;122(2):531-44. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11832466</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Riezzo G, Clemente C, Leo S, Russo F. The role of electrogastrography and gastrointestinal hormones in chemotherapy-related dyspeptic symptoms. J Gastroenterol. 2005 Dec;40(12):1107-15.</citation>
    <PMID>16378174</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peterson DE, Cariello A. Mucosal damage: a major risk factor for severe complications after cytotoxic therapy. Semin Oncol. 2004 Jun;31(3 Suppl 8):35-44. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15181607</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hesketh PJ, Van Belle S, Aapro M, Tattersall FD, Naylor RJ, Hargreaves R, Carides AD, Evans JK, Horgan KJ. Differential involvement of neurotransmitters through the time course of cisplatin-induced emesis as revealed by therapy with specific receptor antagonists. Eur J Cancer. 2003 May;39(8):1074-80.</citation>
    <PMID>12736106</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 24, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 24, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 27, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 8, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 8, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 9, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Azienda Ospedaliera Specializzata in Gastroenterologia Saverio de Bellis</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Francesco Russo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>mucositis</keyword>
  <keyword>dyspepsia</keyword>
  <keyword>chemotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>GLP-2</keyword>
  <keyword>questionnaire</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dyspepsia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glucagon</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glucagon-Like Peptide 1</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

