<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01387893</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CN-07PFren-01-H</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>02-0115-9922</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01387893</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Self-Administered Maneuver to Relieve Symptoms Suggestive of Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study of a Self-Administered Maneuver to Initiate and Maintain Urine Flow Impeded by Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kaiser Permanente</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kaiser Permanente</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study was to evaluate the effectiveness of the Digital Repetitive
      Infrapubic Pressure maneuver, a self-administered procedure used to provide symptomatic
      relief in initiating and maintaining urine flow impeded by benign prostatic hyperplasia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Eligible patients were alternately assigned to either immediate instruction on the use of the
      Digital Repetitive Infrapubic Pressure maneuver (immediate intervention group) or to a return
      appointment to receive instructions in the maneuver four weeks after the initial assessment
      date (delayed intervention group). Patients were to utilize the procedure on every occasion
      they had difficulty initiating, maintaining, or completing urine flow between the time of
      their instruction and their subsequent visit. At the initial assessment visits and the final
      visit, the patients completed an International Prostate Score Sheet (IPSS). A telephone
      survey was conducted with all patients an average of nine months following their instruction
      in the maneuver, to determine the extent to which they were still using it.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the International Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>The initial time frame was to average four weeks. There was a subsequent follow up time frame averaging nine months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary efficacy analyses compared the change over time in the IPSS scores between the immediate and the delayed intervention groups, and the changes over time between pre- and post-intervention scores for all patients completing the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Continued use of technique following intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Nine months after intial 4 week intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary efficacy analysis: The number of patients (percentage of patients completing the study) who were still employing the technique on follow-up nine months later.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate &amp; Delayed Instruction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Male patients with mild to moderate lower urinary tract symptoms will alternately be assigned to either immediate intervention or delayed intervention groups. Statistical assessments will be performed to establish comparability of baseline characteristics in the two groups.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>the Digital Repetitive Infrapubic Pressure maneuver</intervention_name>
    <description>The Digital Repetitive Infrapubic Pressure maneuver is performed by exerting moderate inwards pressure with the index and middle fingers, spread slightly apart, palm-side up, pushing into the fold of skin at the base of the penis, where it comes forward beneath the pubic bones, one fingertip on each side of the penis' suspensory ligament. By repeatedly pushing inwards and slightly upwards, at a rate of about once per second, to a distance of about two centimeters, at times of significant urinary hesitancy it is often possible either to initiate spontaneous flow, or to pass a small quantity of urine with each push, such that after a minute or two one can empty the bladder to a satisfactory degree. While a few men find it useful when voiding in a standing position, for the majority, the maneuver requires a forward-leaning seated posture for optimal results.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate &amp; Delayed Instruction</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  mild to moderate symptoms of difficulty initiating and maintaining the flow of urine

          -  not currently receiving treatment for the condition

          -  not taking an alpha-blocker at least one month before randomization

          -  not taking 5-alpha reductase inhibitor six months or more before randomization.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  non-ambulatory

          -  taking medications known to affect urination,

          -  any of the following: a debilitating concomitant illness, a history of prostate or
             bladder cancer or prostate surgery or radiation treatment to the pelvis, urethral
             stricture, neurogenic bladder, current urinary tract infection or otherwise
             potentially compromised urinary tract systems, a creatinine level of over 3.0 mg per
             deciliter, or a residual urinary volume after voiding of over 350 cubic centimeters.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Perrin L French, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kaiser Permanente Santa Clara</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kaiser Permanente</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santa Clara</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95014</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 29, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 1, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 6, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 1, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 1, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 2, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia</keyword>
  <keyword>BPH</keyword>
  <keyword>Lower Urinary Tract Symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>LUTS</keyword>
  <keyword>Self-Administered Maneuver</keyword>
  <keyword>Symptomatic Relief</keyword>
  <keyword>Digital Repetitive Infrapubic Pressure maneuver</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hyperplasia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Hyperplasia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

