<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00286546</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00286546</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Testosterone and Major Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Role of Testosterone in Major Depression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Health Network, Toronto</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Context - As men age, testosterone levels decline leading to symptoms that overlap with the
      symptoms of major depression. Little is known about the potential role of testosterone in the
      treatment of major depression.Objective - To assess the levels of bioavailable testosterone
      and total levels of testosterone in men diagnosed with major depressive disorder between the
      ages of 40 and 65.Design, Setting and Participants - 50 men between the ages of 40 and 65 and
      who suffer from major depressive disorder will be compared with 50 age matched healthy
      controls in an outpatient hospital setting. Main Outcome Measures - Bioavailable testosterone
      and total testosterone levels will be measured as well as blood pressure, pulse rate, height,
      weight, waist and hip measurements. Medical and psychiatric history will be assessed by the
      study physician. The Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI) will be used to
      administered by the physician to ensure that the patient meets the DSM-IV criteria for Major
      Depression. The Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HAM-D-17) will be used to assess depression
      symptom severity. A Symptom/Side Effect Rating Scale will also be administered to measure the
      presence and severity of side effects that each patient may be experiencing. In addition, the
      SEX FX questionnaire will be administered. Each patient will be asked to complete a series of
      self-report measures including the Social Adaptation Self-Evaluation Scale Questionnaire
      (SASS), the Androgen Deficiency in Aging Males (ADAM) and the Beck Depression Inventory
      (BDI-II).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will be carried our at the Mood Disorders Psychopharmacology Unit (MDPU),
      University Health Network (UHN), University of Toronto, with the approval of the Research
      Ethics Board (REB). Informed consent will be obtained from all subjects prior to study
      enrollment.50 male subjects between the age of 40 and 65 will be evaluated by the
      psychiatrist to assess whether each patient meets DSM-IV criteria for Major Depression using
      the MINI and to obtain their medical and psychiatric history. In addition, the SEX FX
      questionnaire (an instrument measuring sexual dysfunction) will be administered. Once each
      patient has signed the informed consent document, the research staff will assess the severity
      of depressive symptoms by administering the Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HAM-D-17). A
      Symptom/Side Effect Rating Scale will also be administered to measure the presence and
      severity of side effects that each patient may be experiencing. Each patient will then have
      pulse, blood pressure, weight, height, waist and hip measurements taken to evaluate their
      health. Patients will be asked to provide blood (about 3 teaspoons) and urine (about 1/4 cup)
      samples for laboratory tests (bioavailable testosterone, LH, thyroid and prolactin). The
      blood samples will be obtained in the morning between 0800 and 1100 hr. Each patient will
      then be asked to complete a series of self-report measures including the SASS, the ADAM, and
      the Beck Depression Inventory.The 50 healthy controls will have a structured diagnostic
      interview (MINI) administered by the coordinator to obtain their psychiatric and medical
      history. They will undergo all laboratory tests required of the depressed population and all
      rating scales mentioned above will be completed with this population as well. Each patient is
      free to withdraw from the study at any time.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date>August 2005</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Defined Population, Natural History</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional, Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>100</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depression</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Meets DSM IV criteria for a diagnosis of Major Depressive Disorder as per an
             assessment by the PREN physician-investigator.

          -  Subjects must have a Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HAM-D-17) of at least 16.

          -  Subjects must be male between the ages of 40 and 65.

          -  Subjects must be judged by the investigator to be in generally good health.

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) between 20 to 29 kg/m2.

          -  Able and willing to give meaningful written consent.

          -  Educational level and a degree of understanding such that they can communicate
             effectively with the Investigator.

          -  Subjects must have had normal sexual functioning prior to the onset of depression.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must not suffer from clinically significant medical conditions. Examples
             include neurological, cardiovascular, gastrointestinal, hepatic, renal,
             haematological, respiratory or endocrine illnesses.

          -  Recent history of drug or alcohol abuse/dependence within the past 6 months as defined
             by DSM-IV or in the opinion of the investigator.

          -  Uncorrected hypothyroidism or hyperthyroidism.

          -  Current use of hormone replacement therapy.

          -  Current diagnosis of schizophrenia or other psychotic disorder (including psychotic
             disorder due to general medical condition, substance-induced psychotic disorder,
             psychotic disorder not otherwise specified) as defined in the DSM-IV.

          -  Current diagnosis of depressive disorder not otherwise specified or bipolar I
             disorder, most recent episode major depression mixed or manic bipolar II disorder as
             defined in the DSM-IV.

          -  Electroconvulsive therapy (ECT) within the 3 months prior to visit 1.

          -  Not currently on any antidepressants or must have an interval of the following prior
             to entry into the study: Fluoxetine-4 weeks; MAOIs- 2 weeks

          -  All other psychotic medications and herbal preparations with putative antidepressant
             properties (e.g. paroxetine HCI, other antidepressant not specified above, St. John's
             Wort, kava-kava or Valerian: 1 week)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Roger McIntyre, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Health Network, University of Toronto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Roger McIntyre</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UHN Toronto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toronto Western Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5T 2S8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2005</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 1, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 1, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 3, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 8, 2006</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 8, 2006</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 11, 2006</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Testosterone</keyword>
  <keyword>Major Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Men</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Testosterone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone enanthate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone undecanoate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone 17 beta-cypionate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methyltestosterone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

