<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00281489</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>04-1112</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00281489</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study Evaluating Ways of Preventing Patients From Being Awake During High-Risk Surgery and Anesthesia</brief_title>
  <official_title>B-Unaware Study: Comparison of BIS-guided Anesthesia With End-Tidal Volatile-Guided Anesthesia to Decrease The Incidence of Awareness During High-Risk Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Barnes-Jewish Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall purpose of this study is to see if a Bispectral Index (BIS) monitor, a Food and
      Drug Administration (FDA) approved brain monitoring device, will help to reduce the risk of
      patients remembering being awake during surgery. The BIS monitor may be able measure how
      asleep a patient is during surgery. Using the BIS monitor to guide anesthesia will be
      compared with using the concentration of anesthetic gas to guide anesthesia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      General anesthesia is a state of drug-induced unconsciousness, during which patients should
      neither perceive nor recall noxious stimuli. Many patients facing surgery dread the prospect
      of being awake, in pain and unable to move owing to inadequate general anesthesia. A large
      multi-center study in the USA showed that, despite modern anesthesia techniques, the overall
      incidence of awareness or conscious recall remains about 0.1-0.2%. For high-risk (for
      awareness) surgery, such as cardiac surgery, trauma surgery and obstetric surgery, the
      incidence of conscious recall approaches 1%. This can lead to extreme anxiety and even
      posttraumatic stress disorder. Several monitors, including the Bispectral Index (BIS), which
      is based on processed electroencephalographic information, have been developed in an attempt
      to monitor depth of anesthesia. A recent landmark study suggested that harnessing the
      information provided by the BIS monitor decreases the incidence of explicit recall during
      high-risk surgical procedures from almost 1% to 0.1%. The possible impact of this study is
      enormous. The American Society of Anesthesiologists and the American Association of Nurse
      Anesthetists do not currently consider neurological monitors an essential part of routine
      anesthesia care. Increasingly, members of the anesthetic community are suggesting that for
      every patient undergoing general anesthesia, especially for procedures where the risk of
      awareness is considered higher, a neurological monitor, such as the BIS monitor, should be
      routinely applied.

      Explicit recall under general anesthesia is a major concern among members of the public and
      has even been featured on the popular Oprah Winfrey Show. Several patients presenting for
      surgery at Barnes Jewish Hospital have questioned whether the anesthesia provider would be
      using a BIS monitor to &quot;prevent awareness&quot;. Excluding the cost of the BIS monitor itself, the
      cost to use BIS is $17.50 for the disposable strip. If this monitor was to be used for every
      anesthetic administered at Barnes Jewish Hospital, this might translate to an annual cost of
      about $500,000. Explicit recall, especially when patients have been aware and unable to move,
      is a serious complication that frequently precipitates posttraumatic stress disorder. If
      indeed the BIS monitor does decrease the incidence of explicit recall, this could translate
      into a cost effective and more importantly clinically imperative intervention. Currently BIS
      monitors, or similar alternatives, are not used routinely to monitor depth of general
      anesthesia at Barnes Jewish Hospital.

      However, there are several concerns regarding the studies that have been conducted using the
      BIS monitor. There have been no parameters guiding administration of anesthesia in the
      control groups. BIS data have not been collected for patients in control groups, which
      prevents retrospective analysis and assessment of the true sensitivity, specificity, positive
      and negative predictive values of the BIS recordings. Most of the studies have been funded by
      the manufacturer of the device, which introduces a potential conflict of interest and
      investigator bias. In view of the current pressure to adopt BIS monitoring or an equivalent
      into the standard of anesthesia care, it is essential to conduct a study to address some of
      the concerns. The hypothesis of this proposed study is that an anesthetic algorithm can be
      designed for high-risk surgical patients such that the incidence of awareness will be
      equivalent to or lower than that in a group where anesthesia depth is guided by the BIS
      monitor.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2005</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of explicit recall of events during the surgical and anesthetic periods.</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>1 Anesthetic concentrations &amp; BIS values in each group.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>2 Implicit memory (number).</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3 Dreaming.</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>4 One-year mortality (and &quot;anesthetic depth&quot;).</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>5 Relation of assessment to BIS value.</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6 Relation of events (e.g. movement) to BIS &amp; ETAG.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>7 Relation of EMG to BIS.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Explicit Recall of Intra-operative Events</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BIS Monitor guided algorithm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BIS guided algorithm (BIS target 40 to 60) during anesthesia. Alarms when BIS is outside this range.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Volatile anesthetic guided algorithm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Volatile anesthetic guided algorithm. Target anesthetic concentration 0.7 to 1.3 minimum alveolar concentration during anesthesia. Alarms when anesthetic concentration not in this range.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BIS Monitor guided algorithm</intervention_name>
    <description>BIS guided algorithm (BIS target 40 to 60) during anesthesia. Alarms when BIS is outside this range.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BIS Monitor guided algorithm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Volatile anesthetic guided algorithm</intervention_name>
    <description>Volatile anesthetic guided algorithm. Target anesthetic concentration 0.7 to 1.3 minimum alveolar concentration during anesthesia. Alarms when anesthetic concentration not in this range.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Volatile anesthetic guided algorithm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        MUST HAVE:

        General Anesthesia with volatile anesthetic

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS

        Major Criteria (any 1 of the following:)

          1. Medications - anticonvulsants, abuse of opiates, benzodiazepines, cocaine

          2. EF&lt;40%

          3. Prior history of awareness (recall)

          4. History of difficult intubation or anticipated difficult intubation

          5. ASA IV or V status

          6. Aortic stenosis

          7. End stage lung disease

          8. Marginal exercise tolerance not secondary to musculoskeletal dysfunction

          9. Pulmonary hypertension

         10. Daily alcohol consumption

        Minor Criteria (any 2 of the following)

          1. Beta blockers

          2. COPD

          3. Moderate exercise tolerance not secondary to musculoskeletal dysfunction

          4. Smokes ≥2 packs per day

          5. Morbid obesity BMI&gt;30 -

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Surgical procedure that prevents the use of the BIS (e.g surgery of forehead)

          2. Patient positioning prevents use of the BIS

          3. Surgery with wake-up test.

          4. Less than 18 years of age

          5. Vulnerable populations, such as those with dementia and those unable to provide
             informed consent.

          6. Stroke with residual neurological deficits
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael S Avidan, MBBCh</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Beth Burnside</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Barnes-Jewish Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>St Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Myles PS, Leslie K, McNeil J, Forbes A, Chan MT. Bispectral index monitoring to prevent awareness during anaesthesia: the B-Aware randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2004 May 29;363(9423):1757-63.</citation>
    <PMID>15172773</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 20, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 20, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 24, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 20, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 20, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 23, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael Avidan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Institute of Quality Improvement, Research &amp; Informatics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Recall</keyword>
  <keyword>Awareness</keyword>
  <keyword>BIS</keyword>
  <keyword>Anesthesia</keyword>
  <keyword>Explicit Recall</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

