<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00287365</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GCRC-2371</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCCAM 1PO1AT002620</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00287365</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Genetic Susceptibility to Ozone in Mild Asthmatic Volunteers</brief_title>
  <acronym>Glutoz</acronym>
  <official_title>Glutathione S Transferase M1 (GSTM1) Genotype Associated Susceptibility to Airway Response to Ozone in Mild Asthmatic Volunteers.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Environmental Protection Agency (EPA)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Recent reports have shown that people with asthma who have a particular gene, known as the
      GSTM1 null gene, are more susceptible to the effect of air pollutants. The purpose of this
      research study is to learn if volunteers who have asthma and have a GSTM1 null gene have
      increased response (change in lung function and increase in lung cells collected from sputum)
      compared to volunteers with asthma who have the GSTM1 sufficient gene when challenged with
      0.4 ppm ozone during intermittent exercise. The principal purpose of this study is to
      identify hyper-responsive, responsive and non-responsive groups of human subjects with mild
      asthma based on their airway neutrophilic response to ozone exposure, and to perform analyses
      on DNA from airway cells to explore possible differences in genetic profiles between the
      three groups. An additional pilot aim is to compare expression of a small number of specific
      genes of interest in a subset of ozone-responsive and ozone-non-responsive subjects with mild
      asthma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Fifty volunteers with mild asthma will be recruited to undergo ozone challenge in the
      controlled exposure facility of the US EPA Human Studies Division (104 Mason Farm Road,
      Chapel Hill, NC) with 0.4ppm for 2 hours with moderate exercise alternating with rest.
      Endpoints will include genetic analysis for the GSTM1 genotype, sputum and spirometry changes
      pre and post exposure, and blood endpoints pre and post exposure.

      TRAINING DAY: (at least 3 days prior to the ozone challenge) Eligible subjects will report to
      the research lab for a 3 hour training session.

        -  All female volunteers will undergo a urine pregnancy test.

        -  After informed consent is obtained, Measurement of orally exhaled nitric oxide will be
           obtained

        -  Subjects will perform spirometry.

        -  Subjects will exercise on a treadmill to determine the workload for the actual exposure.

        -  Finally the subject will undergo sputum induction following pretreatment with albuterol.

      The sputum will be assessed for quality to determine continued eligibility. If a subject has
      provided an acceptable sputum sample within the prior 6 months this may be used as inclusion
      criteria rather than repeating the induction at this point. After subjects have demonstrated
      production of an adequate sputum sample, they will be scheduled for the ozone exposure visit.

      24 HOURS PRIOR to the exposure day (Day 1): Subjects will be asked to refrain from smoking as
      well as drinking alcohol for 24 hours prior to Day 1 until after completion of Day 3.

        -  Subjects will have vital signs and oxygen saturation checked, including the symptom
           questionnaire.

        -  They will also undergo a physical examination of the ears, nose, throat and chest (lung
           sounds).

        -  Female volunteers will undergo urine pregnancy testing.

        -  Measurement of orally exhaled nitric oxide will be obtained.

        -  Spirometry testing will be performed.

        -  Subjects will have a sputum induction preceded by administration of 2 puffs of
           albuterol.

      EXPOSURE DAY (at least 3 days after the training day):

        -  Subjects will be asked to arrive at the study site at approximately 8 AM and will
           undergo assessment of vital signs (temperature, pulse, respiratory rate, blood
           pressure), oxygen saturation, and symptom score assessment.

        -  A telemetry unit will be placed for cardiac monitoring during the exposure.

        -  Measurement of orally exhaled nitric oxide will be obtained prior to exposure and 4
           hours after the end of the exposure

        -  Spirometry testing to rule out acute illness prior to the exposure.

        -  They will also undergo a physical examination of the ears, nose, throat and chest.

        -  Exposure sessions: The 0.4 ppm ozone exposure will be conducted in an ozone exposure
           chamber. Each subject will be exposed to 0.4 ppm ozone for 2 hours. During exposures,
           subjects will perform four 15 minute bouts of moderate exercise (minute ventilation or
           VE = 30 40 L/min) on a treadmill, each separated by 15 minutes of seated rest. Minute
           ventilation is measured for 2 to 3 minutes after about 4 minutes of exercise during the
           first exercise period, and again at about 12 minutes of exercise. It is then measured at
           about 12 minutes into each exercise period. Two subjects may be exposed simultaneously,
           in which case the exercise/rest periods will be alternated.

        -  Immediately post exposure and 4 hours after completion of exposure, subjects will have
           an assessment of vital signs, oxygen saturation, symptom score assessment and undergo
           spirometry evaluation.

        -  Venipuncture: 20 ml of blood will be collected for a CBC/ differential, assessment of
           blood monocyte phagocytic function and cell surface markers just prior to the exposure
           and 4 hours after the end of exposure. A portion of the sample will be used for
           genotyping.

        -  Induced sputum will be collected 6 hours after initiation of exposure after subjects
           have been premedicated with albuterol. The subjects will be observed at the study site
           until sputum induction is complete. Subjects will not be discharged home following the
           post-exposure sputum induction until FEV1 is within 90% of baseline values and vital
           signs are normal. Subjects not meeting safety criteria at the end of the exposure day
           will be admitted to the GCRC for overnight observation.

           24 HOURS POST EXPOSURE (Day 3): The following morning, approximately 24 hours after
           exposure, the volunteer subject will be assessed directly at the study site. The subject
           will undergo spirometry, vital sign monitoring and symptom scoring.

      STUDY DISCONTINUATION VISIT (5-10 days after exposure): The volunteer subject will again be
      assessed directly at the study site. The subject will undergo spirometry, vital sign
      monitoring and symptom scoring.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post Ozone Change in Lung Function (FEV1) Between Subjects With GSTM1 Null Genotype Compared to GSTM1 Sufficient Subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours post exposure</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary Endpoints Include Post Ozone Airway PMN Influx Between Subjects With GSTM1 Null Genotype Compared to GSTM1 Sufficient Subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours post exposure</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>% Decrease in FVC in Asthmatics Between Subjects With GSTM1 Null Genotype Compared to GSTM1 Sufficient Subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours post exposure</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Mild Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1-ozone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Mildly asthmatic subjects with GSTM1 null genotype compared to GSTM1 sufficient subjects</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ozone</intervention_name>
    <description>2 hour exposure to 0.4 ppm ozone</description>
    <arm_group_label>1-ozone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>O3</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  healthy volunteers with mild asthma

          -  Normal lung function,

          -  Oxygen saturation of &gt; 94 %

          -  Normal blood pressure

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A history of significant chronic illnesses

          -  Allergy to any medications which may be used or prescribed in the course of this study
             (albuterol, acetaminophen, aspirin or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents,
             corticosteroids, lactose, polyethylene glycol)

          -  Positive pregnancy test within 48 hours of the time of challenge

          -  Subjects currently taking medications which may impact the results of the ozone
             challenge, interfere with any other medications potentially used in the study (to
             include steroids, beta antagonists, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents) or suggest
             an ongoing illness (such as antibiotics).

          -  Mega doses of vitamins and supplements, homeopathic/naturopathic medicines

          -  Any acute, non-chronic, medical conditions occurring in the prior two weeks. Such
             illnesses must be totally resolved symptomatically for 2 weeks and documentation of
             normal lung function must be obtained.

          -  Unspecified illnesses, which in the judgment of the investigator might increase the
             risk associated with ozone inhalation challenge, will be a basis for exclusion.

          -  Physician directed emergency treatment for an asthma exacerbation within the preceding
             12 months.

          -  Use of systemic steroid therapy within the preceding 12 months.

          -  &gt; 0.5 pack year history of tobacco use

          -  Use of inhaled steroids, cromolyn or leukotriene inhibitors initiated within the past
             month (except for use of cromolyn exclusively prior to exercise). Patients must be on
             a stable regimen of therapy.

          -  Use of daily theophylline within the past month.

          -  Pregnancy or nursing a baby.

          -  Nighttime symptoms of cough or wheeze greater than 1x/week at baseline (not during a
             clearly recognized viral induced asthma exacerbation) which would be characteristic of
             a person of moderate or severe persistent asthma as outlined in the current NHLBI
             guidelines for diagnosis and management of asthma.

          -  Exacerbation of asthma more than 2x/week which would be characteristic of a person
             with moderate or severe persistent asthma as outlined in the current NHLBI guidelines
             for diagnosis and management of asthma.

          -  Daily requirement for albuterol due to asthma symptoms (cough, wheeze, chest
             tightness) which would be characteristic of a person of moderate or severe persistent
             asthma as outlined in the current NHLBI guidelines for diagnosis and management of
             asthma. (Not to include prophylactic use of albuterol prior to exercise).

          -  Dosing level of an inhaled steroid must be consistent with mild episodic asthma as
             outlined by the NHLBI NAEPP guidelines. Use of inhaled steroid at doses typically used
             for moderate or severe asthma will result in exclusion of that individual from the
             protocol.

          -  Students or staff members who work directly for the PI, Dr David Peden, are excluded
             from study participation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David B. Peden, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of NC Center for Environmental Medicine, Asthma and Lung Biology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Environmental Medicine, Asthma and Lung Biology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.med.unc.edu/cemalb/</url>
    <description>UNC Center for Environmental Medicine, Asthma and Lung Biology</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 3, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 3, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 6, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>February 15, 2017</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>May 12, 2017</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2017</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 12, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 12, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 13, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease Susceptibility</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <pre_assignment_details>None. All subjects who successfully screened were enrolled.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Mildly Asthmatic Subjects With GSTM1 Null Genotype Compared to</title>
          <description>Mildly asthmatic subjects with GSTM1 null genotype compared to GSTM1 sufficient subjects
ozone: 2 hour exposure to 0.4 ppm ozone</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="25"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="12"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="13"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>sample not acquired</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="13"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <population>Analysis population only includes those who could produce sputum after ozone challenge. 2 of the original 25 volunteers did not produce adequate sputum</population>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Mildly Asthmatic Subjects With GSTM1 Null Genotype Compared to</title>
          <description>Mildly asthmatic subjects with GSTM1 null genotype compared to GSTM1 sufficient subjects
ozone: 2 hour exposure to 0.4 ppm ozone</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="12"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="25" lower_limit="18" upper_limit="50"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <population>2 subjects had insufficient sputum post exposure for analysis.</population>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Post Ozone Change in Lung Function (FEV1) Between Subjects With GSTM1 Null Genotype Compared to GSTM1 Sufficient Subjects</title>
        <time_frame>6 hours post exposure</time_frame>
        <population>Mild asthmatics exposed to ozone</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>GSTM1 Null</title>
            <description>GSTM1 null mild asthmatics</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>GSTM1 Sufficient</title>
            <description>GSTM1 sufficient mild asthmatics</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Post Ozone Change in Lung Function (FEV1) Between Subjects With GSTM1 Null Genotype Compared to GSTM1 Sufficient Subjects</title>
          <population>Mild asthmatics exposed to ozone</population>
          <units>percentage of FEV1 predicted</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Error</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="4"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="8"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="85" spread="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="79" spread="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Secondary Endpoints Include Post Ozone Airway PMN Influx Between Subjects With GSTM1 Null Genotype Compared to GSTM1 Sufficient Subjects</title>
        <time_frame>6 hours post exposure</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>GSTM1 Null</title>
            <description>GSTM1 null mild asthmatics</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>GSTM1 Sufficient</title>
            <description>GSTM1 sufficient mild asthmatics</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Secondary Endpoints Include Post Ozone Airway PMN Influx Between Subjects With GSTM1 Null Genotype Compared to GSTM1 Sufficient Subjects</title>
          <units>percentage of cells</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Error</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="4"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="8"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="4" spread="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="8" spread="16"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>% Decrease in FVC in Asthmatics Between Subjects With GSTM1 Null Genotype Compared to GSTM1 Sufficient Subjects</title>
        <time_frame>6 hours post exposure</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>GSTM1 Null</title>
            <description>GSTM1 null mild asthmatics</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>GSTM1 Sufficient</title>
            <description>GSTM1 sufficient mild asthmatics</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>% Decrease in FVC in Asthmatics Between Subjects With GSTM1 Null Genotype Compared to GSTM1 Sufficient Subjects</title>
          <units>percentage of FVC predicted</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Error</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="4"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="8"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="93" spread="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="85" spread="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Mildly Asthmatic Subjects With GSTM1 Null Genotype Compared to</title>
          <description>Mildly asthmatic subjects with GSTM1 null genotype compared to GSTM1 sufficient subjects
ozone: 2 hour exposure to 0.4 ppm ozone</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="25"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="25"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>decreased FEV1</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="25"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>sore throat</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="25"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>David B. Peden, MD, MS</name_or_title>
      <organization>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</organization>
      <phone>919-966-0768</phone>
      <email>dpeden@med.unc.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

