<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01570296</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCC-11-03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01570296</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Trial of Gefitinib in Combination With BKM120 in Patients With Advanced Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer, With Enrichment for Patients Whose Tumours Harbour Molecular Alterations of PI3K Pathway and Known to Overexpress EGFR</brief_title>
  <acronym>BKM120</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase Ib Trial of Gefitinib (EGFR Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor, Iressa™) in Combination With BKM120, an Oral Pan-class I PI3K Inhibitor in Patients With Advanced Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer, With Enrichment for Patients Whose Tumours Harbour Molecular Alterations of PI3K Pathway and Known to Overexpress EGFR</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Centre, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Centre, Singapore</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The safety, tolerability and recommended phase 2 dose (RP2D) of the combination of gefitinib
      and BKM120 will be determined.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      2.1 Primary

      • The safety, tolerability and recommended phase 2 dose (RP2D) of the combination of
      gefitinib and BKM120 will be determined.

      2.2 Secondary

        -  The pharmacokinetic (PK) profile of gefitinib in combination with BKM120 will be
           determined.

        -  The preliminary anti-tumor activity of gefitinib in combination with BKM120 will be
           determined.

        -  The pharmacodynamic target modulation effects using a hair follicle assay will be
           determined.

      2.3 Exploratory

        -  The role of circulating tumour cells as assessed by a microfluidic device will be
           analyzed and the genetic alterations implicated in lung cancer, including but not
           limited to EGFR mutations, PI3KCA mutations, PTEN loss will be characterized.

        -  The feasibility of detecting somatic mutations from plasma DNA will be ascertained.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 3, 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 22, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recommended phase 2 dose for gefitnib and BKM120 combination therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic (PK) profile of BKM120 in combination with gefitinib.</measure>
    <time_frame>22 time points up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preliminary antitumor activity</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Using radiological imaging and RECIST criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">38</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Solid Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gefitinib and BKM120</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with NSCLC who progress on treatment with single-agent EGFR TKI (e.g., gefitinib or erlotinib), and meet the clinical definition of EGFR TKI resistance (Jackman et al., 2010):
A tumour that harbours an EGFR mutation known to be associated with drug sensitivity
Previous objective clinical benefit from treatment with an EGFR TKI
Patients should have systemic progression of disease (by RECIST) while on continuous treatment with gefitinib or erlotinib. Patients that have previously progressed on EGFR TKI (not in the preceding line of treatment) may also be enrolled and will receive gefitinib and BKM120 sequentially.
Patients with any solid tumour-type and &quot;activated&quot; PI3 kinase pathway and historically known to over express EGFR may also be recruited.
Once the RP2D is reached, an expansion cohort of 40 patients will be accrued for extended safety experience and to ascertain preliminary activity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gefitinib and BKM120</intervention_name>
    <description>Dose escalation study of gefitinib and BKM120 with expansion cohort</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gefitinib and BKM120</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Two patient groups are eligible for enrolment. Either:

               -  Patients with histologically or cytologically proven NSCLC who meet the clinical
                  definition of EGFR TKI resistance, and are progressing on existing treatment or
                  have previously progressed on EGFR TKI (Patient Group 1 &quot;EGFR TKI Resistant&quot;)

               -  Enrichment Cohort (Patient Group 2 &quot;Pathway Driven Group&quot;) Activated PI3K status
                  (Section 7.1) in patients whose tumours are known historically to overexpress
                  EGFR. Patients permitted in this group are those in whom no standard treatment
                  options are available.

          2. Age &lt;/= 21 years

          3. WHO performance status &lt;/= 2

          4. Patients must have at least one site of measurable disease [only in dose expansion
             phase] (per RECIST for solid tumors or the appropriate disease classification/criteria
             for the target population)

          5. Life expectancy of &lt;/= 12 weeks

          6. Adequate bone marrow function as shown by: ANC 1.0 x 109/L, Platelets 100 x 109/L, Hb
             &gt;9 g/dL

          7. Adequate coagulation profile with INR &lt; 2

          8. Total calcium (corrected for serum albumin) within normal limits (bisphosphonate use
             for malignant hypercalcemia control is not allowed)

          9. Magnesium &gt; the lower limit of normal

         10. Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspirate aminotransferase (AST) within normal range
             (or 3.0 ULN if liver metastases are present)

         11. Serum bilirubin within normal range ( or 1.5 x ULN if liver metastases are present; or
             total bilirubin 3.0 x ULN with direct bilirubin within normal range in patients with
             well documented Gilbert Syndrome

         12. Serum creatinine 1.5 x ULN or 24-hour clearance 50 mL/min

         13. Serum amylase &lt; ULN

         14. Serum lipase &lt; ULN

         15. Fasting plasma glucose &lt; 120 mg/dL (6.7 mmol/L)

         16. Negative serum pregnancy test within 48 hours before starting study treatment in women
             with childbearing potential

         17. Signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who have received prior treatment with a PI3K inhibitor.

          2. Patients with a known hypersensitivity to BKM120 or to its excipients

          3. Patients with symptomatic brain metastases are excluded. However, patients with
             metastatic CNS tumors that are controlled and asymptomatic may participate in this
             trial, if the patient is &gt; 4 weeks from therapy completion (incl. radiation and/or
             surgery), or is clinically stable at the time of study entry and is not receiving
             chronic corticosteroid therapy for CNS metastases

          4. Patients with acute or chronic liver, renal disease or pancreatitis

          5. Patients with the following mood disorders as judged by the Investigator or a
             psychiatrist, or as result of patient's mood assessment questionnaire:

             i. medically documented history of or active major depressive episode, bipolar
             disorder (I or II), obsessive-compulsive disorder, schizophrenia, a history of
             suicidal attempt or ideation, or homicidal ideation (immediate risk of doing harm to
             others) ii. CTCAE grade 3 anxiety iii. meets the cut-off score of 10 in the PHQ-9 or a
             cut-off of 15 in the GAD-7 mood scale, respectively, will be excluded from the study
             unless overruled by the psychiatric assessment. iv. selects a positive response of '1,
             2, or 3' to question number 9 regarding potential for suicidal thoughts ideation in
             the PHQ-9 (independent of the total score of the PHQ-9) Note: The psychiatric judgment
             overrules the mood assessment questionnaire result/investigators judgment.

          6. Patients with diarrhea &lt; CTCAE grade 2

          7. Any of the following concurrent severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions which
             could compromise participation in the study: i. ST depression or elevation of &lt; 1.5 mm
             in 2 or more leads ii. Congenital long QT syndrome iii. History or presence of
             ventricular arrhythmias or atrial fibrillation iv. Clinically significant resting
             bradycardia (&lt; 50 beats per minutes) v. QTc &gt; 480 msec on screening ECG vi. Complete
             left bundle branch block vii. Right bundle branch block + left anterior hemiblock
             (bifascicular block) viii. Unstable angina pectoris &lt; 6 months prior to starting study
             drug ix. Acute myocardial infarction &lt; 6 months prior to starting study drug x. Other
             clinically significant heart disease such as congestive heart failure requiring
             treatment (NYHA Class III or IV) or uncontrolled hypertension (please refer to WHO-ISH
             guidelines)

          8. Patients with uncontrolled diabetes mellitus or steroid-induced diabetes mellitus

          9. Other concurrent severe and/or uncontrolled concomitant medical conditions (e.g.,
             active or uncontrolled infection) that could cause unacceptable safety risks or
             compromise compliance with the protocol

         10. Impairment of gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may significantly
             alter the absorption of BKM120 (e.g., ulcerative diseases, uncontrolled nausea,
             vomiting, diarrhea, malabsorption syndrome, or small bowel resection). Patients with
             unresolved diarrhea will be excluded as previously indicated

         11. Patients who have been treated with any hematopoietic colony-stimulating growth
             factors (e.g., G-CSF, GM-CSF) 2 weeks prior to starting study drug. Erythropoietin or
             darbepoetin therapy, if initiated at least 2 weeks prior to enrollment, may be
             continued

         12. Patients who are currently receiving treatment with medication that has the potential
             to prolong the QT interval or inducing Torsades de Pointes and the treatment cannot
             either be discontinued or switched to a different medication prior to starting study
             drug

         13. Patients who have received corticosteroids 2 weeks prior to starting study drug.
             Topical and systemic corticosteroids should not be administered with BKM120

         14. Patients receiving chronic treatment with steroids or another immunosuppressive agent.

         15. Patients who are currently treated with drugs known to be moderate and strong
             inhibitors or inducers of isoenzyme CYP3A, and the treatment cannot be discontinued or
             switched to a different medication prior to starting study drug. Please refer to Table
             3-5 for a list of moderate to strong inhibitors of CYP3A4 (Please note that
             co-treatment with weak inhibitors of CYP3A4 is allowed).

         16. Patients who have received chemotherapy or targeted anticancer therapy 4 weeks (6
             weeks for nitrosourea, antibodies or mitomycin-C) prior to starting study drug or who
             have not recovered from side effects of such therapy

         17. Patients who have received any continuous or intermittent small molecule therapeutics
             (excluding monoclonal antibodies) or 5 effective half lives prior to starting study
             drug or who have not recovered from side effects of such therapy

         18. Patients who have received wide field radiotherapy 4 weeks or limited field radiation
             for palliation 2 weeks prior to starting study drug or who have not recovered from
             side effects of such therapy

         19. Patients who have undergone major surgery 4 weeks prior to starting study drug or who
             have not recovered from side effects of such therapy

         20. Patients who are currently taking therapeutic doses of warfarin sodium or any other
             coumadin-derivative anticoagulant.

         21. Women who are pregnant or breast feeding or adults of reproductive potential not
             employing an effective method of birth control. Double barrier contraceptives must be
             used through the trial by both sexes. Oral, implantable, or injectable contraceptives
             may be affected by cytochrome P450 interactions, and are therefore not considered
             effective for this study. Women of child-bearing potential, defined as sexually mature
             women who have not undergone a hysterectomy or who have not been naturally
             postmenopausal for at least 12 consecutive months (i.e., who has had menses any time
             in the preceding 12 consecutive months), must have a negative serum pregnancy test &lt;
             48 hours prior to initiating treatment

         22. Known diagnosis of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection

         23. History of another malignancy within 3 years, except cured basal cell carcinoma of the
             skin or excised carcinoma in situ of the cervix

         24. Patient is unable or unwilling to abide by the study protocol or cooperate fully with
             the investigator
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel SW Tan, BSc, MRCP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Early Clinical Research Unit, Medical Oncology, National Cancer Centre Singapore</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Centre Singapore</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>169610</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 27, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 3, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 4, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Advanced Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>tumors harbor molecular</keyword>
  <keyword>alterations of PI3K pathway</keyword>
  <keyword>known to overexpress EGFR</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gefitinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

