<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01571934</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00046800</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5K23HL105785</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>PASs</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01571934</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Inhibitor Development in Patients With Hemophilia A Undergoing Surgery</brief_title>
  <acronym>PASs</acronym>
  <official_title>Inhibitor Development in Patients With Hemophilia A Undergoing Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hemophilia A is a genetic deficiency of factor VIII that causes blood to clot too slowly. The
      disease is classified based on how much factor VIII is in the blood. People with mild or
      moderate hemophilia A have low, but detectable, blood levels of factor VIII and bleed with
      trauma or surgery. At the time of surgery, they need to receive factor VIII replacement by
      infusion into the vein so that blood can clot normally and abnormal bleeding can be avoided.
      A complication of hemophilia A is the development of an antibody that binds factor VIII and
      makes the factor VIII infused for treatment not work properly. This antibody is called an
      inhibitor. In mild and moderate hemophilia A, inhibitors are not common, but have been
      reported to occur after intensive factor VIII infusions, as may occur at the time of surgery.
      This study is designed to observe people with mild and moderate hemophilia A who are having
      surgery. Information on the surgery, treatments given, bleeding, and infection will be
      gathered. Also, blood will be drawn to determine how the immune system is reacting to the
      factor VIII. No specific treatments will be given as part of this study. We will use the
      information to determine what influences inhibitor development. A better understanding of
      inhibitor development will help medical providers do things to avoid inhibitor development in
      this population or researchers to design new treatments.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The development of neutralizing anti-factor VIII (fVIII) antibodies, fVIII inhibitor, is the
      most significant complication affecting patients with hemophilia A (HA). Once an inhibitor
      develops, treatment is less effective and costly. Although inhibitors occur most commonly in
      those with severe HA, 25% of new inhibitors occur in those with non-severe HA. In patients
      with non-severe HA, the development of a fVIII inhibitor can change the course of disease
      from one that is easily managed to one with the potential for spontaneous life-threatening
      difficult to treat bleeding. Although significant advances have been made in understanding
      risk factors for fVIII inhibitor development in patients with severe HA, studies that seek to
      understand the risk for fVIII inhibitor development in those with non-severe disease have
      been limited to retrospective analyses. In these retrospective analyses, intensive fVIII
      treatment and surgery have been identified as risk factors for fVIII inhibitor development in
      non-severe HA. Additionally, receiving fVIII by continuous infusion has been associated with
      fVIII inhibitor development in non-severe HA in some but not all studies and may be due in
      part to a more robust proinflammatory response during continuous infusion. Accordingly, the
      next logical step to evaluate the risk of inhibitor development associated with continuous
      fVIII infusion is a prospective observational cohort study. Additionally, knowledge of the
      immune response to fVIII in the surgical setting is essential for identification of patients
      at high risk for inhibitor development and development of strategies to prevent inhibitor
      development and is best evaluated in the setting of an prospective cohort study.

      This multicenter prospective observational cohort study will enroll a total of 140 subjects
      at 10 centers who have mild or moderate hemophilia a (fVIII activity 1-40%) who are scheduled
      to undergo surgery for which at least 5 consecutive days of fVIII replacement therapy is
      required. The study will gather clinical data and collect blood specimens on 4 occasions over
      a 3 month period. Outcomes include: inhibitor development, total fVIII usage, bleeding, and
      markers of T cell activation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Inhibitor development (inhibitor titer &gt; 0.4 BU/ml)</measure>
    <time_frame>postopereratvie date 90</time_frame>
    <description>Primary Study Endpoint: Inhibitor development (inhibitor titer &gt; 0.4 BU/ml) by post-operative (POD) day 90. Three months or 90 days was selected as the primary end point based on data collected in the case-control study where 17/18 cases had developed their inhibitor within 12 weeks of their intensive fVIII treatment and only 1 case developed the inhibitor &gt;16 weeks after the intensive fVIII treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Hemophilia A</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mild or moderate hemophilia A</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects with mild or moderate hemophilia A (fVIII activity 1-40%) who are scheduled to undergo surgery for which at least 5 consecutive days of fVIII replacement therapy is required.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood drawn during study includes 15 ml within 7 days prior to surgery and 15 ml drawn on
      post-operative days 1, 14 and 90.

      Samples for DNA storage will be generated from blood draw study samples.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        In addition to Emory University, subjects will be recruited at one of 8 following sites:
        University of Pittsburgh, University of North Carolina, Oregon Health and Science
        University, University of Colorado, University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston,
        University of Minnesota, and Indiana Hemophilia Treatment Center.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males with mild/moderate hemophilia A (fVIII activity 1-40%)

          -  Planned surgical intervention which is anticipated to require 5 consecutive days of
             fVIII replacement therapy (These can be outpatient or inpatient treatment days.)

          -  Weight &gt;22.5 kg (To assure that volumes of blood to be drawn for study purposes are
             safe.)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Past history of an inhibitor (inhibitor titer &gt;0.4 BU/ml)

          -  HIV infection with CD4 count &lt;400/ul

          -  Currently receiving immunosuppressive medication(s)

          -  Unable to tolerate quantity of blood to be drawn

          -  Current or past diagnosis autoimmune disorder

          -  Current or past diagnosis of immune deficiency disorder other than HIV
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christine Kempton, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado, Hemophilia and Thrombosis Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University Comprehensive Hemophilia Treatment Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana Hemophilia and Thrombosis Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46260</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599-7035</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon Health &amp; Science University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh and Hemophilia Center of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 4, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 4, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 5, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 26, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Christine Kempton, MD, MSc</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Christine Kempton, MD, MSc</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hemophilia A</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemophilia A</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Factor VIII</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

