<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01575249</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>The ENIGMAS trial</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01575249</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Identification of Parameters in rapId-proGression Subgroup Patients With Moderate Aortic Stenosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>ENIGMAS</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective Study Focused on idEntification of cliNical, Biological and Imagistic Parameters in rapId-proGression Subgroup Patients With Moderate Aortic Stenosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Carol Davila University of Medicine and Pharmacy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Carol Davila University of Medicine and Pharmacy</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators aim to identify all clinical, biological, echo and imagistic parameters
      that predispose to increased progression rates in a prospective observational trial which
      will include ONLY patients with moderate AS, with the complete cardiological investigational
      tools provided in 2012. Once those parameters are found, medical and interventional treatment
      could be implemented to decrease the mortality rates.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. Why this study? 1.1. Significance and difficulty of the problem being addressed. Aortic
           stenosis is the most encountered valvular disease According to the 2007 ESC guidelines
           (1), moderate aortic stenosis (AS) is defined as valve area 1.0-1.5 cm² (0.6 cm²/m² to
           0.9 cm²/m² body surface area (BSA)) or mean aortic gradient of 30-50 mmHg in the
           presence of normal flow conditions. We already know how to treat patients with severe
           AS, symptomatic or not. On the contrary, in patients with moderate AS there is not a
           clear agreement on what to do to reduce the excess mortality (detailed below). Why do
           these patients die and what can we do to reduce mortality rates? 1.2. Originality of the
           proposed solution and the appropriateness of the objectives. There are already some
           progression factors in all spectrum of AS that have been highlighted (discussed below)
           and which could influence mortality in this patient subgroup, but none of the studies
           address exclusively to moderate AS. The majority of these studies have major
           limitations, are not prospective, and even if some are, the parameters followed do not
           cover the complete cardiological investigational tools (no 3D left ventricular (LV)
           ejection fraction (EF), no strain, no magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), etc.). As in any
           major disease, lots of studies that include moderate AS are contradictory on the same
           matter (see progression of AS). We aim to identify all clinical, biological, echo and
           imagistic parameters that predispose to increased progression rates in a prospective
           randomized trial which will include ONLY patients with moderate AS, with the
           investigational tools provided in 2012. Once those parameters are found, medical and
           interventional treatment could be implemented to decrease the mortality rates.

           But first, some data about survival and death in moderate AS. I would like to start by
           paraphrasing one of the most passionate researchers in the field of aortic stenosis, C.
           Otto (2): &quot;even mild disease is important&quot; (referring of course at the outcomes of
           patients with mild AS). Similarly, people with moderate AS/ aortic sclerosis, not even
           mentioning moderate to severe AS (3) have an increased death rate in comparison to
           age-matched healthy population. The same author reported in 1999 the results of a
           prospective study (4) with a follow-up (FU) at 5 years and she observed a cardiac death
           rate of 6.1% in general population (normal aortic valves), 10.1% in patients with aortic
           sclerosis and 19.6% in patients with AS. In 2004 Rosenhek et al. (5) found a cardiac
           death rate of 8.7% in a population with mean age of 67 years, with moderate AS at the
           initial examination. Even though the largest study (6) evaluating medical treatment in
           moderate AS reported a cardiac death rate of 6.0% (similar to general population), we
           consider this study not eloquent because there was a super-selected population enrolled
           (investigators ruled out the most important progression factors of AS: exclusion
           criteria included history of coronary artery disease (CAD), stroke and diabetes mellitus
           (DM)).

        2. Trials involving patients with moderate AS. In this presentation we will not review or
           discuss outcomes of severe AS, but ONLY outcomes of patients with MODERATE AS.

           The first step in our research was the identification of all studies involving moderate
           AS. We observed that there are few studies that included ONLY patients with moderate AS.
           At the opposite, the large majority of studies included moderate AS among all spectrum
           of AS patients (sclerosis, mild, moderate, severe- alone or combined). That is why we
           categorized all previous studies regarding moderate AS by the baseline inclusion
           criteria. We found 4 major groups of enrolled patients that we reviewed and discussed
           below: patients with mild to moderate AS (Table 1) (5-10), patients with moderate AS
           (Table 2)(11-12), patients with mild, moderate and severe AS (Table 3)(13-20) and
           patients with moderate to severe AS (Table 4)(21-27).

           Even though all essential data regarding moderate AS can be easily read in the tables
           (patient characteristics, progression of moderate AS, outcomes, survival, limitations
           and conclusions) and even though progression factors are summed-up below, of great
           importance are the results of some echo studies recently published on which I would like
           to briefly discuss. Monin et al. enrolled 107 patients with baseline peak velocity (PV)
           of 3.5 to 4.4 m/s (26), he concluded that female sex, PV and brain natriuretic peptide
           (BNP) at baseline were correlated with AS progression and developed a score to best
           stratify outcomes in these patients (see Table 4 for limitations). Marechaux et al. (27)
           included 135 patients with at least moderate AS (53% had severe AS), with normal stress
           test at baseline. Increased progression was present in those with resting mean gradient
           (MG) &gt;35 mmHg and exercise-induced increase in MG &gt;20 mmHg (see Table 4 for
           limitations). Two studies tried to clarify the role of strain in AS. One of the studies
           showed that strain gradually decreased as severity of AS increases and that global
           longitudinal strain (GLS) might be useful to assess subtle changes in LV function in
           patients with mild, moderate and severe AS (17). In the second study, Ng et al. (19)
           found that longitudinal, radial and circumferential strain and strain rate (SR)
           deteriorate with aortic valve disease progression. Important limitations of both studies
           are found in Table 3.

        3. Progression of AS. There is a wide variability in AS progression. Progression rates (for
           the PV) begin from 0.15±0.01 m/s/y in population without cardiovascular risk factors (6)
           and increase to 0.34±0.42 m/s/y in patients with CAD, reaching 0.45±0.38 m/s/y in
           patients with cardiovascular events (5).

           High progressors are those that have at least one abnormal parameter of the followings:
           echocardiography parameters: baseline PV (3, 12, 5, 10, 16, 20, 26), baseline peak
           gradient (24), mean gradient (3), rate of increase in PV (3, 20), moderate to severe
           aortic valve calcification on echo (5, 12), LV hypertrophy (27), resting MG &gt;35 mmHg
           (27), exercise-induced increase in MG &gt;20 mmHg (27), E velocity (16), bicuspid aortic
           valve (16); clinical predictors: CAD (5, 21), age (&gt;80 years-8, 12, 18, 20, &gt;64
           years-21, &gt;65years-27), diabetes (14, 27), metabolic syndrome (MS) (24), dialysis (28,
           29), increased BMI (7), functional status (3), history of smoking (7, 30), systolic
           blood pressure (SBP) (18, 30), male gender (24, 30), female gender (26); and biological
           parameters: parathyroid hormone (PTH) level (18), BNP at baseline (26), high lipoprotein
           (a) (Lp(a)) and low density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol levels (30).

           No influence on AS progression were treatment with simvastatin and ezetimibe (6),
           elprenone (25) or rosuvastatin (9) and statins (14).

           Slower progression was observed after osteoporosis (11) and bisphosphonate treatment
           (15), but studies were either too small, retrospective (11, 15) or biased (11).
           Geographical differences are evident in two papers which show that Korean patients
           progress slower than western population (12, 16).

           Data regarding the role of C-reactive protein in AS progression are controversial (10,
           13).

           We did not discuss the old studies or small series of patients with AS, some in the era
           of cardiac catheterizations (31-36), some in the early echo decades (37-41). Their
           capability to address this subject was limited by a retrospective design in most cases,
           potential selection bias, limited clinical, functional, or exercise data, the
           availability of only two data points per patient, lack of factors that predict the rate
           of hemodynamic progression and clinical outcome.

        4. Incidence of AS. Degenerative aortic valve disease evolves slowly from aortic sclerosis
           to aortic stenosis. Aortic sclerosis and stenosis are found in about 29% and 2-9%
           respectively in adults older than 65 years (4). In 5,201 subjects &gt; 65 years, aortic
           valve sclerosis was present in 26% and AS in 2% of the entire study cohort; in subjects
           &gt;75 years of age, sclerosis was present in 37% and stenosis in 2.6% (30). The prevalence
           of critical AS was 2.9% in the group 75 to 86 years of age in another study (42). In an
           observational study (43) which enrolled 953 subjects (aged 25-74 years), the overall
           prevalence of degenerative aortic valve disease (defined as the presence of valvular
           sclerosis, calcification, or thickening on echocardiographical examination) was 28%. The
           prevalence of degenerative aortic valve disease by age groups was the following: 7%
           (35-44 years), 19% (45-54), 30% (55-64), 38% (65-74) and 64% (75-84). There were no
           significant differences between men and women.

      Clinical factors associated with AS are similar to those associated with CAD (3, 44). Even
      though several small non-randomized studies (45, 46-49) suggested a beneficial effect of
      statins, three prospective randomized studies did not find any effect of lipid-lowering
      therapy on the progression of aortic-valve stenosis.(6, 10, 50).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>occurrence of major adverse cardiac events (MACE) defined by the followings: death, aortic valve replacement (AVR) and myocardial infarction (MI).</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TIME TO SYMPTOMS (angina, dyspnea, syncope) at stress echocardiography</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TIME TO ALTERED HEMODYNAMIC PARAMETERS at stress (strain decrease, EF decrease, ventricular arrhythmia, decrease in SBP, stress gradients suggestive of severe AS)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>differentiate outcomes of patients with mean gradients between 40 and 50 mmHg (grey zone of AS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Aortic Stenosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Asymptomatic group</arm_group_label>
    <description>one hundred patients with a negative exercise stress echo for symptoms/ECG/wall motion abnormalities (WMA), negative spirometry test for pulmonary disease, without known CAD or other valvular diseases, in sinus rhythm and with a LVEF&gt;55%</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Symptomatic group</arm_group_label>
    <description>one hundred patients with symptomatic AS (negative pulmonary tests but positive stress echo or prior CAD or other valvular diseases and a LVEF&gt;55%</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      standard blood count, c-reactive protein, urea, creatinin, hepatic standard biology, serum
      calcium, cholesterol and tryglicerides.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The enrollment will be done by echo screening of the population (of the 3rd Arrondissement
        in Bucharest, Romania) with age &gt;50 years until target patients reached and also by
        screening out-patients arriving at &quot;Bagdasar-Arseni&quot; Emergency Hospital (Bucharest) with
        other cardiovascular diseases other than specified in the exclusion criteria.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age 21 years;

          -  native aortic valve leaflet thickening with reduced systolic opening on
             two-dimensional echocardiography and an aortic jet velocity at rest between 2.8 and
             3.1 m/s or a valve area calculated by the continuity equation of 1.7 to 1.5 cm2,
             evaluated at a heart rate between 60 and 90/ minute and at a systolic arterial
             pressure of 120-140mmHg at baseline;

          -  LVEF &gt; 55% (calculated by modified Simpson formula).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  positive stress test (symptoms including dyspnoea, angina, syncope, ECG pathological
             changes, WMA);

          -  positive pulmonary disease (spirometry);

          -  heart failure;

          -  LVEF &lt; 55%;

          -  moderate/severe aortic or mitral regurgitation or mitral stenosis, subvalvular or
             supravalvular AS, dynamic subaortic obstruction;

          -  CAD (history of MI or coronary artery stenosis on coronary angiography);

          -  active endocarditis;

          -  rhythm other than sinus rhythm;

          -  severe uncontrolled risk factors for CAD:

               -  uncontrolled DM,

               -  uncontrolled hypertension (SBP &gt; 180mmHg),

               -  refuse to discontinue smoking,

               -  persistent hypercholesterolemia under treatment (total cholesterol &gt; 240mg/dl);

          -  glomerular filtration rate &lt; 30% or patient requiring dialysis;

          -  patient refusal; survival expectancy &lt; 2 years;

          -  inability to perform physical exercise;

          -  suboptimal echo window;

          -  different types of echo machines.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>ALEXANDRU N MISCHIE, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>BAGDASAR ARSENI EMERGENCY HOSPITAL</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>&quot;Bagdasar-Arseni&quot; Emergency Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bucharest</city>
        <zip>041915</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>ALEXANDRU N MISCHIE, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0040723708050</phone>
      <email>alexandru_mischie@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>ALEXANDRU N MISCHIE, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>CRINA SINESCU, MD FESC FACC</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Romania</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed?term=6.%20Rosseb%C3%B8%20AB%2C%20Pedersen%20TR%2C%20Boman%20K%2C%20Brudi%20P%2C%20Chambers%20JB%2C%20Egstrup%20K%2C%20Gerdts%20E%2C%20Gohlke-B%C3%A4rwolf%20C%2C%20Holme%20I%2C%20Kes%C3%A4niemi%20YA%2C%20Malbecq%20</url>
    <description>protocol of the SEAS trial</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed?term=Usefulness%20of%20exercise-stress%20echocardiography%20for%20risk%20stratification%20of%20true%20asymptomatic%20patients%20with%20aortic%20valve%20stenosis.</url>
    <description>similar protocole to our study</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 9, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 10, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 11, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 10, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 10, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 11, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Carol Davila University of Medicine and Pharmacy</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>MISCHIE Nicolae Alexandru</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>CARDIOLOGIST, ASSISTANT PROFESSOR</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>progression</keyword>
  <keyword>moderate aortic stenosis</keyword>
  <keyword>asymptomatic</keyword>
  <keyword>symptomatic</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Constriction, Pathologic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease Progression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aortic Valve Stenosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

