<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01576250</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL38795.068.11/METC 11-3-074</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01576250</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Lowered Physical Activity on Insulin Sensitivity and Lipid and Glucose Metabolism</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Lowered Physical Activity (Induced by Lower Limb Suspension (ULLS)) on Insulin Sensitivity and Lipid and Glucose Metabolism</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Maastricht University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Maastricht University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate the effects of lowered physical activity
      (resulting in decreased muscle mitochondrial oxidative capacity) alone and together with
      increased plasma free fatty acid availability (by infusion of a clinically widely used lipid
      emulsion (Intralipid)) on insulin sensitivity and glucose and lipid metabolism. To this end,
      we will compare skeletal muscle insulin sensitivity and glucose and lipid metabolism (within
      one subject) after 9 days of immobilization of one leg (unilateral lower limb
      suspension(ULLS))(decreased muscle mitochondrial oxidative capacity) versus an active control
      leg (unchanged muscle mitochondrial oxidative capacity). Further, changes in IMCL and fatty
      acid intermediates will be investigated in the immobilized vs the control leg, and this will
      be related to insulin sensitivity. The effectiveness of the ULLS intervention will be tested
      by measuring muscle mitochondrial oxidative capacity in both the immobilized and the control
      leg. All measurements will be performed both in the immobilized and control leg after 9 days
      of ULLS.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the Netherlands and worldwide, the number of individuals suffering from obesity and type 2
      diabetes mellitus is rising steadily. It is well established that obesity predisposes
      individuals to accumulation of excessive fat in non-adipose tissues such as the liver, the
      heart and skeletal muscle (called steatosis or ectopic fat accumulation). Furthermore, in
      sedentary humans ectopic fat accumulation in skeletal muscle is strongly associated with
      insulin resistance. However, paradoxically, IntraMyoCellular Lipid (IMCL) content is also
      increased in highly insulin sensitive endurance trained subjects (known as the athlete's
      paradox). This is suggesting that IMCL per se is not causative in skeletal muscle insulin
      resistance. The increased IMCL storage following endurance training serves to match
      training-induced increase in oxidative capacity and reliance on fat as a substrate during
      exercise, whereas in obesogenic/diabetogenic conditions the high fat availability is not
      matched by improved oxidative capacity. It is therefore speculated that under the latter
      conditions, the lipid intermediates of IMCL metabolism such as diacylglycerol (DAG),
      ceramides and fatty acyl-CoAs will accumulate and impede cellular insulin signalling. The
      rate of oxidative capacity is regulated by mitochondria, which are cellular organelles
      responsible for cellular energy production and cellular metabolism. Therefore, the overall
      hypothesis of this project is that a low muscle mitochondrial oxidative capacity can lead to
      muscle fat accumulation and/or accumulation of lipid intermediates when fatty acid
      availability is high, and this may result in insulin resistance in skeletal muscle.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>after 9 days of ULLS</time_frame>
    <description>After 9 days of ULLS a muscle biopsy will be derived before and after a 5 h lipid infusion,from both the immobilized and the control leg. Insulin sensitivity will further be investigated from the skeletal muscle tissue ex vivo.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>intramyocellularlipid content</measure>
    <time_frame>after 9 days of ULLS</time_frame>
    <description>After 9 days of ULLS a muscle biopsy will be derived before and after a 5 h lipid infusion,from both the immobilized and the control leg. Muscle tissue will immediately be frozen and stored for later determination of Intramyocellular lipid content.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lipid intermediates</measure>
    <time_frame>after 9 days of ULLS</time_frame>
    <description>After 9 days of ULLS a muscle biopsy will be derived before and after a 5 h lipid infusion,from both the immobilized and the control leg. Lipid intermediates will further be investigated from the skeletal muscle tissue ex vivo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lipid metabolism</measure>
    <time_frame>after 9 days of ULLS</time_frame>
    <description>After 9 days of ULLS a muscle biopsy will be derived before and after a 5 h lipid infusion,from both the immobilized and the control leg. Lipid metabolism will further be investigated from the skeletal muscle tissue ex vivo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Glucose metabolism</measure>
    <time_frame>after 9 days of ULLS</time_frame>
    <description>After 9 days of ULLS a muscle biopsy will be derived before and after a 5 h lipid infusion,from both the immobilized and the control leg. Glucose metabolism will further be investigated from the skeletal muscle tissue ex vivo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Insulin Sensitivity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>unilateral lower limb suspension</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is an intervention study, where each subject will undergo 12 days of unilateral lower limb suspension. Randomly, the dominant or the non-dominant leg of the subject will be suspended by attachment of a sling to a non-rigid ankle brace and to a harness on the upper body and unloaded from all weight bearing. The knee will be slightly flexed at an angle of 130°. Hip, knee and ankle will be fully mobile. The sling will be used during all locomotory activity, and the subjects will use crutches for walking.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>unilateral lower limb suspension</intervention_name>
    <description>This is an intervention study, where each subject will undergo 12 days of unilateral lower limb suspension. Randomly, the dominant or the non-dominant leg of the subject will be suspended by attachment of a sling to a non-rigid ankle brace and to a harness on the upper body and unloaded from all weight bearing. The knee will be slightly flexed at an angle of 130°. Hip, knee and ankle will be fully mobile. The sling will be used during all locomotory activity, and the subjects will use crutches for walking.</description>
    <arm_group_label>unilateral lower limb suspension</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men between 18-35 years of age at time of enrolment

          -  Non smoking

          -  No recent bone fractures of the limbs

          -  No cardiovascular medication or other medication

          -  No family history of thrombosis

          -  No engagement in programmed exercise for more than two hours a week

          -  Stable dietary habits

          -  No contra-indication for MRI

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Regular smokers

          -  Participation in other studies

          -  Female sex

          -  Recent bone fractures of the limbs

          -  Medication use

          -  Cardiovascular disease

          -  Family history of type 2 diabetes mellitus

          -  Family history of thrombosis

          -  Contraindications for MRS scans:

          -  Electronic implants such as pacemakers or neurostimulator

          -  Iron-containing foreign bodies in eyes or brain

          -  Some hearing aids and artificial (heart) valves which are contraindicated for MRS

          -  Claustrophobia

          -  Participants, who do not want to be informed about unexpected medical findings, or do
             not wish that their physician will be informed, cannot participate in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patrick Schrauwen, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Maastricht University Medical Center (MUMC)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lena Bilet, MSc.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Maastricht University Medical Center (MUMC)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maastricht University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maastricht</city>
        <zip>6200 MD</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 10, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 10, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 12, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 27, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 27, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 28, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Maastricht University Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lena Bilet</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD student</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin Resistance</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Insulin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

