<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01571167</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-26875</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>DPMC</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01DA027134-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01571167</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Varenicline as a Treatment for Methamphetamine Dependence</brief_title>
  <acronym>Varenicline</acronym>
  <official_title>A Human Laboratory Assessment of the Safety and Potential Efficacy of Varenicline in Methamphetamine-Dependent Volunteers Receiving Methamphetamine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baylor College of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of the study is to determine the effects of treatment with varenicline (1
      and 2 mg daily), compared to treatment with placebo, on methamphetamine-induced craving and
      subjective effects in methamphetamine-dependent human volunteers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is part of an effort to develop treatments for methamphetamine abuse. Varenicline
      is a drug that changes levels of certain brain chemicals that may also be useful in helping
      people to stop using methamphetamine. Our goal is to determine the safety and effects of
      varenicline (1 and 2 mg, daily, vs. a placebo) when it is used before experimental
      administration of methamphetamine, on a number of physical and psychological measures;
      specifically blood pressure, heart rate, and how you feel after taking methamphetamine. The
      secondary purpose is to determine the effects of treatment with varenicline (1 and 2 mg
      daily), compared to treatment with placebo, on the reinforcing effects of methamphetamine by
      measuring methamphetamine self-administration in methamphetamine-dependent human volunteers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The effects of varenicline and methamphetamine on safety and cardiovascular measures</measure>
    <time_frame>On study day 6 and 7</time_frame>
    <description>The safety of MA administration during treatment will be assessed by reporting of adverse events (AEs), and using ECG recording, and heart rate and blood pressure measurements. Digital 12-lead ECG will also be recorded prior to randomization. Blood pressure and heart rate will be measured from 15 min prior to MA or placebo dosing until 2 h after dosing. In addition, heart rate and blood pressure will be assessed throughout the inpatient portion of the protocol.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effects of varenicline and methamphetamine on subjective effects</measure>
    <time_frame>On study day 6 and 7</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy will be assessed by measuring effects of treatment on subjective effects produced by administration of MA. Patients will complete visual analog scale (VAS) ratings at T= 5, 15, 30, 60, 120, 240 and 360 min post dosing. Other diagnostic measures and assessment instruments will be used to further characterize the study population.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">17</enrollment>
  <condition>Methamphetamine Dependence</condition>
  <condition>Methamphetamine Abuse</condition>
  <condition>Substance Abuse</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Varenicline 2 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Varenicline 1 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive varenicline or matched placebo from day 1 through day 7, then the same subjects will return within 2-4 weeks and assigned to each of the two remaining study medication conditions, and undergo the identical procedures (3-phase study).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sugar pill</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Varenicline</intervention_name>
    <description>For varenicline 1 mg, dosing will begin at 0.5 mg once daily (with 0 mg placebo to maintain blind of bid dosing) for days 1-3, will be increased to 0.5 mg twice daily for the days 4-6, and then reduced to 0.5 mg once daily on day 7. No medication is given on Day 8.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Varenicline 1 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Chantix</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Varenicline</intervention_name>
    <description>For varenicline 2 mg, dosing will begin at 0.5 mg once daily for days 1-3 (with 0 mg placebo to maintain blind of bid dosing), will be increased to 0.5 mg twice daily for day 4, and increased to 1 mg twice daily on days 5-6, and then reduced to 1 mg once daily on day 7. No medication is given on Day 8.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Varenicline 2 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Chantix</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        In order to participate in the study, participants must:

          1. Be English-speaking volunteers who are not seeking treatment at the time of the study

          2. Be between 18-55 years of age

          3. Meet DSM-IV TR criteria for MA dependence

          4. Must be cigarette smokers, defined as smoking 10 or more cigarettes per day by
             self-report

          5. Have a self-reported history of using MA by the smoked or IV route and provide at
             least one MA-positive urine prior to admission

          6. Have vital signs as follows: resting pulse between 50 and 90 bpm, blood pressures
             between 105-150 mm Hg systolic and 45-90 mm Hg diastolic; this criterion must be met
             within 2 days of admission

          7. Have hematology and chemistry laboratory tests that are within normal (+/- 10%) limits
             with the following exceptions: a) liver function tests (total bilirubin, ALT, AST, and
             alkaline phosphatase) &lt; 3 x the upper limit of normal, and b) kidney function tests
             (creatinine and BUN) &lt; 2 x the upper limit of normal

          8. Have a baseline EKG that demonstrates normal sinus rhythm, normal conduction
             (including QTc), and no clinically significant arrhythmias

          9. Have a medical history and brief physical examination demonstrating no clinically
             significant contraindications for study participation, in the judgment of the
             admitting physician or nurse practitioner and the principal investigator.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects will be excluded if they:

          1. Have any previous medically adverse reaction to METH, including loss of consciousness,
             chest pain, or epileptic seizure

          2. Have neurological or psychiatric disorders, as assessed by MINI, such as: episode of
             major depression within the past 2 years; lifetime history of schizophrenia, other
             psychotic illness, or bipolar illness; current organic brain disease or dementia
             assessed by clinical interview; history of or any current psychiatric disorder which
             would require ongoing treatment or which would make study compliance difficult;
             history of suicide attempts within the past three months and/or current suicidal
             ideation/plan; history of psychosis occurring in the absence of current METH use

          3. Meet DSM-IV criteria for abuse/dependence on alcohol or other drugs, except nicotine
             or marijuana

          4. Have used methamphetamine only by the intravenous route

          5. Have evidence of clinically significant heart disease or hypertension, as determined
             by physician

          6. Have evidence of untreated or unstable medical illness including: neuroendocrine,
             autoimmune, renal, hepatic, or active infectious disease

          7. Have HIV and currently symptomatic, have a diagnosis of AIDS, or currently taking
             antiretroviral medication

          8. Be pregnant or nursing. Other females must either be unable to conceive (i.e.,
             surgically sterilized, sterile, or post-menopausal) or be using a reliable form of
             contraception (e.g., abstinence, birth control pills, intrauterine device, condoms, or
             spermicide). All females must provide negative pregnancy urine tests before study
             entry, and throughout the study

          9. Have any history of asthma, chronic coughing and wheezing, or other chronic
             respiratory illnesses

         10. Currently use alpha or beta agonists, theophylline, or other sympathomimetics

         11. Have made a suicide attempt in the past year

         12. Have any other illness, condition, or use of medications, which in the opinion of the
             PI and/or the admitting physician would preclude safe and/or successful completion of
             study.

        Criteria for Discontinuation Following Initiation:

          1. Positive urine drug screen or breath test indicating illicit use of cocaine, MA,
             alcohol, opiates, or other abused drugs not delivered as part of this protocol

          2. Inability to comply with study procedures

          3. Meet discontinuation criteria due to exaggerated response to MA, described below

          4. Nausea severe enough to require treatment.

        Rationale for Subject Selection Criteria:

        Participants are required to have used MA by the smoked or IV route to avoid exposing
        participants to routes of administration that produce more intensive interoceptive effects.
        The age criteria were selected primarily to avoid enrolling participants with undiagnosed
        cardiovascular disease. Participants with active HIV disease are excluded to avoid
        potential exacerbation of their underlying disease; participants with asymptomatic HIV are
        included because this group is at high risk for MA dependence. Participants with asthma (or
        who take asthma medications) are excluded due to potential adverse interactions between
        beta agonist medications and MA.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard De La Garza, II, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Michael E. DeBakey Veterans Affairs Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 20, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 3, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 5, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 12, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 12, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 13, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Richard De La Garza</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Methamphetamine</keyword>
  <keyword>Chantix</keyword>
  <keyword>Varenicline</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Varenicline</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methamphetamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

